<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>A Few Questions about Science Spam</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2012-02-24">
<day>24</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>This was another week with a fair amount of spam in my email inbox.
We all receive email
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20161026234722/http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=anwy2MPT5RE">spam</ext-link>
on a regular basis and most of us have probably also received science
spam: invitations to scientific conferences about topics we are not
working on, invitations to submit articles to journals not covering your
field, and information about lab supplies we never had asked for.
Although I’m of course aware that spam is now a fact of online life, I
don’t quiet understand how this science spam works.</p>
<fig>
  <caption><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20161026234722/http://www.flickr.com/photos/ajc1/519906069/in/photostream/">Flickr
  photo</ext-link> by
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20161026234722/http://scienceoftheinvisible.blogspot.com/">AJ
  Cann</ext-link>.</p></caption>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20161026234722im_/http://farm1.staticflickr.com/206/519906069_de5953764a_m.jpg" xlink:title="" />
</fig>
<p><bold>1. How do science spammers get my email address?</bold>
Most science spam is not really targeted towards my research interests.
From this I conclude that these spammers automatically harvest email
addresses of researchers, or they buy these lists. One potential source
to harvest
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20161026234722/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2011/07/13/did-you-receive-spam-because-you-published-a-paper/">email
addresses is PubMed</ext-link> and other bibliographic databases, but I
don’t know whether this is actually done.</p>
<p><bold>2. Is even a small percentage of researchers responding to this
science spam?</bold>
Science spam is as uninteresting to me as any other spam, and I can’t
really imagine a colleague submitting a manuscript to a journal marketed
this way. But the idea behind spam is that there is a – admittedly very
small – conversion rate.</p>
<p><bold>3. When will we start to see more social media science
spam?</bold>
I think it is only a question of time before we see more science spam on
Twitter, Google+ and Facebook – I already receive a small amount of spam
through these channels.</p>
<p><bold>4. Is there anything an individual researcher can other than
using good spam filters in his email program?</bold>
Would it for example help if we hide our email address as much as
possible? Should we deny publishers the permission to post our email
address in journal articles, and should places like PubMed hide them? Do
publisher organizations such as OASPA (Open Access Scholarly Publishers
Association) enforce their
<bold><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20161026234722/http://www.oaspa.org/conduct.php">Member
Code of Conduct</ext-link>,</bold> which clearly state that a<italic>ny
direct marketing activities publishers engage in shall be appropriate
and unobtrusive.</italic></p>
<p><bold>5. Will it get worse?</bold>
I know this answer. Yes. This blog has seen more than 60,000 spam
comments already, most of the spam in my email is filtered out before I
even see it, but I think it will get much worse – via email and other
channels.</p>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
