<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Announcing the ScienceCard Relaunch</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2012-09-19">
<day>19</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Almost exactly a year ago (in the hackathon of the Science Online
London 2011 conference) I
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20160402053034/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2011/09/28/announcing-sciencecard/">started
the ScienceCard project</ext-link>. ScienceCard is a fork of the Open
Source PLOS Article-Level Metrics (ALM) code, personalizing the
Article-Level Metrics.</p>
<p>A lot has happened in the last 12 months, most importantly that I
started to work for PLOS as technical lead for the Article-Level Metrics
project in May. In July, version 2.0 of the PLOS ALM application was
released, and the code made
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20160402053034/https://github.com/articlemetrics/alm">available
on Github</ext-link>. This not only means that everyone can install his
own ALM application (assuming some familiarity with the Ruby and Rails
web framework), but that we can fork the code and modify it.</p>
<p>Although my focus is now clearly on improving the PLOS application,
it didn’t feel right to shut down the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20160402053034/http://sciencecard.org/">ScienceCard</ext-link>
project. I really like the idea of personalized Article-Level Metrics
(something I spoke about at the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20160402053034/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2012/06/25/random-notes-from-the-altmetrics12-conference/">altmetrics12</ext-link>
conference). So I sat down the last two weekends to upgrade ScienceCard
to the PLOS ALM 2.0 code (the source code of my fork can be found
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20160402053034/https://github.com/mfenner/alm">here</ext-link>).
With the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20160402053034/http://about.orcid.org/content/orcid-launch-plan-announced">imminent
launch</ext-link> of the Open Researcher &amp; Contributor ID (ORCID)
service next month I dropped the functionality to get all articles by a
particular person from Microsoft Academic Search. For now you can add
your articles by DOI or PubMed ID (currently only articles from PubMed),
but you can now also add interesting articles not authored by you. This
makes ScienceCard a nice tool to try out the PLOS ALM code without
installing the software. Please remember that all metrics are collected
in the background, so it can take a few hours until they show up for
newly added articles.</p>
<fig>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20160402053034im_/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/files/2012/09/sciencecard_new-500x312.png" xlink:title="sciencecard_new" />
</fig>
<p>ScienceCard also shows the power of open source software. Open source
doesn’t simply mean free software, it means that you can modify the code
if your requirements are different. For ScienceCard I added
authentication via Twitter (required to add articles, I don’t want to
deal with usernames and passwords), a simple lookup by DOI or PubMed ID
(something not needed if you are publisher of the article and have that
information), and comments and likes. Article-Level Metrics is not about
collecting numbers, it is about capturing the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20160402053034/http://blogs.bmj.com/bmj/2011/04/06/richard-smith-what-is-post-publication-peer-review/">activity
surrounding an article post-publication</ext-link>.</p>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
