<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Announcing ScienceCard</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2011-09-28">
<day>28</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2011</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Metrics for scholarly works are used for evaluation and discovery.
The Journal Impact Factor is widely used, but is not the best tool to
look at the metrics of an individual article. In the past few years we
finally started to have the technology to do article-level metrics
(citations, downloads, etc.) and PLoS has
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120610140041/http://article-level-metrics.plos.org/">pushed
this concept</ext-link> since at least 2009. I first heard about the
PLoS Article-Level Metrics project in a presentation given by Pete
Binfield in July 2009, and a month later I
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120610140041/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2009/08/15/plos_one_interview_with_peter_binfield/">interviewed
him</ext-link> about this project.</p>
<p>Article-level metrics are a major step forward from journal-level
metrics, but I always wanted to extend this concept to authors. Three
events in the past few weeks worked nicely together and made me start an
author-level metrics project myself:
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120610140041/http://dev.mendeley.com/api-binary-battle">programming
contest by Mendeley and PLoS</ext-link> with a September 30 deadline, a
hackfest following the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120610140041/http://www.scienceonlinelondon.org/">Science
Online London Conference</ext-link> in early September, and two
conferences (in
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120610140041/http://irisc-workshop.org/irisc2011-helsinki/">Helsinki</ext-link>
and
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120610140041/http://www.orcid.org/civicrm/event/info?id=2&amp;reset=1">Geneva</ext-link>)
in mid-September discussing the value of unique author identifiers for
researchers.</p>
<fig>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120610140041im_/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/files/2011/09/sciencecard-500x345.jpg" xlink:title="sciencecard" />
</fig>
<p>I’ve taken the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120610140041/http://code.google.com/p/alt-metrics/">Open
Source Article-Level Metrics API Server</ext-link> from PLoS and added a
few important features: metrics by author, additional metrics from
Mendeley and Microsoft Academic Search, and a web-based interface that
less authors register via their Twitter account. The result is
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120610140041/http://sciencecard.org/">ScienceCard</ext-link>,
a website I launched this weekend and today entered for the
Mendeley/PLoS Binary Battle contest. ScienceCard currently uses
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120610140041/http://code.google.com/p/alt-metrics/">Microsoft
Academic Search</ext-link> to find all papers of a particular author,
the next version will allow users to retrieve info about their personal
papers from Mendeley.</p>
<p>Working on ScienceCard has already taught me a lot about the problems
we face when doing metrics for scholarly works. Most problems are social
and not technical. Digital object identifiers (DOIs) for example have
been the standard identifier for journal articles for ten years, but
many places (including PubMed, Microsoft Academic Search and Mendeley)
want users to use their own identifiers for journal articles. This makes
it unnecessarily difficult to find articles and collect metrics.
Identifiers for authors are even more complicated. ScienceCard will of
course use
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120610140041/http://orcid.org/">ORCID</ext-link>
identifiers when they become available in 2012, and I hope that I can
make the transition to ORCID easier for ScienceCard users.</p>
<p>Let me know what you think.</p>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
