<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Annotum: Publishing with WordPress soon coming to a
journal near you</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2011-06-30">
<day>30</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2011</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Last week the first
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611092155/http://annotum.wordpress.com/2011/06/23/alpha-release/">Alpha</ext-link>
version of <bold><bold>Annotum</bold></bold> was released.
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611092155/http://annotum.wordpress.com/about/">Annotum</ext-link>
is “a scholarly authoring and publishing platform based on WordPress”. I
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611092155/http://river-valley.tv/annotem-an-open-source-journal-authoring-and-publishing-platform-based-on-wordpress/">first
learned</ext-link> about Annotum at the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611092155/https://sites.google.com/site/beyondthepdf/">Beyond
the PDF</ext-link> workshop in January. One of the themes of the
workshop was that we need better tools for authoring, reviewing and
publishing of scholarly articles. For many at the workshop it was
obvious that these tools should be web-based, use HTML as the file
format, and should use readily available tools whenever possible.</p>
<p>WordPress is a perfect candidate for such a tool, but needs to be
extended with functions required for scholarly articles: better handling
of citations, figures and tables, support of standard document formats
such as
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611092155/http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/">NLM-DTD</ext-link>,
and support of  a review workflow with co-authors, editors and
reviewers. WordPress can easily be extended with
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611092155/http://wordpress.org/extend/plugins/">plugins</ext-link>,
and a good number of plugins have been released for scholars. A good
starting point are plugins tagged
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611092155/http://wordpress.org/extend/plugins/tags/res-comms">res-comms</ext-link>
and the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611092155/https://groups.google.com/forum/#!forum/wordpress-for-scientists">WordPress
for Scientists</ext-link> Google Group.</p>
<p>There is one problem with these scholarly plugins: none of them
offers a complete solution, and it is sometimes tricky to make them work
with other required plugins or with each other (a particular problem are
plugins that use Javascript). This means that there is currently no
out-of-the-box solution to create, review and publish scholarly content
with WordPress.</p>
<p><bold><bold>Annotum</bold></bold> is an ambitious project that wants
to change this. It helps that Annotum seems to have sufficient funding
and commitment to launch a production version later this year – rather
than being the part-time effort of a single developer. Technically it is
a WordPress theme, and not a plugin. Themes normally are responsible for
the look of a WordPress site, but they can also contain functions
normally found in plugins. Installing a single theme is much easier for
the average WordPress user than installing a number of plugins plus a
theme that works with all plugins. BTW, themes can have child themes, so
this doesn’t mean that all Annotum sites will look the same.</p>
<p>Annotum of course can’t do everything by itself and has to work with
existing plugins (it took me only one hour to
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611092155/http://blogs.xartrials.org/annotum/article/the-mycobacterium-tuberculosis-drugome-and-its-polypharmacological-implications/">make
it work</ext-link> with my
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611092155/http://wordpress.org/extend/plugins/epub-export/">ePub
Export</ext-link> plugin). Annotum’s Carl Leubsdorf is part of the
WordPress for Scientists community and I think he will make sure that
Annotum will work well with the plugins already out there.</p>
<p>I hope that Annotum will not only become a nice out-of-the-box
solution to create a WordPress-based journal or science blog, but will
also be a big stimulus for the budding community of scholarly WordPress
users and developers.</p>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
