<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Are posters worth the effort?</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2008-03-01">
<day>1</day>
<month>3</month>
<year>2008</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Posters are an important tool to communicate your research findings
to a larger audience. The format is different from oral presentations or
full papers, and
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120612094621/http://www.ploscompbiol.org/article/info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.0030102">special
rules</ext-link> for a good poster apply. Posters can be an important
step before a full publication, although many posters will
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120612094621/http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sites/entrez?db=pubmed&amp;uid=17296415">never</ext-link>
be peer-reviewed and published.</p>
<p>The problem with posters is that they are second class citizens to
oral presentations in most meetings. My personal experience with
posters, both my own work and posters from others, has been mixed. In
some meetings the poster presentation was a relaxed event (including
beer and brezels in the last meeting) with good discussions in front of
the poster, but often the poster presentation is not much more than a
trick to increase conference attendance.</p>
<p>A
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120612094621/http://www.aerzteblatt-international.de/int/article.asp?src=search&amp;id=58801">recent
paper</ext-link> (link to english version) in the German journal
<italic><italic>Deutsches</italic> Ä<italic>rzteblatt</italic></italic>
systematically interviewed poster authors and attendees at a German
meeting. This meeting used the format of a moderated poster
presentation. The attendance in the poster presentations was very low,
but was valued by younger scientists and by the moderators. One third of
the posters had already been presented at another meeting, an issues
that touches the problem of duplicate papers that we recently discussed
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120612094621/http://network.nature.com/forums/harvardpublishingforum/954">here</ext-link>
on Nature Network. In
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120612094621/http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sites/entrez?db=pubmed&amp;uid=17296415">another
study</ext-link>, 12% of the posters had already been published as full
paper at the time of the meeting.</p>
<p>In my opinion poster presentations are an important part of every
scientific meeting. They should be taken seriously by using a
competitive peer review process, including the rejection of abstracts
that have already been presented or published. And they should be
allowed enough space and time in the meeting schedule. Maybe we could
also come up with new formats (e.g. this
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120612094621/http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/18246386">video
in poster</ext-link>) that make the poster presentation both fun and
scientifically engaging.</p>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
