<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Are names important?</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2008-02-17">
<day>17</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2008</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>A Nature News article last week talked about the confusion that
happens if a number of authors have the same or similar names
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611110744/http://www.nature.com/news/2008/080213/full/451766a.html">Scientific
publishing: Identity crisis</ext-link>). This is apparently a special
issue in China because of the difficulties transliterating Chinese
characters into English and the use of only a limited number of
surnames. The Nature Nanotechnology – Asia Pacific and Beyond Forum has
a discussion about this topic
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611110744/http://network.nature.com/forums/nnano/939">What's
in an Asian name?</ext-link>).</p>
<p>The difficulties for German authors are much smaller, and this is
probably true for other European languages. We do have a fair number of
surnames, but umlauts in our names (e.g. in the very popular last name
Müller) are frequently lost. As
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611110744/http://network.nature.com/profile/cesarsanchez">Cesar
Sanchez</ext-link> pointed out in the Nature Nanotechnology discussion
mentioned above, Pubmed started using diacritics, including umlauts,
last year
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611110744/http://www.nlm.nih.gov/pubs/techbull/nd07/nd07_diacritics.html">Diacritics
in PubMed Displays and Searching</ext-link>). And the American Physical
Society started to allow Chinese, Japanese and Korean authors to use
names in their own language
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611110744/http://pra.aps.org/PhysRevLett.99.230001">Editorial:
Which Wei Wang?</ext-link>).</p>
<p>But the problem is the same. There are at least 6 different
<italic><italic>M. Fenner</italic></italic> in the MEDLINE database, one
of them my cousin. Using the middle initial can help. I try to publish
as <italic><italic>MH Fenner</italic></italic>, and very smart people
will figure out that papers written by <italic><italic>H
Fenner</italic></italic> are from my father. And what happens when you
marry? My wife and I have different last names (which is uncommon in
Germany) and one small reason was the scientific track record (including
publications) connected to this name. Some of the other issues are
nicely summarized in a PLOS post by Richard Cave
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611110744/http://www.plos.org/cms/node/133">Unique
Author Identification</ext-link>, thanks Cesar Sanchez).</p>
<p>The solution? We need unique identifiers for authors. I recently
wrote about
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611110744/http://network.nature.com/blogs/user/mfenner/2008/01/21/thomson-scientific-launches-researcherid-to-uniquely-identify-authors">ResearcherID</ext-link>,
one such effort announced this January by Thomson Scientific. The
problem with ResearcherID is that author identity is a very sensitive
issue and many people will be reluctant to rely on a private company for
that. Elsevier is doing something similar in their Scopus database
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611110744/http://info.scopus.com/etc/authoridentifier/">The
Scopus Author Identifier</ext-link>).</p>
<p>Author identifiers should really come from a neutral organization
such as CrossRef (a publishing organization that brought us the DOI to
uniquely identify a scientific paper). They held a meeting with various
interested parties in February 2007
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611110744/http://www.crossref.org/CrossTech/2007/02/crossref_author_id_meeting.html">CrossRef
Author ID meeting</ext-link>). Because of the number of parties involved
and the different issues, this is a very slow process. And what is the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611110744/http://www.nlm.nih.gov/">U.S.
Library of Medicine</ext-link> doing on this issue? After all, they
publish MEDLINE, the most important database of biomedical research.</p>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
