<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Article downloads and citations of open access
papers</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2008-08-01">
<day>1</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2008</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>The <italic><italic>British Medical Journal</italic></italic> this
week published
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611040451/http://www.bmj.com/cgi/content/full/337/jul31_1/a568">Open
access publishing, article downloads, and citations: randomised
controlled trial</ext-link> by Phlip Davis et al. There are already
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611040451/http://biology.plosjournals.org/perlserv/?request=get-document&amp;doi=10.1371%2Fjournal.pbio.0040157">several
publications</ext-link> that looked at the full paper downloads and
citations of open access papers compared to closed access papers. But
this is the first prospectively randomized study, thus avoiding some of
the typical problems of retrospective evaluations (e.g. that important
papers are more likely to have free access).</p>
<p>Articles published in 11
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611040451/http://www.the-aps.org/">American
Physiological Society</ext-link> journals between January and April 2007
were randomly (1 out of 7) made open access at the time of publication.
Full text viewing, PDF downloads and citations were measured over a 12
month period. The authors found a significant increase in readership
(full text HTML and PDF) but no difference in citation rates.</p>
<p>There are plausible arguments why citation rates weren't different
between the two groups. Most researchers that cite APS papers in their
own publications will have institutional access to these journals. But
citation rates of open access papers are a political topic, that's why
we already have a number of reactions from the blogosphere (e.g. from
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611040451/http://scholarlykitchen.sspnet.org/2008/07/31/open-access-doesnt-drive-citations/">The
Scholarly Kitchen</ext-link>,
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611040451/http://openaccess.eprints.org/index.php?%2Farchives%2F441-Davis-et-als-1-year-Study-of-Self-Selection-Bias-No-Self-Archiving-Control%2C-No-OA-Effect%2C-No-Conclusion.html">Stevan
Harnard</ext-link> and
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611040451/http://gunther-eysenbach.blogspot.com/">Gunther
Eysenbach</ext-link>). There are also some
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611040451/http://www.bmj.com/cgi/eletters/337/jul31_1/a568">direct
responses</ext-link> to the paper at the BMJ website. The main criticism
of the paper is the short time of 12 months to look at the citation
rate. The citations will increase in the next few years, but because all
papers from APS journals are made available as full text after 12
months, there will be no longer a difference in access to the two groups
of papers.</p>
<p>What surprised me post about the paper is the journal. I would have
expected that it would appear in an APS journal, but a medical journal?
The
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611040451/http://www.bmj.com/cgi/content/extract/337/jul31_1/a1051">editorial</ext-link>
explains the reasoning behind it. Like many other journals, the BMJ is
trying out new access models. All research papers (but not the other
content, including the editorial) in the BMJ are open access. And as
Fiona Godlee in the editorial puts it:</p>
<p specific-use="wrapper">
  <disp-quote>
    <p><italic><italic>Academic publishing is going through interesting
    times. We don</italic>'<italic>t know which model will prevail, or
    indeed whether there will ultimately be one or several coexisting
    models.</italic></italic></p>
  </disp-quote>
</p>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
