<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Auto generating links to data and
resources</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2013-07-02">
<day>2</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>A few weeks ago Kafkas et al. (2013) published a paper looking at
current patterns of how datasets o biological databases are cited in
research articles, based on an analysis of the full text Open Access
articles available from Europe PMC. They identified data ctiations
by:</p>
<list list-type="order">
  <list-item>
    <p>Accession numbers available in articles as publisher-supplied,
    structured content;</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>Accession numbers identified in articles by text mining;</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>References to articles from the ENA, UniProt and PDBe
    records.</p>
  </list-item>
</list>
<p>They could show that text mining doubles the number of structured
annotations available in journal articles (from 2.26% to 5.15%), and
that these structured annotations should be extended beyond the ENA,
UniProt and PDB identifiers that their analysis focused on. ENA
identifiers (for nucleotide sequences in GenBank, EMBL or DDBJ) make up
the largest group, with 160,112 identifiers found in the 410,364
articles that were analyzed.</p>
<fig>
  <caption><p><bold>Database Citation in Full Text Biomedical
  Articles</bold>. Fig. 3 from <milestone-start />(Kafkas et al.,
  2013)<milestone-end />.</p></caption>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="http://blog.martinfenner.org/images/journal.pone.0063184.g003.png" xlink:title="" />
</fig>
<p>Another result in the paper is that references to articles in these
databases show little overlap with database links found in articles. One
of the conclusions drawn by the author is that</p>
<p specific-use="wrapper">
  <disp-quote>
    <p>Text-mining can be used to extend structured data citation, and
    could be a basis for the development of services to help authors or
    editors to add structured content at the beginning of the
    publication process, rather than after the fact.</p>
  </disp-quote>
</p>
<p>Adding structured data citations during the authoring phase of a
manuscript requires tools that make this process easier, providing
auto-linking and verification of the without requiring extra input from
the author. Scholarly Markdown is an ideal platform for these tools, as
it is easier to extend than traditional word processors such as
Microsoft Word. During a small workshop around persistent identifiers
for data
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://datacite.org/">DataCite</ext-link>),
people
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://orcid.org/">ORCID</ext-link>)
and geological samples
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.geosamples.org/igsnabout">IGSN</ext-link>)
that took place yesterday and today at the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.gfz-potsdam.de/portal/gfz/cegit">GFZ
Potsdam</ext-link> I worked on a tool that does auto-linking for these
identifiers:</p>
<list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
    <p>IGSN.
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.geosamples.org/igsnabout">International
    Geosample Number</ext-link></p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>MGI identifiers for genetically modified mouse strains in the
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.findmice.org/about">Internal
    Mouse Strain Resource</ext-link></p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>ENA.
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/ena/about/about">Genbank
    / ENA / DDBJ nucleotide sequences</ext-link></p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>UniProt protein sequences from the
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.uniprot.org/help/about">UniProt
    database</ext-link></p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>PDB.
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.rcsb.org/pdb/static.do?p=home/faq.html">Protein
    Data Bank protein structure information</ext-link></p>
  </list-item>
</list>
<p>The list includes the IGSN, the database identifiers studied by
Kafkas et al (2013), and the MGI identifier for genetically altered
mice. In the life sciences there is a long tradition - and requirement
by journals - to use database identifiers for data, but identifiers for
resources such as genetically modified mice are unfortunately not in
common use.</p>
<p>This blog uses the Pandoc markdown processor and the Jekyll static
website generator. The easiest way to implement this functionality was
by writing a filter for the liquid templating engine used by Jekyll, and
provide this filter as a Jekyll plugin. The Jekyll plugin can be found
at
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/mfenner/jekyll-scholmd">mfenner/jekyll-scholmd</ext-link>.
The plugin expects the name of the identifier, followed by a colon and
optional space, followed by the identifier:</p>
<preformat>GenBank:  M10090
IGSN:  JRH964436
MGI:  96922
UniProt:  P02144
PDB:  1mbn</preformat>
<p>This input is automatically translated into
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/ena/data/view/M10090">GenBank:M10090</ext-link>,
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hdl.handle.net/10273/JRH964436">IGSN:JRH964436</ext-link>,
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.findmice.org/summary?gaccid/96922">MGI:96922</ext-link>,
and information about the human myoglobin protein
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.uniprot.org/uniprot/P02144">UniProt:P02144</ext-link>,
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.rcsb.org/pdb/explore/explore.do?structureId=1mbn">PDB:1mbn</ext-link>)
is generated in a similar fashion.</p>
<p>The plugin was written in a few hours today, and is my first Jekyll
plugin. There is room for improvement, e.g. support for more
identifiers, better regex matching, validation of the resulting links,
and automated tag generation if an identifier is found. Ideally the
auto-linking should happen in the markdown and not the HTML output, so
that these structured database links are also available in other
markdown outputs such as PDF. But this is another example how Scholarly
Markdown can make it easier for researchers to author documents without
requiring a fancy web-based user interface.</p>
<sec id="references">
  <title>References</title>
  <p>Kafkas, Ş., Kim, J.-H., &amp; McEntyre, J. R. (2013). Database
  Citation in Full Text Biomedical Articles. <italic>PLoS ONE</italic>.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0063184">doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0063184</ext-link></p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
