<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Automatically list all your publications in your
blog</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2013-08-04">
<day>4</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>A common feature of blogs written by scientists is a listing of all
their publications. Publication lists are a great way to provide
background information about your research. Publication lists should
provide links to the fulltext versions of these publications, should be
nicely formatted - e.g. using a common citation style such as APA - and
should be easy to maintain. A number of tools for a variety of blogging
platforms (including Wordpress and Jekyll) are available to help with
this task, but maintaining the list of publications has remained
difficult.</p>
<p>Publication lists are best maintained in a system built for this
purpose. This could be either a reference manager, or a profile page in
a social network for scientists. Even better suited for this task is
your Open Researcher &amp; Contributor ID
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://orcid.org/">ORCID</ext-link>)
profile, as this service (<bold><bold>???</bold></bold>) directly
integrates with a number of bibliographic databases and makes the
profile information available via an open API.</p>
<sec id="orcid-feed">
  <title>ORCID Feed</title>
  <p>Last week I have started work on
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://feed.labs.orcid-eu.org/">ORCID
  Feed</ext-link>, a service that reformats the API response from ORCID
  into RSS, bibtex and formattted citations, making it easier for
  scientists to reuse the content stored in their ORCID profile. This
  service is still experimental, so please report any issues
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/orcid-eu-labs/orcid-feed/issues">here</ext-link>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="jekyll-orcid">
  <title>jekyll-orcid</title>
  <p>I have now added the final piece to automatically import my
  publications into this blog.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/mfenner/jekyll-orcid">jekyll-orcid</ext-link>
  is a Jekyll plugin that automatically downloads all my publications
  from my ORCID profile via <bold><bold>ORCID Feed</bold></bold> and
  stores them in a subfolder of this blog, both in bibtex and Citeproc
  JSON format. It does this every time you regenerate your blog, so that
  the publication list will be automatically updated with new content. I
  can then use
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/inukshuk/jekyll-scholar">jekyll-scholar</ext-link>,
  a popular Jekyll plugin written by Sylvester Keil to generate a
  bibliography (<monospace>jekyll-orcid</monospace> automatically adds a
  YAML frontmatter section to the files so that jekyll-scholar can
  process it). I can format this auto-generated bibliography in a
  variety of ways - you can see the result in my
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://blog.martinfenner.org/about.html">About</ext-link>
  page where I also provide a download link of the bibtex file.</p>
  <p>My publications are of course also available if I want to cite them
  in the text, e.g. our recent publication summarizing the main findings
  from the 2011 European Consensus Conference on germ-cell cancer
  (<bold><bold>???</bold></bold>), or last year’s case report on liver
  toxicity induced by the cancer drug imatinib
  (<bold><bold>???</bold></bold>).</p>
  <p>Similar tools also exist for Wordpress, e.g.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://wordpress.org/plugins/papercite/">Papercite</ext-link>,
  which can import the bibtex file directly from ORCID Feed.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="next">
  <title>Next</title>
  <p>Now there is only one step missing to have your paper that was just
  published automatically appear in your publication list. Assuming you
  have provided your ORCID identifier when you submitted the paper, and
  the publisher has included your ORCID identifier in the metadata sent
  to CrossRef (both are already common practices), we only need CrossRef
  to automatically push that paper into your ORCID profile.</p>
  <p>And once we have this workflow in place, we can automatically add
  additional information, including links to the fulltext paper in the
  institutional repository, copyright information, and metrics.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="references">
  <title>References</title>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
