<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Beyond the PDF … is ePub</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2011-01-23">
<day>23</day>
<month>1</month>
<year>2011</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Having breakfast at the end of a conference is a good way to recap
what was discussed and can help to generate new ideas. Two years ago at
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120628140912/http://scienceonline09.com/">ScienceOnline09</ext-link>
a conversation with Cameron Neylon that followed up on the session
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120628140912/http://precedings.nature.com/documents/2801/version/1/html">Reputation,
authority and incentives. Or: How to get rid of the Impact
Factor</ext-link> (moderated by Björn Brembs and Pete Binfield) was
started my interest in unique author identifiers for researchers. An
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://blog.martinfenner.org/posts/nterview_with_geoffrey_bilder/">interview
with Geoff Bilder</ext-link> about author identifiers and the CrossRef
Contributor ID project followed a month later – still one of my favorite
blog posts. I have since become deeply involved with author identifiers
and have joined the Board of the Open Researcher &amp; Contributor ID
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120628140912/http://www.orcid.org/">ORCID</ext-link>)
initiative last September.</p>
<fig>
  <caption><p><italic><italic>Beyond the PDF group photo my
  lesliekwchan, on Flickr</italic></italic></p></caption>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120628140912im_/http://farm6.static.flickr.com/5010/5376544624_9914bebffa.jpg" xlink:title="" />
</fig>
<p>Wednesday to Friday I attended the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120628140912/https://sites.google.com/site/beyondthepdf/">Beyond
the PDF</ext-link> workshop in San Diego to discuss how we can do better
in scholarly publishing. The limitations of the PDF format were just one
topic, the main themes were annotation, data, provenance, new models,
writing and reviewing and impact. This is my presentation:</p>
<p>We had two very productive breakout sessions about writing and
reading tools, and we agreed that we should
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120628140912/https://sites.google.com/site/beyondthepdf/home/program-draft/notes-from-the-breakout">build
something that makes it much easier to describe and distribute our
research data</ext-link>. Most people in the group took a very pragmatic
approach and want to build simple tools appropriate for small research
groups in the next few months. We thought that graduate students would
be good early adopters, and we already have three principal
investigators willing to test these tools in their labs.</p>
<fig>
  <caption><p><italic><italic>Our first prototype, as drawn by Peter
  Murray Rust</italic></italic></p></caption>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120628140912im_/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/files/2011/01/BTPDFdiagram-500x373.jpg" xlink:title="BTPDFdiagram" />
</fig>
<p>Peter Sefton demonstrated his
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120628140912/http://fascinator-demo.com/portal/default/search">Fascinator</ext-link>
tool that already has a lot of the required functionality. But it was
the breakfast discussion before departing – again with Cameron Neylon,
but this time also including Peter Murray Rust, Peter Sefton and Ana
Nelson – that helped me to put all my thoughts into place.</p>
<p specific-use="wrapper">
  <disp-quote>
    <p>ePub should become the standard document format for authoring,
    distributing and reading scholarly content.</p>
  </disp-quote>
</p>
<p>The
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120628140912/http://www.idpf.org/">ePub
format</ext-link> uses a collection of files held together in a zip
archive. Content is displayed using a combination of XHTML and CSS – not
different from web pages – and the ePub can also contain other files.
Journal publishers use XML internally, and it is therefore easy to
distribute journal articles in ePub format –
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120628140912/http://www.hindawi.com/epub.html">some
of them</ext-link> are already doing this routinely. ePub has several
advantages over PDF, including:</p>
<list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
    <p>ePub can be used for all steps in the creation of a scholarly
    document, including data collection, authoring, annotating and peer
    review. There is no need for time-consuming and expensive format
    conversions. Currently most manuscripts are submitted in Microsoft
    Word or LateX formats, and then converted first to XML and then to
    HTML and PDF. Metadata such as author identifiers, digital object
    identifiers and semantic information can be added early on and don’t
    get lost in a format conversion.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>ePub makes it easy to include supplementary material, e.g. video
    and other multimedia content, the datasets used in the publication
    (particularly the data used for tables and figures), all cited
    references in BibTeX format, etc.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>ePub is much better suited for reading on mobile devices, as the
    format allows reflowing of content. Most articles today are printed
    from the PDF and then read, but this behavior is
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120628140912/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2010/01/10/how_do_you_read_papers_2010_will_be_different/">rapidly
    changing</ext-link>.</p>
  </list-item>
</list>
<p>ePub is relatively new, and not many applications for scientists
already support this format. We want lab equipment that stores its data
in ePub, lab notebooks that write all files from an experiment into an
ePub file, reference managers that store and display papers in ePub
format, authoring tools that import all these ePub files and thus make
it much easier to write, annotate and submit a manuscript, and journal
submission systems that take ePub files. I have
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120628140912/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2010/12/28/wordpress-for-reference-management/">written
a lot about WordPress</ext-link> recently and this is of course a
platform that would play nicely with ePub. At least two WordPress
plugins
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120628140912/http://wordpress.org/extend/plugins/tags/epub">support
ePub</ext-link>, and it should be possible to modify them to the
requirements of the scholarly paper.</p>
<fig>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120628140912im_/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/files/2011/01/epub-500x199.jpg" xlink:title="epub" />
</fig>
<p>Almost as important as the document format is the distribution
mechanism of these ePub files. We need a system that makes it easy to
collaborate on a document, and that includes version control. The
simplest solution would of course be centralized and web-based, but I’m
not sure that this is a realistic scenario. We talked a lot about
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120628140912/http://www.dropbox.com/">Dropbox</ext-link>
during the meeting, but a solution using git (and
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120628140912/https://github.com/">github</ext-link>),
Amazon
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120628140912/http://aws.amazon.com/s3/">Simple
Storage Service</ext-link>,
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120628140912/http://explore.live.com/windows-live-skydrive">Windows
Live SkyDrive</ext-link> or the repository software ePrints or DSpace is
also possible. As an ePub document can contain all required documents,
the submission of a manuscript to a journal or institutional repository
could become as simple as uploading a single file, and all the peer
review (including reviewer comments and revisions) could be done with
that file. Submissions of datasets to databases such as
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120628140912/http://datadryad.org/about">Dryad</ext-link>
could of course also be done using ePub files. A versioned distribution
system should also make it easier to automatically get information about
corrections or retractions (e.g. using the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120628140912/http://www.crossref.org/crossmark.html">CrossMark</ext-link>
system that will launch in 2011), and to receive regular updates of
article-level metrics, including new citations of the article or
dataset.</p>
<p>Several of us attending the meeting will continue the discussion in
the coming weeks, and I hope I can convince them of the advantages of
ePub. It shouldn’t take us more than a month or two to produce a nice
ePub of the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120628140912/http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000976">sample
PLoS Computational Biology article</ext-link> provided for the Beyond
the PDF workshop. The next <bold><bold>Science Online London
Conference</bold></bold> will be September 2-3 at the British Library.
This is a good opportunity to discuss the progress of this project,
ideally including reports about new ePub tools for scientists, more
journals using ePub for their articles, and practical feedback from the
first users.</p>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
