<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Book Review: Cognitive Surplus by Clay
Shirky</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2010-08-14">
<day>14</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2010</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>In his new book <italic><italic>Cognitive Surplus</italic></italic>
Clay Shirky argues that in the last 50 years many of those living in
industrialized countries have seen a dramatic increase in free time,
paired with better education and a higher standard of living. But a very
large part of that free time or cognitive surplus is now routinely used
to watch television, a passive activity that makes us a consumer rather
than a participant. In a trend that is also true for other media (eg.
music), we have seen a shift away from participation (usually on an
amateur level) towards consuming professionally produced media
content.</p>
<p>In the last few years we have seen a dramatic change in Internet
technologies that now make it extremely easy for everybody to produce
content and distribute it on the Internet (e.g. Wikipedia, blogs, photos
on Flickr, or YouTube videos) something we usually call Web 2.0 or
social media. Clay Shirky contrasts the time that users spend editing
<italic><italic>Wikipedia</italic></italic> (or other social media
activities) with the hours we typically watch television to kill the
argument that most of us would have no time for social media.</p>
<p>The combination of increased free time and social media is creating a
lot of interesting collaborative projects, and the book is full of
interesting examples. Clay Shirky stresses that social media only enable
new uses of the cognitive surplus, it is how they are used that decides
whether we create personal, communal, public or civic values. He uses
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120524201437/http://www.icanhazcheeseburger.com/">ICanHazCheeseburger</ext-link>
(a popular website that shows cute pictures of cats with cute captions)
as an example for communal value, the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120524201437/http://www.apache.org/">Apache
Webserver</ext-link> Open Source software project as an example of
public value, and
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120524201437/http://www.ushahidi.com/">Ushahidi.com</ext-link>
(a site started to allow citizens to track outbreaks of ethnic violence
in Kenya) as an example of civic value.</p>
<p>Social media in the context of science and medicine are discussed
briefly in the book. Clay Shirky describes the <italic><italic>Invisible
College</italic></italic>, a group formed around 1645 in London by
Robert Boyle, Robert Hooke and others that established many of the
principles of conducting science that are still valid today (test every
hypothesis with experiments, describe experiments detailed enough so
that they could be reproduced, etc.). The group formed the core of what
a little later became the <italic><italic>Royal
Society</italic></italic>. Clay Shirky argues that the collaborative
nature of how science was conducted by the Invisible College lead to a
dramatic increase in our scientific knowledge and contrasts this with
how alchemy was performed at the time (reclusive and secretive).</p>
<p>Clay Shirky also talks about
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120524201437/http://www.patientslikeme.com/">PatientsLikeMe.com</ext-link>,
a site that allows patients with chronic diseases to share their health
information, both for personal advice, but also as participants in
clinical trials. Patients Like Me only works because patients are
willing to share their personal healthcare information, and that is a
cultural shift from the strict privacy that usually surrounds
information about your personal health. Patients participating in
Patients Like Me obviously think that the benefits from sharing their
personal healthcare information outweigh the risks.</p>
<p>Cognitive Surplus is very entertaining reading, and on almost every
page Clay Shirky gives us food for thought that will keep us busy for
days or weeks. The book is required reading for everybody who is
interested in how social media are changing the way we consume,
communicate, and conduct science. After finishing the book, you will no
longer think that the scientific article of the future is primarily
about integration of video or other multimedia, intelligent navigation,
or display on mobile devices. The successful journals of the future will
be those that work hardest in facilitating collaboration among
scientists, and this requires cultural changes as much as it requires
technological changes.</p>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
