<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Books about scientific writing</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2007-09-30">
<day>30</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2007</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Last weekend I visited my brother-in-law in Cambridge (UK). In the
Cambridge University Press bookstore I found the wonderful little book
<italic><italic>How to Write and Illustrate a Scientific
Paper</italic></italic> by Björn Gustavii
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611101312/http://www.cambridge.org/catalogue/catalogue.asp?isbn=9780521823234">Cambridge
University Press 2003</ext-link>). On less than 150 pages B. Gustavii
gives a good summary of the typical problems and their solutions. He
encourages the reader to avoid unnecessary verbosity, use the active
voice more often, draw less complicated charts and to be very careful
with statistics.</p>
<p>A few years ago I bought an old copy of <italic><italic>Scientific
Writing</italic></italic> by Lester S. King and Charles G. Roland
(Journal of the American Medical Association 1968). King and Roland
encourage the reader to avoid unnecessary verbosity and use the active
voice more often (they don't talk much about graphs and statistics).
Scientific writing seemed to have almost the same problems 40 years ago.
This raises two interesting questions:</p>
<list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
    <p>Could the writing of the average scientific paper be improved and
    are we in need of these books?</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>Does the quality of the writing help in getting a paper accepted?
    In other words, should I make the effort and improve my writing
    skills or should I rather do experiments?</p>
  </list-item>
</list>
<p>Journal editors can probably better answer these questions. My guess
would be that most people would answer these questions with
<italic><italic>yes</italic></italic> and
<italic><italic>no</italic></italic>. So we will continue to struggle
with our writing skills, especially those of us who learned English as a
second language, but it will not be that important in our career. I
therefore rather list some other books about scientific writing that I
own and can recommend:</p>
<list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
    <p><italic><italic>Medical Writing: a Prescription for
    Clarity</italic></italic> by Neville W. Goodman and Martin B.
    Edwards (Cambridge University Press 2006). Very detailed
    instructions about the use of the language. Includes many examples
    of bad scientific writing and suggestions for better
    alternatives.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p><italic><italic>The Elements of Style</italic></italic> by
    William Strunk Jr. and E.B. White (Logman 2000). The classic text
    from the beginning of the 20th century, not specific to scientific
    writing.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p><italic><italic>The Visual Display of Quantitative
    Information</italic></italic> by Edward R. Tufte (Graphics Press
    2001). Another classic text and a beautiful book.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p><italic><italic>Clinical Epidemiology</italic></italic> by R.
    Brian Haynes, David L. Sackett, Gordon H. Guyatt and Peter Tugwell
    (Lippincott 2006). This epidemiology/statistics textbook has a small
    chapter about scientific writing. More importantly, it is very
    helpful in how to read a scientific paper and the statistics behind
    it.</p>
  </list-item>
</list>
<p>And I finish with an example for good scientific writing that is used
a lot in the books mentioned above:</p>
<p specific-use="wrapper">
  <disp-quote>
    <p>We wish to suggest a structure for the salt of deoxyribose
    nucleic acid (D.N.A.). This structure has novel features which are
    of considerable biological interest…</p>
  </disp-quote>
</p>
<p>This is of course the opening paragraph of the 1953
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611101312/http://www.nature.com/nature/dna50/watsoncrick.pdf">Nature
paper</ext-link> by Watson and Crick. Which brings us back to
Cambridge…</p>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
