<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Book Review: Visualize This by Nathan Yau</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2011-08-13">
<day>13</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2011</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>In July Wiley published the book
<bold><bold><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611111645/http://book.flowingdata.com/">Visualize
This – The Flowing Data Guide to Design, Visualization and
Statistics</ext-link></bold></bold>. The book is written by
<italic><italic>Nathan Yau</italic></italic>, and he is of course also
behind the popular
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611111645/http://flowingdata.com/">FlowingData</ext-link>
blog about the same topic. This is a short review of the book.</p>
<fig>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611111645im_/http://book.flowingdata.com/images/visualize-this-drop.png" xlink:title="Visualize This" />
</fig>
<p>Please keep in mind that I’m no expert in data visualization. The
book is written for people like me, an expert in the topic will probably
look at the book differently.</p>
<p>And the book is intended as an introduction to important concepts. It
is probably the wrong book if you are interested in using a particular
tool – e.g. Adobe Illustrator, R or Flash – for Data Visualization.</p>
<p>The examples in the book are about topics similar to those used in
the FlowingData blog, most of them are about data journalism. This is
not a book about visualization of scientific experiments.</p>
<p>The first chapter of the book talks about how to tell stories with
data. This is a very important chapter, as learning how to tell a good
story is more important than knowing all the details on how to use a
tool for visualization.</p>
<p>Nathan continues with a chapter on how to find and format data for
data visualization. We are then introduced to a number of important
visualization tools, and their particular strengths. Nathan uses a large
number of tools in the book, but seems to particularly like Python for
formatting data, R for for calculation and visualization, and Adobe
Illustrator for perfecting the result for publication. This is one of
the take-home messages of the book for me: instead of perfecting the use
of one particular tool, learn to decide what works best for a particular
problem. R and Illustrator are a good start for most problems.</p>
<p>The next few chapters look at visualizations in different contexts:
patterns over time, proportions, relationships, differences and spatial
relationships. All chapters are written with examples that you can
follow along, and with enough basic information that you can start
solving similar problems on your own. Below is a chart I tried myself
after reading the book. It looks at the number of member organizations
of the non-profit ORCID over time (more info
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611111645/http://www.orcid.org/news/250-participating-organizations-have-joined-orcid">here</ext-link>).</p>
<fig>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611111645im_/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/files/2011/08/orcid-500x400.png" xlink:title="orcid" />
</fig>
<p>I can highly recommend <bold><bold>Visualize This</bold></bold> to
anybody interested in learning about data visualization. I found only
two things I didn’t like. I wish Nathan had spent more time explaining
how a data graph can be improved visually. In many examples he shows how
small changes in color or font size can make a big difference in
presentation, but I would prefer to see a more systematic approach to
this important topic. I wouldn’t mind if he would drop the chapter on
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611111645/http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chernoff_face">Chernoff
faces</ext-link> instead – fun stuff, but not really important in an
introductory text.</p>
<p>My other problem is with the publisher. I read the book as ePub on my
iPad. It is nice to have weblinks you can click in the text, but it
would have been even nicer if the ePub had ben prepared with a little
bit more care. Most images in the text (there are many) are too small –
in an ePub you expect figures to enlarge and show more detail when you
click on them. And figure headings were regularly orphaned (on a
different page than the figure itself). ePub is an evolving standard,
but a little bit of consideration for typography and layout would go a
long way.</p>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
