<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Build Roads not Stagecoaches</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2014-07-18">
<day>18</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2014</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>I attended the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://2014.okfestival.org/">Open
Knowledge Festival</ext-link> this week and I had a blast. For three
days (I also attended the fringe event
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://csvconf.com/">csv,conf</ext-link>
on Tuesday) I listed to wonderful presentations and was involved in
great discussions - both within sessions, but more importantly all the
informal discussions between and after sessions.</p>
<fig>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://martinfenner.ghost.io/images/okfest-2014-logo.png" xlink:title="" />
</fig>
<p>Of all the things that were discussed I want to pick one theme that
resonated in particular with me. It surfaced in many places, but was
articulated particularly well by
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://twitter.com/erichysen">Eric
Hysen</ext-link> - who heads the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.google.com/elections/ed/us">Google
Politics &amp; Elections Group</ext-link> - in his keynote yesterday
(starting at 54:52, but please also watch the keynote by Neelie Kroes,
Vice-President of the European Commission):</p>
<boxed-text>
  <boxed-text id="player">
  </boxed-text>
  <sec id="an-error-occurred.">
    <title>An error occurred.</title>
    <boxed-text>
      <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0UNRZEsLxKc">Sieh
      dir dieses Video auf www.youtube.com an</ext-link> oder aktiviere
      JavaScript, falls es in deinem Browser deaktiviert sein
      sollte.</p>
    </boxed-text>
  </sec>
</boxed-text>
<p>In his keynote he described how travel from Cambridge to London in
the 18th and early 19th century improved mainly as a result of better
roads, made possible by changes in how these roads are financed.
Translated to today, he urged the audience to think more about the
infrastructure and less about the end products:</p>
<p specific-use="wrapper">
  <disp-quote>
    <p>Ecosystems, not apps – Eric Hysen</p>
  </disp-quote>
</p>
<p>On Tuesday at
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://csvconf.com/#nickstenning">csv,conf</ext-link>,
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://twitter.com/nickstenning">Nick
Stenning</ext-link> - Technical Director of the Open Knowledge
Foundation - talked about
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dataprotocols.org/data-packages/">data
packages</ext-link>, an evolving standard to describe data that are
passed around betwen different systems. He used the metaphor of
containers, and how they have dramatically changed the transportation of
goods in the last 50 years. He
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/nickstenning/put-it-in-a-box">argued</ext-link>
that the cost of shipping was in large part determined by the cost of
loading and unloading, and the container has dramatically changed that
equation. We are in a very similar situation with datasets, where most
of the time is spent translating between different formats, joining
things together that use different names for the same thing, etc.</p>
<fig>
  <caption><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Hafenarbeiter_bei_der_Verladung_von_Sackgut_-_MS_Rothenstein_NDL,_Port_Sudan_1960.png">Wikimedia
  Commons</ext-link> image used in
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/nickstenning/put-it-in-a-box">Nick
  Stelling's presentation</ext-link></p></caption>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://martinfenner.ghost.io/content/images/2021/01/640px-Hafenarbeiter_bei_der_Verladung_von_Sackgut_-_MS_Rothenstein_NDL-_Port_Sudan_1960.png" xlink:title="" />
</fig>
<p>What the two presentations have in common is not only that they link
the building of an open digital infrastructure to important transforming
events in the history of transportation, but also the emphasis on the
building blocks rather than the finished product. When I thought more
about this I realized that these building blocks are exactly the
projects I get most excited about, i.e. projects that develop standards
or provide APIs or libraries. Some examples would be</p>
<list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
    <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://orcid.org/">ORCID</ext-link>:
    unique identifiers for scholarly authors</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://citationstyles.org/">Citation
    Style Language</ext-link>: a language to describe the formatting of
    citations and bibliographies</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/jgm/pandoc">Pandoc</ext-link>:
    a universal document converter</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ropensci.org/">rOpenSci</ext-link>:
    packages for the statistical programming language R to access data
    repositories</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.niso.org/topics/tl/altmetrics_initiative/">NISO
    Alternative Assessment Metrics</ext-link>: standards and best
    practices for novel scholarly metrics</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.re3data.org/">re3data</ext-link>:
    a registry of research data repositories</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/">Creative
    Commons</ext-link>: copyright licenses for creative works</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/articlemetrics/alm">ALM</ext-link>:
    software to collect comprehensive information about the discussion
    of scholarly articles on the web</p>
  </list-item>
</list>
<p>This list doesn’t include all the generic software needed to build
open science tools, with <bold>git</bold> being a perfect example. The
last project is obviously the project I have been working on the past
two years for PLOS, but I have tried to support the other projects
mentioned in various ways from small code contributions to promotion via
this blog and presentations, or direct work in these projects. But
strangely enough, I haven’t really realized this until now.</p>
<p>Not surprisingly infrastructure, servers, libraries and other
building blocks are exactly the areas where open source software has
been most successful so far, and this is of course a core part of the
UNIX philosophy of building parts that work well together rather than
big monolithic programs that do everything.</p>
<sec id="next">
  <title>Next</title>
  <p>We need more <bold><bold>Open Science Infrastructure</bold></bold>
  and it is the stuff that I really care about. I think we need to
  better support those projects that build these essential building
  blocks via advice, cooperation, promotion, and financial support. I am
  willing to help with that effort, and I have started to think how I
  can best contribute.</p>
  <p>On the other hand there are many great open science projects that
  don’t fall in this category, maybe even the majority of them. I wish
  them good luck, but I would advice them to think more about
  infrastructure, and whether there is a small area where they can focus
  on. It still amazes me how successful projects such as
  <bold><bold>Citation Style Language</bold></bold> and
  <bold><bold>Pandoc</bold></bold> have been with no or almost no
  funding and a very small core group of people doing the majority of
  the work. One critical ingredient is the total focus on a very
  specific problem that is both important and can be solved with
  specific actions. Too many open science projects want to solve too
  many problems at once, try to solve the exact same problems that many
  other parallel projects work on, don’t cooperate enough with those
  parallel projects, and require a critical mass of users to work.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
