<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Citation Style Language: An Interview with Rintze Zelle
and Ian Mulvany</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2010-09-24">
<day>24</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2010</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Citation styles are one of the greater mysteries for the novice
manuscript writer. There are numerous ways that authors, title, journal,
etc. can be arranged and formatted (see examples below), and in
bibliographies citations can be ordered either alphabetically or by
order of appearance in the text.</p>
<p><bold><bold>Laemmli UK</bold></bold>. Cleavage of Structural Proteins
during the Assembly of the Head of Bacteriophage T4.
<italic><italic>Nature</italic></italic>. 1970;227:680-685.</p>
<p><bold><bold>U. K. Laemmli</bold></bold> (1970). ‘Cleavage of
Structural Proteins during the Assembly of the Head of Bacteriophage
T4′. <italic><italic>Nature</italic></italic>
<bold><bold>227</bold></bold>(5259):680-685.</p>
<p><bold><bold>U. K. Laemmli</bold></bold>,
<italic><italic>Nature</italic></italic> <bold><bold>227</bold></bold>,
680 (1970).</p>
<p>Because of this complexity, it has long become impractical to format
citations manually, and formatting of citations and bibliographies is
one of the main reasons for using reference management software. I
interviewed Rintze Zelle (scientist and open source contributor) and Ian
Mulvany (vice president of new product development at Mendeley) to
better understand citation styles in general and the open source
Citation Style Language (CSL) in particular. CSL co-developers Bruce
D’Arcus and Frank Bennett provided important feedback.</p>
<sec id="1-what-is-the-citation-style-language">
  <title><bold><bold>1. What is the Citation Style
  Language?</bold></bold></title>
  <p>Rintze Zelle: Scientific literature depends heavily on proper
  referencing. However, when writing a manuscript, manually editing
  citations and bibliographies is time consuming and error prone.
  Citation styles also differ between scientific journals, so authors
  often have to switch citation styles when they submit their manuscript
  to a different journal than originally anticipated.</p>
  <p>The
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525124720/http://citationstyles.org/">Citation
  Style Language</ext-link> (CSL) is an open XML based language meant to
  automate the formatting of citations and bibliographies. When provided
  with the metadata (title, year, authors, etc.) of the cited items
  (journal articles, books, etc.), and a CSL style, a CSL processor can
  automatically generate the bibliography and in-text citations. CSL is
  currently used by
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525124720/http://www.zotero.org/">Zotero</ext-link>
  and
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525124720/http://www.mendeley.com/">Mendeley</ext-link>,
  and both programs offer word processor plug-ins for
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525124720/http://office.microsoft.com/en-us/word/">Microsoft
  Word</ext-link> and
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525124720/http://www.openoffice.org/">OpenOffice.org</ext-link>.
  Several other projects are working on or exploring CSL support.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="2-do-we-really-need-hundreds-of-citation-styles">
  <title>2. Do we really need hundreds of citation styles?</title>
  <p><bold><bold>Rintze Zelle</bold></bold>: We have asked ourselves
  this question many times over. Some variability is certainly
  warranted: numeric, author-date and footnote styles are very
  different, and each type has its own advantages and disadvantages.
  However, small variations in citation styles result in a situation
  where almost every journal or publisher has its unique style. We think
  that even with the use of automated tools like CSL, reducing the
  number of citation styles in use could result in significant cost and
  time savings in scientific publishing. But this is a problem beyond
  the scope of CSL, so our goal is simply to support all the variability
  that currently exists in citation styles.</p>
  <p><bold><bold>Ian Mulvany</bold></bold>: After working for many years
  at Springer, and then Nature, I was well aware that most large
  publishers just push submitted manuscripts out to companies in India
  where the formatting of the paper happens. The input format and
  citation formatting really doesn’t matter to most publishers. They
  just tear the submitted manuscript to pieces and rebuild it in their
  chosen XML schema.</p>
  <p>However, most people using citations are not actually submitting
  manuscripts for publication, but rather are writing term papers, or
  theses, or reports. So the weird thing is that citations started off
  as a required identifier for the literature. Google Scholar and HTTP
  URIs such as the DOI have almost totally made formatted citations
  redundant as identifiers, and yet there is still a huge user need to
  be able to format citations according to a huge variety of styles, and
  since that need is going to continue for quite a long time, it’s a
  need that we have to support.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="3-what-is-the-difference-between-csl-and-other-citation-style-systems">
  <title><bold><bold>3. What is the difference between CSL and other
  citation style systems?</bold></bold></title>
  <p>Rintze Zelle: Our main “competition” arguably comes from
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525124720/http://www.bibtex.org/">BibTeX</ext-link>
  and
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525124720/http://www.endnote.com/">EndNote</ext-link>/<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525124720/http://www.refman.com/">Reference
  Manager</ext-link>. BibTeX is a popular choice for those working with
  the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525124720/http://www.latex-project.org/">LaTeX</ext-link>
  typesetting system, but the user base of LaTeX is relatively small and
  mostly limited to the sciences. EndNote and Reference Manager are
  commercial tools offered by Thomson Reuters. While large collections
  of citation styles are available for each program, the use of these
  styles is limited to licensed users.</p>
  <p>CSL was designed with three main goals:</p>
  <list list-type="order">
    <list-item>
      <p>to create an open system that is independent of the operating
      system, application or document format,</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>to cover the full range of citation formatting rules in use,
      extending from the sciences to fields in the humanities as well as
      law,</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>to free end users from the complex task of formatting
      citations.</p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
  <p>Citation styles should be freely available, up to date, and
  complete. Switching between styles should be easy, and citation output
  should automatically localize to the desired language.</p>
  <p>We think we’ve come quite far toward reaching these goals with our
  most recent release, CSL 1.0. The
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525124720/http://citationstyles.org/downloads/specification.html">CSL
  1.0 specification</ext-link> covers a wide range of citation rules,
  and offers advanced features like automatic localization of date
  formats, terms and punctuation, support for in-field rich text and
  extensive support for the rendering and disambiguation of names. The
  first standalone CSL 1.0 processor (the JavaScript
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525124720/http://bitbucket.org/fbennett/citeproc-js/">citeproc-js</ext-link>)
  is currently being integrated into both Zotero and Mendeley, and is
  receiving attention for deployment on both the client and the
  server.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="4-can-you-tell-me-how-csl-was-developed">
  <title>4. Can you tell me how CSL was developed?</title>
  <p><bold><bold>Rintze Zelle</bold></bold>: CSL is the brainchild of
  Bruce D’Arcus, an associate professor of Geography at Miami University
  of Ohio. The language was initially implemented for integration into
  OpenOffice.org, but only became popular in 2006 when Zotero, the first
  reference manager to use CSL, was released. In these early days major
  contributions were made to CSL by Zotero developer Simon Kornblith.
  Subsequently, the Zotero project successfully fostered an active user
  community, with many users contributing styles to a growing repository
  of CSL styles.</p>
  <p>The year 2008 was a watershed of new developments. Mendeley was
  released, the second reference manager to use CSL for its citation
  formatting. Andrea Rossato released the first standalone CSL processor
  (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525124720/http://code.haskell.org/citeproc-hs/">citeproc-hs</ext-link>)
  for use with the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525124720/http://johnmacfarlane.net/pandoc/">Pandoc</ext-link>
  text processing system. Also in 2008, two Zotero users who enjoyed the
  program but felt that CSL could be further improved joined Bruce in
  CSL development: myself, at that time a PhD researcher in
  biotechnology at Delft University of Technology in the Netherlands,
  and Frank Bennett, Jr., an associate law professor at Nagoya
  University in Japan. Together with Andrea, our different academic and
  geographic backgrounds proved very useful in CSL development. In
  preparation for major backward-incompatible changes, CSL 0.8 was
  released in 2009, and in Spring 2010 CSL 1.0 saw the light of day. The
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525124720/http://citationstyles.org/2010/03/22/citation-style-language-1-0/">1.0
  release</ext-link> was accompanied by a move to a new website at
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525124720/http://citationstyles.org/">citationstyles.org</ext-link>,
  and included improved documentation in the form of a full language
  specification. CSL development has now calmed down a bit as we await
  the integration of CSL 1.0 by Zotero and Mendeley.</p>
  <p><bold><bold>Ian Mulvany</bold></bold>: We at Mendeley have been
  using the Citation Style Language for quite a while now. We think it
  is an amazing project and we are very strongly committed to working
  with the CSL community in encouraging uptake. We get a lot of feedback
  from our users and one area that they constantly run into problems
  with is the need to be able to format a citation in just such a
  manner. The CSL project is the best way for us to be able to support
  the needs of our users with these kinds of requests. Our developers
  have been pushing patches upstream to the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525124720/http://bitbucket.org/fbennett/citeproc-js/wiki/Home">citeproc-js</ext-link>
  project, particularly
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525124720/http://www.mendeley.com/profiles/carles-pina/">Carles
  Pina</ext-link>.</p>
  <p>We have added a cut and paste stylebox on our article pages. If you
  have a look at a
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525124720/http://www.mendeley.com/research/karhunenloeve-eigenvalue-problems-cosmology-we-tackle-large-data-sets/">sample
  paper</ext-link> you will now see a little citeproc-js driven “Cite
  this document” box that lets you copy and paste formatted citations in
  several popular citation styles. We have also been supporting the
  creation of a
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525124720/http://bitbucket.org/csledit/csl-wysiwyg-editor">WISYWIG
  citation style editor</ext-link>. The status of the project is that
  most of the code is complete and we just need to work on getting it
  integrated into our client, and figuring out the best way to manage
  the creation of more styles, and how that will work with the CSL
  community.</p>
  <p>One of the things that we have been discussing with Bruce D’Arcus
  is how to manage the redistribution of new styles, and how to make
  sure that corrupt styles don’t propagate, and that people get the
  style that they are looking for. If people want to contribute there is
  a lot of activity on the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525124720/https://lists.sourceforge.net/lists/listinfo/xbiblio-devel">mailing
  list</ext-link> of the CSL project. One thing we think we hope
  Mendeley can help with is reporting usage statistics on specific style
  files, so at least people can find the most popular version of a CSL
  file for a given style.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="5-where-can-a-user-find-more-csl-citation-styles-is-it-easy-to-modify-a-csl-style">
  <title>5. Where can a user find (more) CSL citation styles? Is it easy
  to modify a CSL style?</title>
  <p><bold><bold>Rintze Zelle</bold></bold>: While anyone is free to
  write and host their own CSL styles, most CSL styles that are in use
  are available through the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525124720/http://www.zotero.org/styles">Zotero
  Style Repository</ext-link> (many of these styles are licensed under a
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525124720/http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/">Creative
  Commons license</ext-link>). We have to admit that editing CSL styles
  currently requires some technical skill and knowledge of XML. This
  hasn’t kept members of the Zotero user community from creating over a
  thousand CSL styles, but we do recognize that user friendly editing of
  styles is a very important feature. We therefore applaud Mendeley’s
  effort to create an online CSL editor.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="6-should-publishers-care-about-csl">
  <title>6. Should publishers care about CSL?</title>
  <p><bold><bold>Ian Mulvany</bold></bold>: As I pointed out the big
  publishers don’t care about the submission format, but they have not
  really done a good job of communicating that to their editorial
  boards. Smaller publishers don’t have the resources to totally
  reformat submissions, and beyond academic publishing there are a huge
  number of people who just need to format citations. There is a huge
  waste of people’s time in reformatting papers for submissions, in
  fixing styles according to changing requirements from departments,
  when what should matter is the content. I’d love to get to a point
  where every publisher accepted the same type of XML input, and our
  authoring tools all created content conforming to that input format.
  Citations should be a DOI or other HTTP URI that can be rendered into
  the appropriate format using CSL and an API.</p>
  <p><italic><italic>Martin Fenner: The Open Access publishers BioMed
  Central and PLoS plan to add a CSL style download link to their author
  instruction pages. I hope that more publishers follow this
  example.</italic></italic></p>
</sec>
<sec id="7-do-you-want-to-talk-about-future-plans-for-csl">
  <title>7. Do you want to talk about future plans for CSL?</title>
  <p><bold><bold>Rintze Zelle</bold></bold>: We’re very excited about
  the work Zotero and Mendeley developers are doing to update their
  programs to support CSL 1.0. The update path should be relatively
  smooth for users as styles can be automatically updated to the CSL 1.0
  format, although styles will often need to be edited to take full
  advantage of all the new features. Zotero Everywhere
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525124720/http://www.zotero.org/blog/zoteros-next-big-step/">was
  announced</ext-link> earlier this week and will include a web citation
  formatting service based on citeproc-js.</p>
  <p>There are two things we consider crucial to the further development
  of CSL: one, we still lack an easy way for users to modify existing
  styles, although we’re hopeful that
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525124720/http://bitbucket.org/csledit/csl-wysiwyg-editor/">Mendeley’s
  CSL editor</ext-link> will soon fill this gap. Secondly, we feel there
  is a need for a more full-featured online style repository which
  allows users to find their style of choice, to add comments, and to
  propose style changes.</p>
  <p>The goal of CSL is to make citing formatting easier at a general
  level, across all fields and in all languages. This can only be
  achieved through a collaborative endeavor, and here we think
  publishers also share some responsibility. By providing high quality
  item metadata through robust standards (like
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525124720/http://unapi.info/">unAPI</ext-link>
  or
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525124720/http://ocoins.info/">COinS</ext-link>),
  by freely providing clear, correct and complete style guidelines or
  opting for a standard citation style (like APA, Chicago or
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525124720/http://www.mhra.org.uk/Publications/Books/StyleGuide/download.shtml">MHRA</ext-link>),
  and perhaps even by creating and hosting their own CSL styles,
  publishers can make our work, and that of authors, so much easier.</p>
  <p>With broad participation and support, we believe that CSL can
  benefit all fields of scholarship in a similar way Oren Patashnik’s
  BibTeX helped the sciences, by (further) streamlining the publication
  process, improving access to metadata of materials of all kinds, and
  by allowing scholars to spend more of their time on the core of their
  research.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
