<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Citations are links, so where is the
problem?</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2010-12-11">
<day>11</day>
<month>12</month>
<year>2010</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Citations are a fundamental concept of scholarly works. Unfortunately
they are also difficult to do. Traditional writing tools such as
Microsoft Word can’t really handle them in a way that is appropriate for
a scientific manuscript, and that is why we have reference managers such
as Endnote, Zotero or Mendeley. And the lack of this functionality is a
major reason that Google Docs and other online collaborative writing
tools haven’t become popular for writing scholarly works.</p>
<fig>
  <caption><p><italic><italic>1958 Edsel Citation by
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611074314/http://www.flickr.com/photos/roadsidepictures/">Roadsidepictures</ext-link>,
  on Flickr.</italic></italic></p></caption>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611074314im_/http://farm3.static.flickr.com/2678/4363633528_5026a5ce8b.jpg" xlink:title="" />
</fig>
<p>Using citations is hard for paper authors. The process is still
complicated when using a reference manager, and it remains one of the
more time consuming aspects of writing a manuscript. The main reason is
that something always seems to go wrong with the formatting of the
bibliography, but there are also issues of wrong or duplicate citations
(including
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611074314/http://www.the-scientist.com/news/display/57698/">citation
mutations</ext-link>), correct citation styles, etc. I can’t comment on
how well BibTeX integrates citation management into LaTeX, but the main
issue seems to be that citations usually are not one of the core
functions of the writing tool.</p>
<sec id="wordpress-and-reference-managers">
  <title>WordPress and reference managers</title>
  <p>The blogging platform <bold><bold>WordPress</bold></bold> could
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611074314/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2010/12/05/blogging-beyond-the-pdf/">become
  an excellent authoring platform</ext-link> for scientific papers. But
  to become successful, WordPress has to handle scholarly citations, and
  not just with copy and paste. Carl Boettinger
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611074314/http://www.carlboettiger.info/archives/570">has
  written about doing citations in WordPress</ext-link> ealier this week
  and there is also an
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611074314/http://friendfeed.com/science-2-0/deef8494/how-do-you-manage-citations-when-writing-on-web">ongoing
  FriendFeed discussion</ext-link>. I have also looked at the available
  plugins, in particular
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611074314/http://wordpress.org/extend/plugins/papercite/">papercite</ext-link>
  (based on
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611074314/http://wordpress.org/extend/plugins/bib2html/">bib2html</ext-link>)
  which uses the BibTex format and is giving me some problems. I can’t
  get the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611074314/http://labs.crossref.org/site/blog_plugins.html">CrossRef
  Citation plugin</ext-link> to work (SyntaxError: Parse error) and the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611074314/http://wordpress.org/extend/plugins/mendeleyplugin/">Mendeley
  Plugin</ext-link> is displaying bibliographies, rather than inserting
  citations. There is currently probably no easy solution to cite
  scholarly works in WordPress and I don’t think that creating a
  WordPress Plugin for one of the reference managers is the right
  approach.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="citations-are-links">
  <title>Citations are links</title>
  <p>If we think about it, citations are nothing more than specialized
  links that contain additional information and formatting. And the
  references section is a list of footnotes. Links are a genuine part of
  WordPress, and this system should therefore also be used when writing
  scholarly works with WordPress. A Citation Plugin should extend this
  system, and solve these issues:</p>
  <list list-type="bullet">
    <list-item>
      <p>WordPress isn’t very smart about footnotes. I use the
      <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611074314/http://www.elvery.net/drzax/wordpress-footnotes-plugin">WP-Footnotes</ext-link>
      Plugin, but we need additional functionality: avoid duplicates,
      formatting options of in-text citations (e.g. range of citations
      or author-year) and sorting of footnotes by occurence or name.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>The tool to create links in articles is not really integrated
      with the WordPress Links system (in contrast to images, where you
      have access to the media gallery when inserting an image).</p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
  <p>Both of  these issues can be solved, especially since they are not
  specific to scholarly works and could be tackled by thousands of
  WordPress developers out there.</p>
  <p>We don’t want to use WordPress as a reference manager, as there are
  already many tools out there that can do this job much better. We
  rather want reference manager integration with WordPress, and the
  easiest way to do this would be an automatic synchronization with the
  WordPress Links database. We can already do this with the social
  bookmarking tool <bold><bold>delicious</bold></bold> (I use
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611074314/http://wordpress.org/extend/plugins/wp-deliciouslinks/">DeliciousLinkSync</ext-link>),
  so it shouldn’t be difficult to do this with the social bookmarking
  tools for scientists such as <bold><bold>CiteULike</bold></bold> (you
  can
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611074314/http://blog.citeulike.org/?p=174">sync
  CiteULike with delicious</ext-link>, a workaround I currently use),
  <bold><bold>Connotea</bold></bold> or
  <bold><bold>BibSonomy</bold></bold>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="links-are-powerful">
  <title>Links are powerful</title>
  <p>Using the WordPress Links system makes it very easy to extend the
  core functionality, and many interesting tools are already out there.
  A good example is the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611074314/http://wordpress.org/extend/plugins/broken-link-checker/">Broken
  Link Checker</ext-link>. The Plugin can regularly check the links in
  your blog posts, but could also be used to check DOIs for references
  in a semi-automated way. The Broken Link Checker found 30 broken links
  in the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611074314/http://blogs.xartrials.org/2010/12/05/the-mycobacterium-tuberculosis-drugome-and-its-polypharmacological-implications-2/">Blogging
  Beyond the PDF sample article</ext-link> (all my fault), and
  automatically changed the display style for them.</p>
  <p>And there is so much more that can be done with links. I am
  particularly interested in adding meaning to links using the Citation
  Typing Ontology
  (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611074314/http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/2041-1480-1-S1-S6">CiTO</ext-link>).
  And I want to be able to cite specific parts of an article. Dave Winer
  has
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611074314/http://scripting.com/stories/2010/10/21/newBloggingTechniques.html">introduced</ext-link>
  paragraph-level permalinks to blogs, and I can do this on WordPress
  using the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611074314/http://danielbachhuber.com/2010/10/27/winerlinks-v0-2-released/">WinerLinks
  Plugin</ext-link>. The broken links in my Blogging Beyond the PDF
  sample article are all internal links, and I can now use WinerLinks to
  fix them. An example where I have already done this is the reference
  to Table S8 in
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611074314/http://blogs.xartrials.org/2010/12/05/the-mycobacterium-tuberculosis-drugome-and-its-polypharmacological-implications-2/#p16">this
  paragraph</ext-link>.</p>
  <p><italic><italic>Update on 12/11/10: I’ve installed the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611074314/http://ptsefton.com/2010/12/09/beyond-the-pdf-proposed-session-bring-the-web-to-the-researcher-mainly-on-authoring-tools.htm">Anotar
  Plugin</ext-link> by Peter Sefton that adds paragraph-level
  commenting.</italic></italic></p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
