<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Commenting on scientific papers</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2013-10-25">
<day>25</day>
<month>10</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>I think it is fair to say that commenting on scientific papers is
broken. And with commenting I mean online comments that are publicly
available, not informal discussions in journal clubs or at meetings.
This definition would include discussions of papers on social media such
as Twitter or Facebook. Why do I think that commenting is broken?</p>
<list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
    <p>the number of papers with online comments is low. For PLOS
    Biology we have comments on the journal platform for 11% of
    articles, tweets for 14% of articles and Facebook activity for 22%
    of articles (Fenner, 2013). The numbers for Twitter and Facebook are
    much higher for more recently published articles, but are nowhere
    close to every article having at least one comment.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>even though there is a fair amount of social media activity
    around articles, the quality of the discussion is varied. Twitter
    for example seems to work mostly as an alerting service for
    interesting articles with little more than the title of the article
    in the tweet text and not much discussion.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>when comments are made, they are really hard to find coming from
    the article. Unless they are made on the journal platform, or the
    publisher tracks article-level metrics and links out to these
    comments.</p>
  </list-item>
</list>
<p>What can be done to address these issues, i.e. increase the number of
comments, increase the depth of the discussion, and make it easier to
link comments to articles? Some of the thoughts that I and others have
had include the following:</p>
<list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
    <p>lower the technical barriers for commenting by providing a common
    and familiar commenting platform with an attractive user interface.
    Many blogs (including this one) and
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://elife.elifesciences.org/">some
    publishers</ext-link> use Disqus, which is arguably the most popular
    third-party commenting platform.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>develop new features that make commenting more attractive,
    including comments linked to specific sections of the text and notes
    that can be public, semi-public or private. See for example
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://medium.com/about/5972c72b18f2">what
    Medium is doing</ext-link>, check out
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hypothes.is/">Hypothes.is</ext-link>
    and
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://blog.peerj.com/post/62886292466/peerj-questions-a-new-way-to-never-publish-forget">PeerJ
    Questions</ext-link>, or study what services such as
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://stackoverflow.com/">Stackoverflow</ext-link>
    are doing.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>Link comments made in different places about the same object
    together, e.g. through Article-Level Metrics services.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>create incentives for scientists to comment, e.g. through
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://openbadges.org/">Mozilla
    Open Badges</ext-link> or by making them part of a community.</p>
  </list-item>
</list>
<p>On Tuesday the US National Library of Medicine launched
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ncbiinsights.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/2013/10/22/pubmed-commons-a-new-forum-for-scientific-discourse/">PubMed
Commons</ext-link> as a <italic>New Forum for Scientific
Discourse</italic>:</p>
<p specific-use="wrapper">
  <disp-quote>
    <p>We hope that PubMed Commons will leverage the social power of the
    internet to encourage constructive criticism and high quality
    discussions of scientific issues that will both enhance
    understanding and provide new avenues of collaboration within the
    community.</p>
  </disp-quote>
</p>
<p>PubMed Commons is still a pilot project and in order to read or write
comments you have to be a PubMed Commons participant and be signed in
with your My NCBI account. PubMed Commons has some important
features:</p>
<list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
    <p>PubMed is probably the place where most life sciences researchers
    search for literature. Having comments and discussion there makes
    perfect sense, and is probably a better place than a publisher
    platform that only targets particular journals. PubMed also has a
    reputation that is very different from social media tools that are
    popular, but not really familiar to most scientists.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>Access to PubMed Commons is restricted to researchers, and this
    is one strategy to have the comments focus on scientific discourse.
    It has to be seen whether the process of registering for PubMed
    Commons (which currently is a bit more involved than most commenting
    systems) is a barrier for scientists to take part in the discussion,
    or whether it generates an audience that makes it more likely that
    scientists contribute.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>For people signing in with their My NCBI account (I don’t know
    the percentage of PubMed users that do that on a regular basis),
    commenting is really easy and the interface is straightforward. The
    comment editor uses markdown, which makes it easy to format comments
    and to include links.</p>
  </list-item>
</list>
<p><italic>10/26/13: added link to the recently launched
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://blog.peerj.com/post/62886292466/peerj-questions-a-new-way-to-never-publish-forget">PeerJ
Questions</ext-link> which uses a question and answer format (thanks to
Jason Hoyt for reminding me).</italic></p>
<sec id="references">
  <title>References</title>
  <p>Fenner, M. (2013). What can article-level metrics do for you?
  <italic>PLoS Biol</italic>, <italic>11</italic>(10), e1001687.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.1001687">doi:10.1371/journal.pbio.1001687</ext-link></p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
