<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>CommonMark and the Future of Scholarly
Markdown</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2014-09-07">
<day>7</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2014</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>One of the important outcomes of the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/scholmd/scholmd/wiki">Markdown
for Science</ext-link> workshop that took place in June 2013 was a
decision on a name - <italic>Scholarly Markdown</italic> - and a brief
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/scholmd/scholmd/wiki/What-is-Markdown">definition</ext-link>:</p>
<list list-type="order">
  <list-item>
    <p>Markdown that supports the requirements of scientific texts</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>Markdown as format that glues open scientific text resources
    together</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>A reference implementation with documentation and tests</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>A community</p>
  </list-item>
</list>
<p>In my eyes this is still a great definition. And this week something
important happened that is very relevant for Scholarly Markdown. A small
group of people deeply involved in Markdown announced
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://commonmark.org/">Standard
Markdown</ext-link>:</p>
<p specific-use="wrapper">
  <disp-quote>
    <p>We propose a standard, unambiguous syntax specification for
    Markdown, along with a suite of comprehensive tests to validate
    Markdown implementations against this specification. We believe this
    is necessary, even essential, for the future of Markdown.</p>
  </disp-quote>
</p>
<p>Markdown is in widespread use, but a lack of standard syntax and set
of comprehensive tests has hindered the adoption for more complex use
cases, the development of cross-platform tools, and the use of markdown
as a document interchange format. I am therefore 100% behind this
initiative. In particular since this is not just an initiative by large
commercial organizations heavily using Markdown such as Stackexchange,
Github or Reddit, but that the entire spec and both reference
implementations have been written by
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://johnmacfarlane.net/">John
MacFarlane</ext-link>, the author of Pandoc, the universal document
converter. Not only does Pandoc already support many of the features
required by Scholarly Markdown (e.g. math and citations), but John is
the Chair of the Department of Philosophy at UC Berkeley.</p>
<p>Markdown was developed in 2004 by John Gruber, and he
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/license">holds
the rights</ext-link> to the name Markdown. He didn’t want this
initiative to use the name <bold><bold>Standard Markdown</bold></bold>,
so the implementation was
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://blog.codinghorror.com/standard-markdown-is-now-common-markdown/">renamed</ext-link>
to
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://commonmark.org/">CommonMark</ext-link>.</p>
<p>The consequences of all this for Scholarly Markdown?</p>
<list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
    <p>CommonMark focusses on the basic features of the language, but
    once the specification is agreed upon and implemented by a critical
    mass of tools, it is clear that there needs to be a standardized way
    to handle extensions of the language. This is both about features
    used by lots of people such as tables, but also functionality
    relevant only for scholarly content.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>This brings us one gigantic step closer to a reference
    implementation and set of tests for Scholarly Markdown, as hopefully
    Scholarly Markdown can build upon the work by John and the
    CommonMark team.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>The name Scholarly Markdown might not be a good idea going
    forward. We should either change the name to align with CommonMark,
    or we should come up with a totally different name, something that
    the screenwriters have done with
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://fountain.io/">their</ext-link>
    implementation of Markdown.</p>
  </list-item>
</list>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
