<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Comment: the case for open preprints in
biology</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2013-03-30">
<day>30</day>
<month>3</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Last week Philippe Desjardins-Prouly et al. published the article
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170731034700/http://dx.doi.org/10.6084/M9.FIGSHARE.655710">The
case for open preprints in biology</ext-link> – naturally as a preprint
on figshare. The article sees preprint servers as a great opportunity
for open science, and discusses the status of preprints in the
biological sciences. In this blog post I want to add some comments to
the text.</p>
<sec id="e-biomed">
  <title>E-BIOMED</title>
  <p>What is now PubMed Central
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170731034700/http://www.nih.gov/about/director/pubmedcentral/ebiomedarch.htm">started
  out as E-BIOMED in 1999</ext-link> and initially was envisioned to
  include a repository for preprints. It is important to look back at
  what happened then, and why the preprint repository was dropped from
  what then became PubMed Central. Harold Varmus talks a bit about this
  in this
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170731034700/http://poynder.blogspot.de/2006/06/interview-with-harold-varmus.html">interview</ext-link>
  from 2006.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="nature-precedings">
  <title>Nature Precedings</title>
  <p>The article talks about why biologists have not developed a culture
  of sharing preprints. It would be good to mention
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170731034700/http://precedings.nature.com/">Nature
  Precedings</ext-link>, a preprint server for the life sciences started
  in 2007 that stopped taking new submissions in 2012.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170731034700/http://retractionwatch.wordpress.com/2012/03/30/nature-precedings-to-stop-accepting-submissions-next-week-after-finding-model-unsustainable/">This
  blog post</ext-link> on RetractionWatch cites the announcement by
  Nature Publishing Group (which doesn’t explain why the service was
  shut down), and there are a good number of interesting comments.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="ssrn">
  <title>SSRN</title>
  <p>Preprints in other disciplines are mentioned in the text, in
  particular ArXiv, but also RePEc. I would also include
  <bold>SSRN</bold>
  (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170731034700/http://www.ssrn.com/">Social
  Science Research Network</ext-link>), which uses a different model,
  but is as important for the working paper and preprint culture in the
  social sciences as ArXiV is in physics/mathematics.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="google-scholar-metrics">
  <title>Google Scholar Metrics</title>
  <p>In April 2012 Google launched
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170731034700/http://scholar.google.com/citations?view_op=top_venues&amp;hl=en&amp;vq=en">Google
  Scholar Metrics</ext-link>, listing the top 100 publications
  (according to their h5-index) in several disciplines. Six out of the
  top 10 publications in physics/mathematics are ArXiV sections (arXiv
  Astrophysics (astro-ph) is #2), the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170731034700/http://www.iza.org/en/webcontent/publications/papers">IZA
  Discussion Papers</ext-link> are #1 in Social Sciences, and the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170731034700/http://www.nber.org/papers.html">NBER
  Working Papers</ext-link> are #1 in Economics, and arXiv Astrophysics
  (astro-ph) is #12 on the top 100 list for all disciplines (#1-5 are
  journals in biology and medicine: <italic>Nature</italic>, <italic>New
  England Journal of Medicine</italic>, <italic>Science</italic>,
  <italic>Lancet</italic>, <italic>Cell</italic>). All these metrics are
  a strong indicator that preprints can be highly cited.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="citation-advantage-of-preprints">
  <title>Citation Advantage of Preprints</title>
  <p>Anne Gentil-Beccot et al. have written a nice paper (of course
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170731034700/http://arxiv.org/abs/0906.5418">available
  as preprint</ext-link>) that shows that publication as preprint now
  only increases the citation rate for the corresponding peer-reviewed
  article published later, but also leads to much faster citations, with
  a peak immediately after publication.</p>
  <fig>
    <caption><p>Average number of citations per article per month as a
    function of the time of the citation relative to the time of
    publication. From
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170731034700/http://arxiv.org/abs/0906.5418">http://arxiv.org/abs/0906.5418</ext-link></p></caption>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170731034700im_/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/files/2013/03/gentil-beccot.png" xlink:title="" />
  </fig>
</sec>
<sec id="scoap3">
  <title>SCOAP3</title>
  <p>The Sponsoring Consortium for Open Access Publications in High
  Energy Physics
  (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170731034700/http://scoap3.org/">SCOAP3</ext-link>)
  is working on turning the majority of peer-reviewed publications in
  high energy physics into gold open access. It is important to
  understand that the high energy physics community feels that they need
  peer-reviewed journal articles in addition to ArXiv.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="preprint-culture-in-clinical-medicine">
  <title>Preprint Culture in Clinical Medicine</title>
  <p>It is a little known fact that there is a strong preprint culture
  in clinical medicine. I have written about this topic in
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170731034700/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2010/10/16/in-which-i-suggest-a-preprint-archive-for-clinical-trials/">October
  2010</ext-link>. Clinical trials have to be registered before starting
  the trial, and information about the trial is publicly available in
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170731034700/http://clinicaltrials.gov/">clinicaltrials.gov</ext-link>
  and other registries. Results are presented in conferences (as poster
  or oral presentation), at which stage it becomes public information.
  The peer-reviewed paper – with a few exceptions – follows much later,
  sometimes even after drug approval by the FDA (in the blog post I used
  the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170731034700/http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0140-6736(10)61389-X">TROPIC</ext-link>
  trial as example). The problem is of course that information in oral
  presentations and posters is incomplete and difficult to find. But
  publication of a clinical trial in a peer-reviewed journal is more
  about giving credit to the researchers involved (similar to SCOAP3 in
  high energy physics) than about spreading the knowledge. Peer review
  is not an appropriate filter for whether or not a new drug or drug
  combination should be used to treat patients – the approval process by
  regulatory authorities is much more extensive than any peer review can
  ever be.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="preprint-culture-in-biology">
  <title>Preprint culture in Biology</title>
  <p>The paper mentions several reasons why the field of biology has
  essentially no preprint culture. One argument against preprints is
  that it would be easier to steal ideas. Although I agree with the
  authors that preprints are a great way to establish precedence, there
  is a big difference between research based on years of work using
  expensive equipment (as is often the case in high energy physics but
  also some other fields), and research that can be reproduced in a few
  weeks. In the latter case it is possible that someone else is faster
  in publishing the peer-reviewed paper. Another difference is the
  community: “stealing” ideas from someone else is probably more
  difficult in smaller scientific communities, and some scientific
  communities are more competitive and less collaborative than
  others.</p>
  <p>Another concern about preprints raised in the paper is the
  Ingelfinger rule, i.e. the uncertainty that a journal would accept a
  manuscript if already published as a preprint. This concern is
  fortunately unfounded regarding most publishers, and the paper
  includes a table listing the preprint policies of important publishers
  in biology.</p>
  <p>I would like to add two other reasons why the preprint culture is
  probably not established in biology. Preprints are competition for the
  peer-reviewed journal article and scholarly publishers might not be
  particularly interested in encouraging a preprint culture. A lot has
  fortunately changed since E-BIOMED in 1999.</p>
  <p>Finally, whereas some disciplines use preprints and working papers
  to communicate, in biology the preferred way to communicate research
  findings before publication of a peer-reviewed paper is the oral
  presentation. What we may need is a service that makes it easy to
  upload and share scientific presentations. We for example already have
  Slideshare, Speaker Deck as generic tools, and SciVee, fishare aimed
  at scientists. Speaker Deck
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170731034700/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2012/05/29/speaker-deck-for-sharing-presentations/">is
  currently my favorite tool</ext-link> and is a Github product (Github
  has been mentioned in the manuscript as an option for hosting
  preprints). Maybe what is missing is a killer combination of features
  in a new or existing service – persistent identifiers, uploading of
  background material (text, data, software, video) in addition to the
  slides, non-textual search, cooperation with conference organizers,
  etc. – for presentation sharing to take off as a way to establish a
  preprint culture in biology.</p>
  <p><italic>Update 4/4/13: Yesterday PeerJ launched a new preprint
  service for life sciences research. Read
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170731034700/http://blogs.scientificamerican.com/guest-blog/2013/04/03/who-killed-the-preprint-and-could-it-make-a-return/">this
  blog post</ext-link> for details, and this
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170731034700/http://blog.mendeley.com/open-access/is-the-time-right-for-a-preprint-server-for-life-science/">post</ext-link>
  on the Mendeley blog.</italic></p>
</sec>
<sec id="references">
  <title>References</title>
  <p>Desjardins-Proulx, P., White, E. P., Adamson, J., Ram, K., Poisot,
  T., &amp; Gravel, D. (2013). <italic>The case for open preprints in
  biology</italic>.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.6084/M9.FIGSHARE.655710">https://doi.org/10.6084/M9.FIGSHARE.655710</ext-link></p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
