<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Component DOIs Revisited</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2015-07-09">
<day>9</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2015</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Four years ago I wrote a
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://blog.martinfenner.org/posts/direct-links-to-figures-and-tables-using-component-dois/">blog
post</ext-link> about component DOIs. It is time to revisit the topic,
in particular since our approach to citing data associated with a
publication has changed since 2011.</p>
<p>Component DOIs are explained in the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://help.crossref.org/components">CrossRef
Help System</ext-link>:</p>
<p specific-use="wrapper">
  <disp-quote>
    <p>DOIs may be assigned to items that are part of a journal article,
    book chapter, or any other content item. A component would typically
    be a figure, table, or image which is part of or referred to by the
    parent item. Assigning a DOI to a component allows direct linking to
    the component item.</p>
  </disp-quote>
</p>
<p>Component DOIs are DOIs, i.e. persistent identifiers that link
directly to the resource in question, e.g. a figure in a publication.
The component DOI for a figure in a PLOS paper used in the 2011 post
still
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0006022.g002">works
as expected</ext-link>, despite changes to the URL of the journal
landing page.</p>
<p>The problem with component DOIs is the problem with DOIs in general:
there is basic functionality common to all DOIs, and there are
additional services specific to subgroups of DOIs. This confuses users -
in particular since there is no easy way to immediately see what kind of
DOI they have in front of them - and in the case of component DOIs there
is one important feature missing.</p>
<p>DOis are assigned by registration agencies (CrossRef and DataCite are
the most relevant ones for scholarly content), and these RAs have built
different services around DOIs, e.g. different ways to describe and
search the metadata (title, authors, etc.) associated with a DOI.
Component DOIs are again different, the most important difference is
that in the CrossRef implementation they they are not discoverable by
querying the CrossRef system (Feeney, 2010). Component DOIs are also
always associated with a parent DOI (for the article, book, etc.).
Although this is the expected behaviour, we shouldn’t expect component
DOIs to always look like an extension of the parent DOI, as in
<monospace>10.1371/journal.pone.0006022.g002</monospace> used in the
example above.</p>
<p>In essence, a component DOI is a <bold><bold>DOI light</bold></bold>.
We can use them for persistent linking, but we can’t use them for
discovery via the CrossRef Metadata Search (and by extension other
indexing services). A common use case for component DOIs is
supplementary information in a journal article. Content in supplementary
information files is already much harder to find than content in the
body of an article, using component DOIs instead of regular DOIs makes
the content again harder to find.</p>
<p>All of this might not have been much of an issue when I wrote the
2011 post, but making the data underlying a publication publicly
available and discoverable is increasingly becoming something that
funders, publishers and institutions expect. Most of these data are not
deposited in dedicated data repositories, but in supplementary
information files (for PLOS articles published since March 2014 this is
true for more than 50% of papers). Using regular DOIs for supplementary
information files with proper metadata and proper inclusion in indexing
services will make it easier to find, access and reuse these data.</p>
<p>Unfortunately that still leaves us with the problem that the
supplementary information files then will have CrossRef DOIs, whereas
data repositories typically use DataCite DOIs, so that we need to search
for these datasets in two different places. But that is material for
another post.</p>
<sec id="references">
  <title>References</title>
  <p>Feeney, P. (2010). DOIs for Journals: Linking and Beyond.
  <italic>Information Standards Quarterly</italic>,
  <italic>22</italic>(3), 27.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3789/isqv22n3.2010.06">https://doi.org/10.3789/isqv22n3.2010.06</ext-link></p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
