<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Conference microblogging: FriendFeed, Twitter and now
Google+ ?</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2011-07-04">
<day>4</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2011</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Blogging is a
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611100409/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2009/10/01/conference_blogging_interview_with_alex_knoll/">great
format</ext-link> to report from conferences. The regular blog format
works best for posts written at the end of the day – unless you are
typing really fast. Microblogging, i.e. a number of short or very short
posts by a group of people, works better for live blogging of an event
and has become very popular.</p>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611100409/http://www.friendfeed.com/">FriendFeed</ext-link>
was probably the first widely used microblogging tool for scientific
conferences starting in 2008, and a
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611100409/http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000263">January
2009 paper</ext-link> describes the experience at 2008 ISMB conference
in Toronto. By late 2009 Twitter had surpassed FriendFeed in popularity,
and at some point in 2010 most people seemed to have switched from
FriendFeed to Twitter for conference microblogging.</p>
<p>Twitter is a great tool in many ways, but is far from perfect for
conferences. The biggest problem is that the tweets about a particular
topic aren’t really connected. Hashtags help to find tweets about a
particular conference, but hashtags for a particular session have never
cought on. This makes it very difficult to have a real discussion, or to
find related messages later on.</p>
<p>Facebook is not only extremely popular, but has also taken many of
the features of FriendFeed. But for some reason it has not become a
popular conference microblogging tool for scientists. I think this is
because many people use Facebook primarily for their social
interactions, and keep those separate from their professional
discussions.</p>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611100409/http://plus.google.com/">Google+</ext-link>
was released last week, and the services has many of the features of
FriendFeed and Facebook (who bought FriendFeed in August 2009, one of
the reasons the service has never become that popular). Google+ allows
discussions around a particular message (post, tweet?). It doesn’t have
groups about a particular topic (e.g. conference), and doesn’t yet
understand a concept similar to hashtags. The service looks very nice
from a desktop computer, but the mobile version for iPhone and iPad
isn’t very polished (I haven’t tested the Android app).</p>
<p>The experience from Twitter tells me that the most important feature
for a great conference microblogging tool is popularity, and this is
only partly related to the technology behind the service. There are
already a good number of science bloggers and other Science 2.0 folks on
Google+ and we have seen some good discussions (e.g. a
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611100409/https://plus.google.com/106537123721037364937/posts/buxDWrvq8vU#106537123721037364937/posts/buxDWrvq8vU">discussion
about conference microblogging</ext-link>), so that is a very good sign.
But the experience with Google Wave
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611100409/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2010/08/09/what_comes_after_google_wave/">discontinued</ext-link>)
and Google Buzz (not that many people seem to use it) makes me a bit
cautious, and I will wait how Google+ evolves in the coming months
before I get too exited.</p>
<p>Update: Added a paragraph about Facebook.</p>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
