<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Conference Blogging: Interview with Alex
Knoll</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2009-10-01">
<day>1</day>
<month>10</month>
<year>2009</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Blogging is
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611105344/http://www.nature.com/news/2009/090624/full/4591050a.html">a
great way to report from a scientific conference</ext-link>. This could
be done either with regular blog posts written in the evening or after
the conference, and/or live-blogging using tools such as Friendfeed or
Twitter. One or more blogging scientists can not only add a unique
perspective to the reports about a conference, but for smaller
conferences blogging might be the only way to learn more about a
conference you were unable to attend in person.</p>
<p>Conference blogging (particularly live-blogging) basically requires
four things:</p>
<list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
    <p>a wireless network,</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>a computer or mobile phone with a full battery,</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>a hashtag (and other tools to find the conference blog posts),
    and</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>a blogging policy by the conference organizers.</p>
  </list-item>
</list>
<p>Wireless networks are now commonplace, but enough battery power (or
power outlets that conference participants can use) can be difficult. A
hashtag such as <italic><italic>#solo09</italic></italic> for
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611105344/http://www.scienceonlinelondon.org/">Science
Online London</ext-link> is essential for live-blogging using
Twitter.</p>
<p>The big problem is the blogging policy, or rather that there usually
is a policy only for traditional media, but not for blogging. The
blogging from the Cold Spring Harbor <italic><italic>Biology of
Genomes</italic></italic> meeting in May by Daniel MacArthur
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611105344/http://scienceblogs.com/geneticfuture/2009/06/on_the_challenges_of_conferenc.php">started
a very helpful discussion about blogging policies</ext-link>. It is
impossible to write anything specific about a conference – and that's
the stuff that is most interesting – without a permission from the
conference organizer and speaker. This is best done before the
conference has started. A July <italic><italic>Nature</italic></italic>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611105344/http://www.nature.com/nature/journal/v460/n7252/full/460152a.html">editorial</ext-link>
argues that an opt-out policy, where everything can be blogged about
unless the speaker or poster presenter specifically says so, is a
reasonable alternative.</p>
<p>The organizers of the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611105344/http://www.genetics2009.de/">Annual
Meeting of the German Genetics Society</ext-link> that took place two
weeks ago in Cologne did this right. Not only did they invite
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611105344/http://network.nature.com/people/alexander-knoll/profile">Alex
Knoll</ext-link> to become the official conference blogger, but they
also put up a prominent link to his blog posts on the conference
homepage, and they asked every speaker before the conference whether
Alex would be allowed to blog about their talks. Because his blog on
scienceblogs.de
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611105344/http://www.scienceblogs.de/alles-was-lebt">Alles
was lebt</ext-link>) is in German, he decided to put up his blog posts
here. I've asked him a few questions about this experience.</p>
<fig>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611105344im_/http://gallery.me.com/mfenner/100079/alex_knoll/web.jpg" xlink:title="" />
</fig>
<sec id="1-did-you-have-fun-being-the-official-blogger-for-the-german-genetics-society-meeting">
  <title>1. Did you have fun being the official blogger for the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611105344/http://www.genetics2009.de/">German
  Genetics Society Meeting</ext-link>?</title>
  <p>This conference blogging job was a first for me in many ways. I
  usually blog in German, so I wasn't sure if I would be able to bring
  more than my dry, scientific English. I also knew beforehand that
  there would be no theme, that the meeting was a general one. I would
  have at least to give the impression of having understood the basics
  of the talks. There would be no flitting about from talk to talk, I
  wanted to get whole sessions without interruption.</p>
  <p>But on the other hand, I also got to know lots of people, many more
  than I would have as a lowly PhD student. I attended a conference I
  almost certainly would not have without the invitation to come and
  blog.</p>
  <p>And, as any other (science)blogger will tell you, blogging is a
  labour of love (don't stab me in the back now!). So yes, I had a great
  time!</p>
</sec>
<sec id="2-blogging-about-the-conference-must-have-been-a-lot-of-work-">
  <title>2. Blogging about the conference must have been a lot of
  work!</title>
  <p>About as much as I expected. I was frantically typing away at my
  little netbook keyboard during the talks to take notes, and used any
  spare time to put together the posts. So I did not have as easy a time
  as regular conference attendees. No problem, I came to do a job!</p>
</sec>
<sec id="3-did-you-meet-any-other-science-bloggers-at-the-conference">
  <title>3. Did you meet any other science bloggers at the
  conference?</title>
  <p>As far as I'm aware, I was the only blogger attending, and also the
  only one tweeting from the sessions (no worries, no unpublished data
  got out that route).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="4-what-was-the-feedback-from-the-speakers-what-was-your-experience-getting-permissions-from-speakers-to-blog-about-their-sessions">
  <title>4. What was the feedback from the speakers? What was your
  experience getting permissions from speakers to blog about their
  sessions?</title>
  <p>I got the whole range. From the really open “Go ahead! Write what
  you want, put it online. I'll talk about some unpublished stuff as
  well, but I don't mind” to some who are not interested in getting
  their work out into a blog at all. Great news for the conference
  blogging crowd: the balance was tipped more to the pro side! Most of
  the speakers came out somewhere in between those two sides, probably
  being a bit cautious about that whole strange blogging stuff. But I
  got mostly positive feedback from them, and I believe the next blogger
  will have an easier time when blogging about their talks!</p>
</sec>
<sec id="5-what-tips-would-you-give-a-conference-organizer-who-wants-to-promote-blogging">
  <title>5. What tips would you give a conference organizer who wants to
  promote blogging?</title>
  <p>They should make clear from the start if blogging about the talks
  is generally OK. That doesn't mean all of the speakers have to allow
  blogging about their talk, but an official position will help everyone
  involved. You also don't need to have an
  <italic><italic>official</italic></italic> blogger, but especially at
  smaller meetings asking someone to blog beforehand is probably the
  only chance to get a blogger there at all.</p>
  <p>I also have advice for speakers: Start your talk by telling your
  audience if blogging about it is OK! If a part of your talk is
  unpublished, tell them that as well. Or put an icon on your slides to
  indicate which is good to blog about, for example as Daniel MacArthur
  from the Genetic Future blog
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611105344/http://scienceblogs.com/geneticfuture/2009/07/conference_blogging_icons_for.php">has
  proposed</ext-link>. If bloggers know beforehand if and what part of
  the talk is good to go, they will be more willing to take notes in
  earnest!</p>
  <p>Now that my guest posting here at Martin's blog comes to an end, I
  would like to leave you with one of the last impressions, a rather
  lucky shot of Cologne Cathedral I took while leaving. Many thanks to
  Martin for hosting this conference blog!</p>
  <fig>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611105344im_/http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3492/3969315341_4f8c590711.jpg" xlink:title="" />
  </fig>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
