<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Could you write your next paper with Google
Docs?</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2007-09-09">
<day>9</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2007</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611101232/http://docs.google.com/">Google
Docs</ext-link> and
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611101232/http://writer.zoho.com/">Zoho
Writer</ext-link> are web-based writing tools that have gained many of
the features of traditional word processors such as Microsoft Word.
Looking at Google Docs as an example (Zoho Writer shares many of the
strenghts and weaknesses), I wanted to find out if they are mature
enough to write a scientific paper.</p>
<sec id="the-good">
  <title>The Good</title>
  <p>The major strength is collaboration. All documents are stored
  online, which makes it very easy for several people to work on a
  document simultaneously. Because all changes to the text are kept
  (with author and date), it is easy to go back to an older version. You
  can import and export documents in various formats, including .doc,
  .rtf and .pdf.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="the-bad">
  <title>The Bad</title>
  <p>The obvious missing feature is lack of reference manager
  integration. Google Docs currently doesn't support footnotes or
  endnotes, so you can't roll your own references. Google Docs supports
  font formatting, but unfortunately that doesn't include the Symbol
  font – needed in almost all scientific documents. And Google Docs
  online works with an online internet connection, although offline
  support may come in the form of
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611101232/http://gears.google.com/">Google
  Gears</ext-link>, Zoho Writer already supports Google Gears.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="the-summary">
  <title>The Summary</title>
  <p>Google Docs is <italic><italic>almost</italic></italic> ready to be
  an attractive tool for scientific writing. Some of the small problems
  are easily fixed in future updates. The big problem is integration of
  scientific references. But Google already has
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611101232/http://scholar.google.com/">Google
  Scholar</ext-link>, maybe the two can be integrated?</p>
  <p>For now, Google Docs can help with papers that have many active
  authors (e.g. a review article), but the final steps still have to be
  done with a word processor.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
