<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Creating charts with Datawrapper</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2013-07-19">
<day>19</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Figures are an important part of any scientific document. While the
kind of figure commonly used obviously varies between disciplines,
charts are an important part of many publications. There are two
problems in how charts are currently used:</p>
<list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
    <p>the data used to draw the chart are not available or difficult to
    obtain</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>charts are drawn as static images with no interactivity, e.g. to
    see the values of individual data points</p>
  </list-item>
</list>
<p>Ross Mounce and others did a <bold><bold>Figures → Data</bold></bold>
project at the recent
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hacka4ac.com/">hack4ac</ext-link>
to extract data from figures, described in a
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://rossmounce.co.uk/2013/07/09/hack4ac-recap/">blog
post</ext-link>. The experience was painful, even though they started
with a <italic>really</italic> simple chart.</p>
<p>While we should of course
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://datadryad.org/">publish
all data associated with a paper</ext-link>, the smarter strategy to
overcome the two limitations above would be to embed the data used for a
chart directly into the document. We have many tools that can accomplish
this, and I have given an example using R in an
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://blog.martinfenner.org/2013/06/17/what-is-scholarly-markdown/">earlier
blog post</ext-link>. The problem is the sometimes steep learning
curve.</p>
<p>One approach is to build an easy-to use online tool, and
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://datawrapper.de/">Datawrapper</ext-link>
is exactly that:</p>
<p specific-use="wrapper">
  <disp-quote>
    <p>An open source tool helping anyone to create simple, correct and
    embeddable charts in minutes.</p>
  </disp-quote>
</p>
<p>Datawrapper uses the <bold><bold>d3.js</bold></bold> and
<bold><bold>Highcharts</bold></bold> Javascript libraries for data
visualizations, and the service is easy to use. It took me for example
about 15 min to generate the chart below. The data used for the chart
are embedded (click <bold><bold>Get the data</bold></bold>) and you can
hover over the chart to see the actual numbers by month.</p>
<boxed-text>
  <boxed-text id="header">
    <sec id="monthly-article-views-over-time">
      <title>Monthly Article Views Over Time</title>
      <p>Monthly HTML views from the PLOS website for two PLOS Medicine
      articles published July 21, 2009. The striking difference in usage
      between &quot;Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and
      Meta-Analyses: The PRISMA Statement&quot; and &quot;Can the
      Relationship between Doctors and Drug Companies Ever Be a Healthy
      One?&quot; becomes apparent only 18 months after publication.</p>
      <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://s3.datawrapper.de/7PqqU/?fs=1" xlink:title="Fullscreen"></ext-link></p>
    </sec>
  </boxed-text>
  <boxed-text id="chart">
  </boxed-text>
  <boxed-text id="footer">
    <boxed-text>
      <p>Created with
      <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://datawrapper.de/">Datawrapper</ext-link></p>
    </boxed-text>
    <boxed-text>
      <p>Source:
      <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plosmedicine.org/">PLOS</ext-link>,
      <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="data">Get the
      data</ext-link></p>
    </boxed-text>
  </boxed-text>
</boxed-text>
<p>Most journal articles see the highest usage immediately after
publication, and the light purple line shows this pattern for Darcy et
al. (2009). The dark purple line for Moher et al. (2009) – published on
the same day – on the other hand shows a highly unusual usage pattern,
as the usage actually increases over time, starting about 1 1/2 years
after publication. The article is a guideline for reporting systematic
reviews and meta-analyses, and is now viewed more often than directly
after publication four years ago.</p>
<p>Datawrapper does three things: it makes it easy to generate charts,
it allows you to embed them directly into your webpage (using an
<monospace>&lt;iframe&gt;</monospace> tag), and it is Open Source
software (MIT license, Github repo
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/datawrapper/datawrapper">here</ext-link>)
so that you can help improve the code and host this service on your own.
DataWrapper was written in Javascript and PHP by a group of German
journalists, and the main focus is data journalism where the service has
become really
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://blog.datawrapper.de/2013/datawrapper-crosses-mark-of-10-million-visits/">popular</ext-link>
with more than 3.5 million views of embedded charts in May 2013
alone.</p>
<p>Datawrapper is a perfect tool for science blogs and websites with
scientific content, but it can also enhance the charts in scientific
articles. We need a few additional chart types, error bars and more
flexible labeling. And we might want to add a license picker, making it
easy to add a Creative Commons license so that it is clear how the chart
can be reused. Datawrapper is intended for online use, but the service
can also save the charts as PNG or PDF. We would want to add saving to
SVG (already used for online rendering) for easier embedding into the
XML and ePub versions of articles.</p>
<sec id="references">
  <title>References</title>
  <p>D’Arcy, E., &amp; Moynihan, R. (2009). Can the relationship between
  doctors and drug companies ever be a healthy one? <italic>PLoS
  Medicine</italic>, <italic>6</italic>(7), e1000075. Retrieved from
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pmed.1000075">http://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pmed.1000075</ext-link></p>
  <p>Moher, D., Liberati, A., Tetzlaff, J., &amp; Altman, D. G. (2009).
  Preferred reporting items for systematic reviews and meta-analyses:
  The pRISMA statement. <italic>PLoS Medicine</italic>,
  <italic>6</italic>(7), e1000097. Retrieved from
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pmed.1000097">http://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pmed.1000097</ext-link></p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
