<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>CrowdoMeter goes Mobile</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2012-01-04">
<day>4</day>
<month>1</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Two weeks ago Euan Adie from
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170107002621/http://altmetric.com/">altmetric.com</ext-link>
and myself
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170107002621/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2011/12/20/crowdometer-or-trying-to-understand-tweets-about-journal-papers/">launched</ext-link>
the website
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170107002621/http://crowdometer.org/">CrowdoMeter</ext-link>,
a crowdsourcing project that tries to classify tweets about scholarly
articles using the Citation Typing Ontology (CiTO). Despite the holidays
we have gotten off to a good start with currently 597 classifications by
56 different users, already covering 93% of the tweets we wanted to
classify. We will discuss the results of this project at the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170107002621/http://scienceonline2012.com/">ScienceOnline2012</ext-link>
conference in two weeks, but the most important findings can also be
watched in real-time
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170107002621/http://crowdometer.org/ratings">here</ext-link>.</p>
<p>To our knowledge this is the first time that CiTO has been used for
the systematic classification of tweets, and the preliminary results
seem to confirm what we and others had thought, i.e. that most tweets
contain little semantic information and often only retweet the title of
a paper. But not only do we now have numbers to confirm this, but we can
also make some interesting additional observations. We find for example
that only 1% of tweets disagree with the statements made in a paper –
most Twitter users don’t seem to care telling others about papers they
dislike or disagree with.</p>
<p>This project is far from over, ideally we want 3-5 classifications
per tweet or an additional 1,000 classifications. It is a challenge to
build a website so that enough people want to help with this project.
One idea is to make the classifications as simple as possible, and to
help further with this we today launched a mobile version of
CrowdoMeter. Simply browse to
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170107002621/http://crowdometer.org/">http://crowdometer.org</ext-link>
with your iPhone or Android phone, sign in via your Twitter account, and
you should see something similar to this:</p>
<fig>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170107002621im_/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/files/2012/01/crowdometer.png" xlink:title="crowdometer" />
</fig>
<p>CrowdoMeter uses
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170107002621/http://jquerymobile.com/">jQuery
Mobile</ext-link>, a touch-optimized Javascript framework for
smartphones and tablets. There are still some minor issues, but in
general jQuery Mobile is a great tool to optimize a website for mobile
users. Users are presented with 10 random tweets they haven’t classified
yet, and see a simple classification screen when clicking (touching) a
tweet:</p>
<fig>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170107002621im_/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/files/2012/01/crowdometer1.png" xlink:title="crowdometer1" />
</fig>
<p>It should not take longer than 15 minutes to classify 15-25 tweets,
and this would be a tremendous help for the project.</p>
<p>The CrowdoMeter results page displayed the same information as in the
desktop version of the website, the charts are produced by the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170107002621/http://www.highcharts.com/">Highcharts</ext-link>
Javascript library (and again jQuery).</p>
<fig>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170107002621im_/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/files/2012/01/crowdometer2.png" xlink:title="crowdometer2" />
</fig>
<p>I’m interested to see how well the crowdsourcing for CrowdoMeter will
work in the coming weeks. We hope to finish the data gathering part in
January. If this project generates enough interest I could imagine doing
another crowdsourcing project, maybe again using the Citation Typing
Ontology, but this time for blog posts about scholarly papers.</p>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
