<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>CSL is more than citation styles</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2013-08-08">
<day>8</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>According to the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://citationstyles.org/">description</ext-link>
on the Citation Style Language (CSL) website, CSL <italic>is an open
XML-based language to describe the formatting of citations and
bibliographies</italic>. We use reference managers such as
<bold>Zotero</bold>, <bold><bold>Mendeley</bold></bold>, or
<bold><bold>Papers</bold></bold> to format our references in manuscripts
we submit for publication, and underneath a CSL processor such as
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://bitbucket.org/fbennett/citeproc-js/wiki/Home">Citeproc-js</ext-link>
- together with a CSL file for a particular citation style - is doing
the work:</p>
<fig>
  <caption><p>Citation processing during manuscript
  writing</p></caption>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://martinfenner.ghost.io/content/images/2021/02/csl.png" xlink:title="" />
</fig>
<p>When the journal article is accepted the publisher takes the text
with the formatted text citation and turns it into XML, a process that
is error-prone and takes time:</p>
<fig>
  <caption><p>Citation processing by the publisher</p></caption>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://martinfenner.ghost.io/content/images/2021/02/csl2.png" xlink:title="" />
</fig>
<p>It is not hard to see that something is very wrong here:</p>
<list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
    <p>Authors are required to use a specific citation style (there are
    probably about 1,000 different citation styles and many more
    dependent styles) even though the publisher doesn’t directly use the
    formatted text. The publisher eLife
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.elifesciences.org/elife-references/">accepts
    references in any format</ext-link>.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>Turning structured information into plain text and back into
    structured XML is always a bad idea.
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://twitter.com/kaveh1000">Kaveh
    Bazargan</ext-link> is a typesetter who has gone on record for
    saying that we should stop this nonsense and put him out of
    business.</p>
  </list-item>
</list>
<p>It is also obvious how the ideal workflow should look like:</p>
<fig>
  <caption><p>Ideal workflow of citation processing</p></caption>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://martinfenner.ghost.io/content/images/2021/02/csl3.png" xlink:title="" />
</fig>
<p>We go from structured content to structured content, and never use
citations formatted as text as intermediary steps in the workflow.</p>
<p>What is surprising is that this is an ideal workflow and not
something that publishers actually do. Most journal author instructions
don’t even mention CSL styles (I work for PLOS and they are no
exception). There are some issues to be solved, but they are all
minor:</p>
<list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
    <p>The Citeproc JSON citation format isn’t really an official
    standard, but rather something invented for the most popular CSL
    processor, Citeproc-js.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>People like to fight over standards, and there are always people
    you prefer bibtex, RIS, MODS or BibJSON over Citeproc JSON, or want
    authors to to use JATS XML.</p>
  </list-item>
</list>
<p>I would really like to push Citeproc JSON as a standard bibliographic
exchange format for authors. There are several things I like about
Citeproc JSON:</p>
<list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
    <p>It is the native format to format citations, so it is used
    internally by many reference managers anyway.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>Citeproc JSON is really good in handling all the possible
    variations of author names. Putting all authors into a single text
    field as in bibtex requires a lot of trickery to get it right.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>JSON is a standard serialization format and there are a kinds of
    libraries in different programming languages to do things like
    searching, sorting or finding of duplicates. And JSON is easily
    extensible, e.g. if we would want to add ORCID identifiers for
    authors.</p>
  </list-item>
</list>
<p>I have five suggestions to move forward:</p>
<list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
    <p>Make a specification for Citeproc JSON that is as clear as the
    CSL specification.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>Consider extending the specification to include content other
    than citations. Ideally we should be able to add arbitrary
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://blog.martinfenner.org/2013/06/29/metadata-in-scholarly-markdown/">metadata
    about a manuscript</ext-link>.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>Consider other serialization formats besides JSON. I particularly
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://blog.martinfenner.org/2013/07/30/citeproc-yaml-for-bibliographies/">like
    YAML</ext-link> as it is very similar to JSON, but human-readable,
    but other people might prefer XML. It is relatively easy to
    transform data between these serialization formats, in particular
    between JSON and YAML. In my
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://blog.martinfenner.org/about.html">About
    page</ext-link> I only need the
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/nodeca/js-yaml">js-yaml</ext-link>
    library and one extra line of code to use Citeproc YAML instead of
    Citeproc JSON (in the d3.js visualization).</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>Add Citeproc JSON (and YAML) support to reference managers.
    Zotero is already doing this, but it should be an easy to add
    feature if the reference manager is already using CSL internally
    (Mendeley and Papers).</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>Push publishers to accept Citeproc JSON with manuscript
    submissions.</p>
  </list-item>
</list>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
