<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Data Citation Support in Reference
Managers</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2015-01-05">
<day>5</day>
<month>1</month>
<year>2015</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>This is the title of an upcoming workshop next Sunday organized by
Ian Mulvany and myself. The workshop is a
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.force11.org/meetings/force2015/pre-conference-meeting-list">pre-conference
event</ext-link> of the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.force11.org/meetings/force2015">Force15</ext-link>
conference in Oxford. This blog post summarizes some of the issues and
work that needs to be done.</p>
<p>Data Citation is one of the big themes of the Force15 conference, and
a lot of progress has been made, including the Joint Declaration of Data
Citation Principles (Data Citation Synthesis Group 2014) that start with
the following paragraph on <bold><bold>Importance</bold></bold>:</p>
<p specific-use="wrapper">
  <disp-quote>
    <p>Data should be considered legitimate, citable products of
    research. Data citations should be accorded the same importance in
    the scholarly record as citations of other research objects, such as
    publications.</p>
  </disp-quote>
</p>
<p>Convincing researchers, funders, university administrators and others
that data citation is important is crucial. But for researchers to
actually adopt data citation to the same degree as citations of the
scholarly literature, more needs to be done:</p>
<list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
    <p>incentives (both carrots and sticks) by funders, institutions,
    and scholarly societies</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>training in data management</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>data repositories and other tools and services for the public
    sharing of data</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>tools and services that help citing those datasets</p>
  </list-item>
</list>
<p>The focus of the workshop is on the last bullet point, and I would
argue that more work still needs to be done here compared to the first
three bullet points.</p>
<sec id="reference-managers">
  <title>Reference Managers</title>
  <p>Researchers use reference managers to handle the citations in the
  manuscripts they write. This is both a common practice that everybody
  understands, and there are a plethora of tools - both free and paid -
  available. Most reference managers were originally built to handle
  citations of journal articles and maybe books or book chapters, and
  many of them also help with managing the associated PDF files. In the
  last 15 years we have seen an dramatic increase of non-article
  citations in reference lists, mainly to web resources (Klein et al.,
  2014):</p>
  <fig>
    <caption><p>From Fig. 2: STM articles and URI references per
    publication year - Elsevier corpus (Klein et al. 2014)</p></caption>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://martinfenner.ghost.io/content/images/2021/02/journal.pone.0115253.g002.png" xlink:title="" />
  </fig>
  <p>References managers have started to adapt to these changes in
  citation patterns. Similarly they have become better in handling
  non-textual resources such as slide decks, datasets, or movies. Nobody
  should type in references by hand in 2015, as reference managers have
  come up with several ways of importing metadata about citations:</p>
  <list list-type="bullet">
    <list-item>
      <p>import references stored in a file using a format such as
      BibTex or RIS</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>import references by talking to an external API</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>import references via a bookmarklet that grabs information from
      the current webpage in the browser</p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
  <p>Endnote and Papers typically use the second approach whereas
  Mendeley, Zotero (and others) work almost exclusively via bookmarklets
  (and there are of course combinations of both). Bookmarklets in
  general work better for web resources and other content that is not
  indexed in a central service such as Web of Science or Scopus. This is
  also true for research data, as there are currently few central
  research data indexing services - the Thomson Reuters
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://wokinfo.com/products_tools/multidisciplinary/dci/">Data
  Citation Index</ext-link> and
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.datacite.org/">DataCite</ext-link>
  are two examples in this category. But there are also thousands of
  data repositories, many of them listed in re3data (Pampel et al.,
  2013).</p>
  <p>The reference manager
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.zotero.org/">Zotero</ext-link>
  has built a large open source ecosystem around bookmarklets (what they
  call
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/zotero/translators">web
  translators</ext-link>), making it straightforward to add support for
  a new resource, as I have done for
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/zotero/translators/blob/master/NCBI%20Nucleotide.js">GenBank
  nucleotide sequence datasets</ext-link> in November after learning the
  basics in a
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://blog.martinfenner.org/2014/10/17/webinar-on-writing-zotero-translators/">webinar</ext-link>
  given by Sebastian Karcher, a frequent contributor to Zotero web
  translators.</p>
  <p>There is no technical reason that reference managers can’t support
  a broad range of objects to cite, including datasets. And integration
  of data citation into the reference manager workflow is not only the
  easiest and most natural way for the author of a paper, but also makes
  it easier to discover these citations - reference lists are simply
  much better for that than links in the text, in particular if the
  content is behind subscription walls. There is a long tradition in the
  life sciences to put identifiers for genetic sequences used in a
  publication right into the text (usually into the methods section).
  Links in the body text are worse than references in reference lists,
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://blog.martinfenner.org/2013/07/02/auto-generating-links-to-data-and-resources/">identifiers
  without a link</ext-link> are even worse, as they are very hard to
  find in an automated way (Kafkas, Kim, &amp; McEntyre, 2013).</p>
  <p>Please come to our workshop on Sunday afternoon if you are in
  Oxford and are interested in this topic.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.eventbrite.com/e/data-citation-support-in-reference-managers-tickets-15136593960">Registration</ext-link>
  is free, and the workshop will include both presentations about the
  current state of data citation support in the reference managers
  Endnote, Papers, Mendeley and Zotero, and work in smaller groups on
  practical implementations.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="references">
  <title>References</title>
  <p>Kafkas, Ş., Kim, J.-H., &amp; McEntyre, J. R. (2013). Database
  Citation in Full Text Biomedical Articles. <italic>PLoS ONE</italic>.
  https://doi.org/<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0063184">10.1371/journal.pone.0063184</ext-link></p>
  <p>Klein, M., Van de Sompel, H., Sanderson, R., Shankar, H.,
  Balakireva, L., Zhou, K., &amp; Tobin, R. (2014). Scholarly context
  not found: one in five articles suffers from reference rot.
  <italic>PLoS ONE</italic>, <italic>9</italic>(12), e115253.
  https://doi.org/<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0115253">10.1371/journal.pone.0115253</ext-link></p>
  <p>Pampel, H., Vierkant, P., Scholze, F., Bertelmann, R., Kindling,
  M., Klump, J., … Dierolf, U. (2013). Making Research Data Repositories
  Visible: The re3data.org Registry. <italic>PLoS ONE</italic>,
  <italic>8</italic>(11), e78080.
  https://doi.org/<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0078080">10.1371/journal.pone.0078080</ext-link></p>
  <p>Data Citation Synthesis Group. (2014). <italic>Joint Declaration of
  Data Citation Principles</italic>. Force11.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.25490/A97F-EGYK">https://doi.org/10.25490/A97F-EGYK</ext-link></p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
