<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Designer debacles and other misdemeanors</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2008-05-15">
<day>15</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2008</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>In the last issue of Nature, a
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611103129/http://www.nature.com/news/2008/080514/full/453275a.html">news
feature</ext-link> and
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611103129/http://www.nature.com/nature/journal/v453/n7193/full/453260a.html">research
highlight</ext-link> look at two recent high-profile paper retractions.
The two papers by biochemist Homme Hellinga delt with rational enzyme
design. A second group couldn't reproduce the results, ultimately
leading to the paper retractions. Then a third group was able to
demonstrate that rational enzyme design is indeed possible.</p>
<p>The research highlight looks at the troubles of the second reseach
group led by John Richard. He wasted a lot of time and money trying to
reproduce Hellinga's findings and in the end did not gain anything.</p>
<p>Non-reproducible work is a common problem in research, and papers
containing this questionable work are rarely retracted. I would guess
that most of the time this is unintentional. John P. A. Ioannidis
explains this in an PLoS Medicine essay:
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611103129/http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pmed.0020124">Why
most published research findings are false</ext-link>.</p>
<p>Sometimes the reasons behind non-reproducible results can be
calculated, and this includes drug trials in clinical medicine.
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611103129/http://jco.ascopubs.org/cgi/content/abstract/25/23/3482">Statistical
Power of Negative Randomized Controlled Trials Presented at American
Society for Clinical Oncology Annual Meetings</ext-link> found that more
than half of these randomized controlled trials that showed no benefit
for a new treatment did not have enough patients to detect even a
medium-sized treatment effect.</p>
<p>What should we do about this? The first step is to accept the fact
that a significant number of research findings you read in a paper are
not reproducible. We have to be careful to start a PhD thesis or other
research project based on a few exciting papers, especially when this
work was done by someone else. Thinking about this, I should have taken
that advice myself before starting a particular project 5 years ago.</p>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
