<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Did you receive spam because you published a
paper?</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2011-07-13">
<day>13</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2011</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Brendan Thomas has published an interesting paper that looks at
author email addresses in the PubMed database of biomedical literature.
Email addresses of first authors have been added to PubMed since 1996,
and they can be retrieved via the standard web interface or automated
software. This makes PubMed an excellent place to find the email address
of an academic author, but also shows that PubMed is very vulnerable to
email address harvesting.</p>
<p>The problem is not limited to PubMed; this is also an issue with many
scholarly journals. Email addresses are used as contact information in
scholarly papers, and they are commonly displayed on journal webpages.
You can harvest email addresses from
<italic><italic>NEJM</italic></italic>,
<italic><italic>Science</italic></italic> or
<italic><italic>PLoS</italic></italic> webpages, and you don’t even need
a subscription. <italic><italic>JAMA</italic></italic> is hiding the
email address, and <italic><italic>Nature</italic></italic> is providing
an author contact form. Both journals provide the email address in the
PDF.</p>
<p>Most journals provide the postal address of corresponding authors.
Journals added email addresses in the 1990s, and this of course has
become the preferred method of communication among scientists – when was
the last time you received a postcard for a reprint request?
Unfortunately we have long learned that it is no longer safe to make
email addresses publicly available – more than 90% of email traffic is
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611043917/http://www.ftc.gov/bcp/edu/microsites/spam/">spam</ext-link>.</p>
<p>Journal publishers have to rethink their policies regarding contact
information of their authors. And authors should demand from journals
that their email addresses are treated with more respect for privacy.
There are better ways to provide contact information for corresponding
authors, and I don’t mean a link to their Twitter account or LinkedIn
profile. Journal publishers should create author profile pages that not
only list all publications of a particular author, but also the relevant
contact information. There should be contact forms instead of plain
email addresses, and authors should be able to control what information
is displayed in their author profile. Author profiles of course can be
further extended in many ways, from links to publications with other
publishers to author-level metrics.</p>
<p><italic><italic>Disclaimer: I sit on the Board of Directors of the
Open Researcher &amp; Contributor ID (ORCID) initiative which aims to
help solve this and related problems.</italic></italic></p>
<sec id="references">
  <title>References</title>
  <p><bold><bold>Thomas, B.</bold></bold> (2011). E-mail Address
  Harvesting on PubMed–A Call for Responsible Handling of E-mail
  Addresses. <italic><italic>Mayo Clinic Proceedings Mayo
  Clinic</italic></italic>, 86(4), 362.
  https://doi.org/<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.4065/mcp.2010.0817">10.4065/mcp.2010.0817</ext-link></p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
