<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Do online journals narrow science and
scholarship?</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2008-07-19">
<day>19</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2008</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>James Evans, a sociologist from the University of Chicago,
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611091345/http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.1150473">reports</ext-link>
his research on the kind and frequency of citations over the last 60
years in the latest issue of <italic><italic>Science</italic></italic>.
He found a change in citation behavior as more and more journals became
electronically available: fewer journals and articles were cited and the
cited articles were more recent.</p>
<p>These findings seem to contradict our expectations (and
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611091345/http://www.sciencemag.org/cgi/doi/10.1126/science.321.5887.329a">research
by other groups</ext-link>). The greater availability of research papers
in recent years thanks to electronic publication (and open access)
should broaden and not narrow the papers that we read and ultimately
cite in our own publications. But looking at my own behavior when
reading papers or writing a publication, and thinking about many
discussions we had on related topics, these findings make perfect
sense.</p>
<p>Today's technology allows us to make the distribution of scientific
papers in electronic form very efficient, and thanks to this technology
we have new business models (author-pays) and an ever-increasing number
of journals. Access to research articles is now easier, cheaper and for
a broader audience than in ever was before. This is of course a
wonderful development, but unfortunately creates a new problem:
<italic><italic>information overflow</italic></italic> and how to filter
out the relevant information.</p>
<p>Twenty years ago the typical researcher would use the personal or
institutional journal subscription to regularly follow the important
papers in his field. <italic><italic>Index Medicus</italic></italic> and
<italic><italic>Current Contents</italic></italic> were used to find
additional articles, but they were cumbersome to use. Today few
researchers regularly read printed journals. Most papers are found by
searches of online databases and by subscriptions of tables of content
by email or RSS. There are many clever tools to facilitate this, but
most people probably are overwhelmed by the information and stick to
some very specific research interests and high-profile journals.</p>
<p>This is where the filtering of information becomes critical.
Technology can help a great deal in finding the most relevant research
papers, but I would argue that human intervention is still far more
important. For most people including myself peer review is the first
step in that filtering process. Connected to peer review is the
editorial decision that something is not only scientifically sound but
also interesting. This editorial decision is sometimes debatable but is
a very effective filtering process. Post-publication filtering by human
intervention in the form of comments, voting or paid services (e.g.
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611091345/http://www.f1000biology.com/">Faculty
of 1000 Biology</ext-link>) is still in its infancy.</p>
<p>I am hoping for better filtering tools in the future, both pre- and
post-publication. I'm confident that technology can be a big help
(especially when full-text searching takes off), but will never replace
human editing. Until then, maybe we should kep at least some important
print subscriptions so that we don't miss that fascinating research
paper that for some reason wasn't picked up by that fancy electronic
tool.</p>
<p>David Crotty (in his highly recommended blog <italic><italic>Bench
Marks</italic></italic>) also
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611091345/http://www.cshblogs.org/cshprotocols/2008/07/18/scientific-citations-and-the-alleged-death-of-the-long-tail/">blogged
about this topic</ext-link>. Philip Davis also
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611091345/http://scholarlykitchen.sspnet.org/2008/07/18/online-journal-paradox/">wrote
about</ext-link> the <italic><italic>Science</italic></italic> article
on <italic><italic>the scholarly kitchen</italic></italic> blog. And
Thomas Lemberger
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611091345/http://blog-msb.embo.org/blog/2008/07/impact_of_online_publishing.html">blogged
about the article</ext-link> on <italic><italic>The Seven
Stones</italic></italic>.</p>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
