<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Endnote: Interview with Jason Rollins</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2010-08-03">
<day>3</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2010</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Reference management is a frequent topic on this blog. The last few
years we have seen both a large increase in the number of
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120524201927/http://blogs.nature.com/mfenner/2009/03/15/reference-manager-overview">available
tools</ext-link>, but also big changes in
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120524201927/http://blogs.nature.com/mfenner/2010/05/19/post">how
we use reference management software</ext-link>. But for many of us the
first reference management software was Endnote.</p>
<p>I first used Endnote as a medical student in 1990 (Endnote Plus at
that time, published by Niles Software), and I’m still a regular user. I
can’t say that for many other programs (probably also Microsoft Word,
Excel and Powerpoint, Adobe Photoshop, SPSS and until recently
Freehand). The latest version – Endnote X4 – was just released/is about
to be released (Windows in June, Macintosh in August). This is a good
opportunity to look at how Endnote has changed over the years and why it
is still such a popular application. For this I interviewed
<italic><italic>Jason Rollins</italic></italic>, who is leading the
Endnote development team.</p>
<fig>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120524201927im_/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/files/2010/11/endnote_group.jpg" xlink:title="" />
</fig>
<p><italic><italic>Members of the EndNote development team: Jason
Rollins, Jiaquan Ma, David Pedrick, Rachel Hubbard, Mayra Aguas, Paul
Patanella, Lisa Epps, Lynette Grabow, Howard Harrison, Jennifer Melinn,
Bill Colsher, Tilla Edmunds, Gandalf Sollenberger (with the Philadelphia
in the background).</italic></italic></p>
<sec id="1-what-is-endnote">
  <title>1. What is EndNote?</title>
  <p>Researchers around the world depend on EndNote to simplify
  collaboration, reference collection, and bibliography formatting. It
  is these researchers who have molded the EndNote you see today,
  allowing us to address the pain points as technology evolves. While
  EndNote originated on the Macintosh and Windows desktops, users now
  have the added combination of the Web where they can transfer
  reference groups and share them with colleagues easily. EndNote
  connects to many parts of the research landscape including online
  resources for both basic bibliographic information and full text, word
  processors,
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120524201927/http://www.researcherid.com/">ResearcherID</ext-link>
  for uniquely identifying personal works that will dovetail into the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120524201927/http://www.orcid.org/">ORCID</ext-link>
  initiative as well as decreasing time to publish when submitting
  EndNote formatted documents into publishing systems.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="2-how-is-endnote-different-from-other-reference-managers">
  <title>2. How is EndNote different from other reference
  managers?</title>
  <p>EndNote defined reference management software for generations of
  researchers and continues to offer the highest quality formatting
  available in any tool. Today some variation of the core functionality
  – searching, organizing, sharing, and citing of scholarly reference
  material – is available in many competing tools.</p>
  <p>Two key differences between EndNote and other reference management
  tools include gathering and formatting references. First, EndNote is
  far more accurate and flexible when it comes to the variety of
  publishing styles it supports. EndNote not only provides
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120524201927/http://www.endnote.com/support/enstyles.asp">over
  4,500 formatting styles</ext-link> but it also allows for the most
  control and customization of this formatting. Our EndNote team works
  closely with leading publishers and editors across many academic
  disciplines to ensure that EndNote offers the formatting control our
  users need to meet exacting publisher specifications. Most of the
  power of this formatting is built-in and achieved automatically by
  EndNote – without the user having to think about it. Of course there
  are many customization options too; these allow users to easily make
  changes and tweaks to the way EndNote formats citations, footnotes,
  and bibliographies.</p>
  <p>Second, EndNote offers the best options for easy import and export
  of user data. The Online Search, Find Full Text, importing, and Web
  capture options are all features that make it easy to obtain accurate
  bibliographic information and manage full text data in EndNote. The
  “RIS Tagged Data” format has become a de facto standard for hundreds
  of databases and software tools. Plus, the EndNote XML specification
  is something that is openly shared with partners and competitors alike
  in hopes of making it easier for our customers to move their data into
  and out of any system they may need to use.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="3-what-is-new-in-endnote-x4">
  <title>3. What is new in EndNote X4?</title>
  <p>There’s a
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120524201927/http://www.endnote.com/enx4wnvid/Whats_New-SD.asp">longer
  list of new and improved features</ext-link>, but a few of the key
  features are new PDF functions, better support for collaborative
  writing and more robust footnote handling.</p>
  <fig>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120524201927im_/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/files/2010/11/endnote_screenshot.jpg" xlink:title="" />
  </fig>
  <p>EndNote X4 can create records from PDFs using metadata and a DOI,
  attaching the original file to the newly created reference. Then, PDFs
  are further incorporated into users’ libraries by indexing the
  attached files and making them searchable along with the reference
  data.</p>
  <p>The connection between EndNote and a word processor is more visible
  by incorporating cited references from documents right into the
  EndNote interface. This way, users can work with their references in a
  word processor, and focus on the references in a particular paper
  while managing things in EndNote. Editing and managing individual
  citations in Word now combines all the functionality in one place
  which is a big help for people working on large projects, or
  collaboratively. The “Traveling Library” sharing feature in Word has
  also been significantly improved to help people work together. The APA
  6th style is fully supported and EndNote X4 offers much more
  customization and intelligence to the way footnote formatting styles
  are handled.</p>
  <p>The full list of features, online videos, and a free trial version
  of EndNote X4 are available at
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120524201927/http://www.endnote.com/">www.endnote.com</ext-link>.
  EndNote version X4 was released in June for Windows with the Macintosh
  version available by the end of this summer.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="4-how-does-endnote-handle-pdf-management-can-you-share-pdf-files-with-other-users">
  <title>4. How does EndNote handle PDF management? Can you share PDF
  files with other users?</title>
  <p>With version X4, we have added more PDF-related functionality to
  EndNote. Now, you can import PDF meta-data and search the full text of
  attached PDF files. You can share EndNote library files that contain
  PDF attachments easily – or any other file type. EndNote Web does not
  currently support direct file attachments but this is something we are
  currently working on.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="5-what-is-endnote-web-how-does-it-relate-to-endnote">
  <title>5. What is EndNote Web, how does it relate to EndNote?</title>
  <p>EndNote provides
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120524201927/http://www.endnoteweb.com/">EndNote
  Web</ext-link> to users for easy sharing and collaboration features.
  Transferring references up to the web provides extra flexibility to
  work with EndNote references anywhere. There’s a browser plug-in
  available with EndNote Web, that captures and saves references from
  web pages and allows users to send references to a desktop or
  web-based library. The web version has some features that the desktop
  doesn’t, and vice versa; each is complimentary to the other. EndNote
  Web is also integrated into the Web of Knowledge database platform and
  a limited version of EndNote Web is provided to ResearcherID users for
  managing their personal publication list.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="6-can-i-use-endnote-with-collaborative-writing-tools-such-as-google-docs-or-microsoft-office-live">
  <title>6. Can I use EndNote with collaborative writing tools such as
  Google Docs or Microsoft Office Live?</title>
  <p>While we do not have any custom built plug-ins or similar tools for
  Google Docs or Microsoft Office Live, as always, it’s easy to
  drag-and-drop or copy-and-paste in EndNote citations. If you look
  closely at other products that claim to be compatible, you’ll see that
  they are offering a simple copy and paste function as well. Based on
  our research thus far, these writing tools do not yet offer the right
  APIs to build more robust integration. This is something we hear from
  customers quite often so we will keep an eye on developments and hope
  to offer something more once the APIs are available.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="7-how-does-endnote-help-with-reference-management-beyond-writing-manuscripts-e-g-reading-lists-for-students-writing-blog-posts-etc-">
  <title>7. How does EndNote help with reference management beyond
  writing manuscripts, e.g reading lists for students, writing blog
  posts, etc.?</title>
  <p>You can easily use EndNote to include citations, hyperlinks, or any
  other reference data into nearly any type of document in almost any
  format and customize the output for your specific needs. You can share
  groups of references with both read only and read-write access; this
  supports sharing reading lists and more involved collaboration. But,
  reference management has evolved into so much more than just finding
  things to insert into a document. With the grouping, searching, and
  file attachment options, EndNote is a way to organize the majority of
  your research. These features make EndNote robust and flexible at
  handling a huge volume of items. Plus, you’ve always been able to
  store files of any type with EndNote, therefore making it possible to
  utilize much of the organizational capabilities for non-traditional
  sources like video clips or datasets.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="8-endnote-has-seen-many-updates-since-its-initial-release-more-than-20-years-ago-what-do-you-see-as-some-of-the-most-significant-changes-during-that-time">
  <title>8. EndNote has seen many updates since its initial release more
  than 20 years ago. What do you see as some of the most significant
  changes during that time?</title>
  <p>EndNote started out for the Mac Plus and DOS; so clearly a lot has
  changed along with many of the major developments in personal software
  technology since the late 1980′s. EndNote introduced online searching
  and direct export to simplify the movement of references from
  discovery to a personal collection for citing in papers. Cite While
  You Write is often imitated but never duplicated for ease of use when
  citing references in Apple Pages, Microsoft Word, and OpenOffice.org
  Writer. The fundamental problem that EndNote has been solving for our
  customers has morphed over the years. While keeping up with changes in
  formatting rules and reference types, which have always been the core
  strength of EndNote, we have also evolved EndNote into a more complete
  reference management solution. Where at one time the majority of our
  users worked alone on a single computer writing a static manuscript,
  today most customers interact with a global network of collaborators
  on multiple projects that might be delivered in several formats. Now
  with EndNote Web and ResearcherID, EndNote users can easily promote
  their work and connect with others. Another area that has
  significantly changed over the last twenty years is the means by which
  users access research material, and as our user’s focus has shifted
  from basic reference data and description to inclusion of the full
  text of sources and supporting documentation, EndNote has too. EndNote
  supports this with OpenURL linking, proxy and open source
  authentication, browser plug-ins, and other functions.</p>
  <p>Many of the developments we currently have underway will further
  support online sharing and connectivity and should prove to be some of
  the most valuable including mobile functionality and more.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="9-what-are-your-responsibilities-at-thomson-reuters">
  <title>9. What are your responsibilities at Thomson Reuters?</title>
  <p>My team is responsible for the development of bibliographic
  management tools. This involves leading the development teams for
  EndNote and Reference Manager, listening to customer input, and
  coordinating partnerships.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="10-what-did-you-do-before-working-at-thomson-reuters">
  <title>10. What did you do before working at Thomson Reuters?</title>
  <p>I joined the EndNote team in 2001. Before that, I was completing a
  PhD in Educational Technology from Drexel University and working for
  two different consulting firms and a small web start-up.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
