<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Evolving English at the British Library</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2010-11-24">
<day>24</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2010</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>On Saturday I went to see the exhibition
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611032112/http://www.bl.uk/evolvingenglish/">Evolving
English</ext-link> at the British Library in London. The exhibition
explores the English language in all its diversity and was recommended
to me by Matt Brown, expert on all things London (his review for the
Londonist is
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611032112/http://londonist.com/2010/11/review_evolving_english_british_lib.php">here</ext-link>).
<bold><bold>Evolving English</bold></bold> is interesting in many
different ways, but here I want to focus on English as the language of
science – used in two examples in the exhibition.</p>
<p>The book <italic><italic>Micrographia</italic></italic> from 1665 by
Robert Hooke is the first major scientific work devoted to exploration
using the microscope. It is also an important step in the development of
scientific English. The book was praised for the clarity of the language
at the time, but from today’s science writing perspective contains
sentences that are too long and convoluted, uses conversational English,
and frequently the active voice. The National Library of Medicine
provides a beautiful
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611032112/http://archive.nlm.nih.gov/proj/ttp/flash/hooke/hooke.html">online
version</ext-link> of the book, where observation XXV starts with:</p>
<p specific-use="wrapper">
  <disp-quote>
    <p><italic><italic>A nettle is a plant so well known to every one,
    as to what the appearance of it is to the naked eye, that it needs
    no description; and there are very few that have not felt as well as
    seen it; and therefore it will be no news to tell that a gentle and
    slight touch of the skin by a nettle, does oftentime, not onely
    create very sensible and acute pain, much like that of a burn or
    scald, but often also very angry and hard swellings and
    inflammations of the parts, such as will presently rise and continue
    swoln divers hours.</italic></italic></p>
  </disp-quote>
</p>
<p>As an example of current scientific English, the exhibitors picked
the paper describing the cloning of Dolly (Wilmut 1997). The text is
described in the exhibition as:</p>
<p specific-use="wrapper">
  <disp-quote>
    <p><italic><italic>The language is punctual throughout and technical
    terms are mostly used without explanation. The main text is
    supported by illustrations (here called figures), tables of data and
    – over the page – bibliographic references to other scientific
    research. The purpose is to to maximize accuracy, remove any chance
    of ambiguity and provide writers with every opportunity to give
    detailed evidence.</italic></italic></p>
  </disp-quote>
</p>
<p>The exhibition makes it very clear that the English language is
constantly evolving, and scientific English is no exception. Papers
written in 10, 20 or 100 years might use a very different language. One
important influence today is of course science writing in blogs and
other social media. And with electronic publishing, open access, citizen
science and other trends, scientific papers have become available to a
much larger audience.</p>
<sec id="references">
  <title>References</title>
  <p>Wilmut I, Schnieke AE, McWhir J, Kind AJ, Campbell KH. Viable
  offspring derived from fetal and adult mammalian cells.
  <italic><italic>Nature</italic></italic>. 1997;385:810-813. DOI:
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611032112/http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/385810a0">http://doi.org/10.1038/385810a0</ext-link>.
  </p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
