<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Example article with embedded code and
data</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2013-12-11">
<day>11</day>
<month>12</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>In October I published an essay on Article-Level Metrics (ALM) in
PLOS Biology (Fenner, 2013). The essay is a good introduction into
Article-Level Metrics, and I am proud that it is part of the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/issue.pcol.v06.i03">Tenth
Anniversary PLOS Biology Collection</ext-link>. Like all PLOS content,
the article was published with a
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://blogs.plos.org/tech/creative-commons-for-science-interview-with-puneet-kishor/">Creative
Commons attribution license</ext-link>, allowing me to republish the
article on this blog. I have now done so and the article is available
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://blog.martinfenner.org/2013/12/11/what-can-article-level-metrics-do-for-you/">here</ext-link>.</p>
<p>Of course I didn’t want to simply republish the article, but I wanted
to publish an improved version. The article has five figures, four of
them show visualizations of ALM data that were generated using R (the
fifth figure is a table reproduced from another article). The PLOS
article includes the ALM dataset and the R scripts used to generate the
figures as
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.1001687.s001">supplementary
information</ext-link>. What I have done now is to recreate the article
as a single markdown file (available
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/mfenner/blog/blob/master/_posts/2013-12-11-what-can-article-level-metrics-do-for-you.Rmd">here</ext-link>)
that has all R code embedded. Using R and
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://yihui.name/knitr/">knitr</ext-link>
- and the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://blog.martinfenner.org/data/alm_report_plos_biology_2013-05-20.csv">CSV
file with the ALM data</ext-link> - everyone can now reproduce the
figures from the paper by simply running the embedded code, and can dig
deeper into the data.</p>
<fig>
  <caption><p><bold>Figure 3.</bold> Views vs. citations for PLOS
  Biology articles published in 2010.</p></caption>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="svg+xml" xlink:href="http://blog.martinfenner.org/images/2013-12-11_figure_3.svg" xlink:title="" />
</fig>
<p>This was a good opportunity to improve the accessibility of the
article in other ways. Instead of the raster image formats PNG, JPEG and
TIFF used by PLOS and almost every other publisher, I generated the
figures in the vector format SVG. Not only does SVG produce images
independent of device resolution and screen size (try to zoom in on the
figure above), but SVG can also easily be manipulated in the browser
since it is XML. This is beyond the scope of this blog post, but look at
the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://d3js.org/">d3.js</ext-link>
Javascript library for great examples of how SVG can be dynamically
generated and changed in the browser. <bold><bold>Figure 3</bold></bold>
above could for example be enhanced so that the article title is
displayed when you hover over one of the bubbles, or we could enable
zooming to show more detail.</p>
<p>Like all content on this blog, the article was created using
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://johnmacfarlane.net/pandoc/">Pandoc</ext-link>,
and the bibliography was dynamically generated. This makes it easy to
change the citation style, and I decided to use the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.apastyle.org/">APA
Style</ext-link> that shows the citations in the text as author-date
rather than numbered as with the PLOS style (see the example citation in
the first paragraph). The combined bibliography for all blog posts
including the article can be downloaded in bibtex format
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://blog.martinfenner.org/bibliography/references.bib">here</ext-link>.</p>
<p>Lastly, I wanted to generate nicer HTML for a better online reading
experience. I haven’t done anything fancy, but most publishers seem to
focus on navigation around an article, so that very little screen real
estate is left for the actual content of the article. I’ve tried to
improve readability by reducing the navigation areas to a minimum, by
using readable fonts in larger sizes:
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://typekit.com/fonts/minion-pro">Adobe
Minion Pro</ext-link> for the body text and
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://typekit.com/fonts/myriad-pro">Adobe
Myriad Pro</ext-link> for headings, tables and figure legends.</p>
<sec id="references">
  <title>References</title>
  <p>Fenner, M. (2013). What can article-level metrics do for you?
  <italic>PLoS Biol</italic>, <italic>11</italic>(10), e1001687.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.1001687">doi:10.1371/journal.pbio.1001687</ext-link></p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
