<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Faculty of 1000: Interview with Richard
Grant</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2009-04-28">
<day>28</day>
<month>4</month>
<year>2009</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003075116/http://network.nature.com/people/rpg/blog">Richard
Grant</ext-link>, who needs no introduction here on Nature Network, has
just moved to London
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003075116/http://network.nature.com/people/rpg/blog/2009/04/09/on-the-payroll">to
start a new job</ext-link> as <italic><italic>information
architect</italic></italic> for
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003075116/http://www.f1000biology.com/">Faculty
of 1000</ext-link>. I took this opportunity to ask Richard a few
questions not only about Faculty of 1000, but also about his role in the
company and future plans for the service that they have in mind.</p>
<fig>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003075116im_/http://friendfeed.s3.amazonaws.com/f353fdfe5c24bfb525680563a4a5c04b3760fafd" xlink:title="" />
</fig>
<sec id="1-can-you-describe-what-faculty-of-1000-is-and-does">
  <title>1. Can you describe what Faculty of 1000 is and does?</title>
  <p>The scientific literature is immense, and growing. It has become
  very difficult to keep up, especially if you’re going to keep an eye
  on developments not immediately in your own area. For someone new to a
  field it’s almost impossible to know — without insider knowledge —
  what papers are important, which are the key publications; where a
  field is going and what are the key developments.</p>
  <p>So what we do is provide a kind of ‘filter’ on top of the
  literature: we have about five thousand principle investigators, who
  we call ‘Faculty’, across biology and medicine, who in the course of
  their own reading will write short evaluations on the important and
  influential papers in their field. We’re also recruiting
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003075116/http://www.f1000biology.com/about/associateFMs">Associate
  Faculty members</ext-link>: trusted junior members of a Faculty
  member’s lab or practice who will write their own evaluations and
  increase our coverage. And we’re not just talking about stuff that’s
  published in <italic><italic>Nature</italic></italic> or
  <italic><italic>Cell</italic></italic> — or
  <italic><italic>NEJM</italic></italic> or <italic><italic>The
  Lancet</italic></italic> — but in the specialized, work-a-day
  journals. What’s more, this expert opinion, or what we’re calling
  ‘post-publication peer review’, gives our users a measure of the
  ‘quality’ of individual papers that is independent of, and much
  quicker than, the impact factor of the journal.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="2-what-part-of-faculty-of-1000-is-free-and-what-part-needs-a-paid-subscription">
  <title>2. What part of Faculty of 1000 is free and what part needs a
  paid subscription</title>
  <p>You can search or browse the entire database, and sign up for email
  alerts, so you can see which papers have been evaluated. You can’t
  actually read the evaluations themselves unless you have an
  institutional or personal subscription.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="3-how-does-faculty-of-1000-integrate-with-reference-managers-such-as-endnote-refworks-zotero-or-connotea">
  <title>3. How does Faculty of 1000 integrate with reference managers
  such as Endnote, Refworks, Zotero or Connotea?</title>
  <p>You can download evaluations into a reference manager just like you
  can papers from PubMed. We’re working on proper integration with
  online tools (such as
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003075116/http://www.citeulike.org/">CiteULike</ext-link>
  and
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003075116/http://www.connotea.org/">Connotea</ext-link>)
  and other ‘social media’ tools. I’m also keen to work with
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003075116/http://www.mendeley.com/">Mendeley</ext-link>
  to improve the user experience.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="4-what-are-the-incentives-for-faculty-members-to-evaluate-papers">
  <title>4. What are the incentives for faculty members to evaluate
  papers?</title>
  <p>Exposure and kudos, mainly! The Faculty member’s name is displayed
  prominently on the evaluations (you can see who’s written an
  evaluation even without a subscription). Reputation is important to
  scientists and being invited to become a Faculty member says to the
  rest of the community that your opinion is respected and your peers
  think highly of you. We also profile Faculty members who write timely
  or important evaluations, or who have news of their own (grants,
  papers, awards) and give them publicity through press releases,
  etc.</p>
  <p>What’s more, our Faculty members
  <italic><italic>like</italic></italic> the combination of expert
  opinion and original articles. They see a value in it, and realize
  that there’s a kind of synergy going on here; if they contribute then
  others will be encouraged to too, and everybody wins.</p>
  <p>I’d like to explore how evaluations might become citable — so that
  Faculty can put their work for us on their CV, how it might benefit
  their career, grant applications etc. We’re also considering more
  tangible benefits.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="5-how-are-faculty-members-selected">
  <title>5. How are faculty members selected?</title>
  <p>The Heads of Faculty, for each subject or speciality, are elected
  or selected on the recommendation of large numbers of medics and
  scientists we talk to. They divide their Faculty into Sections and
  then select two or three Section Heads. These scientists in turn
  identify the sub-fields within their Section and select Faculty
  Members, checking with Heads of Faculty. The Section Heads select
  Faculty Members on the basis of various criteria:</p>
  <list list-type="bullet">
    <list-item>
      <p>the number of Faculty Members should be proportionally
      representative of the number of papers published within that
      field;</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>the selected Faculty Members should be well respected by their
      peers and perceived as being fair-minded;</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>there must be a good representation of genders, nationalities
      and age/seniority.</p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
  <p>Faculty Members themselves are being asked to co-opt younger
  workers within their groups — post-docs, say — to help increase
  coverage and to write their own evaluations. We call these ‘Associate
  Faculty’.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="6-can-faculty-of-1000-users-comment-on-papers-or-paper-evaluations">
  <title>6. Can Faculty of 1000 users comment on papers or paper
  evaluations?</title>
  <p>Not at the moment, no. Faculty members can comment, or contribute a
  ‘dissent’ if they disagree with an evaluation, and authors of the
  evaluated papers are encouraged to respond, but we feel it’s important
  for users to know that they can trust what we publish. However, we’re
  currently planning to launch a forum whereby users
  <italic><italic>can</italic></italic> comment freely on evaluated
  papers. This would be open to anyone who registers, without a
  subscription, but kept distinct from the main evaluation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="7-can-paper-authors-comment-on-evaluations-of-their-papers">
  <title>7. Can paper authors comment on evaluations of their
  papers?</title>
  <p>Yes! At the moment we get emails from authors saying that they’re
  pleased to have their papers selected, but we’re going to make it
  possible for them to comment on the evaluations directly so that a
  conversation with the Faculty can be initiated.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="8-what-is-faculty-of-1000-reports">
  <title>8. What is Faculty of 1000 Reports?</title>
  <p>F1000 Reports carries short reviews, or commentaries, on emerging
  trends identified from within the F1000 database.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003075116/http://f1000medicine.com/reports/">F1000
  Medicine Reports</ext-link> features studies that are likely to change
  clinical practice and summarizes implications for clinicians.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003075116/http://www.f1000biology.com/reports/">F1000
  Biology Reports</ext-link> contextualizes important and exciting
  papers or clusters of publications. The Advisory Board (for
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003075116/http://f1000biology.com/reports/advisoryboard">F1000
  Biology Reports</ext-link> and
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003075116/http://f1000medicine.com/reports/advisoryboard">F1000
  Medicine Reports</ext-link>) identifies potential topics and invites
  appropriate Faculty members to write about them.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="9-what-are-your-responsibilities-at-faculty-of-1000">
  <title>9. What are your responsibilities at Faculty of 1000?</title>
  <p>Well, my job title is ‘Information Architect’, which means quite a
  bit more than ‘web manager’. I have overall responsibility for the
  presentation of the F1000 service, and I have to ensure that the web
  site is fast and intuitive, and that the content is suitable for both
  medics and biologists. I’m also keen to keep F1000 relevant in the Web
  2.0 world.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="10-what-did-you-do-before-starting-to-work-for-faculty-of-1000">
  <title>10. What did you do before starting to work for Faculty of
  1000?</title>
  <p>I was at the University of Sydney for three years, the token cell
  biologist in an NMR lab, looking at RNA-binding zinc fingers. Before
  that I was at the MRC-LMB in Cambridge for six years, learning how to
  do X-ray crystallography and NMR and applying those techniques to cell
  biological questions.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="11-do-you-want-to-talk-about-future-plans-for-faculty-of-1000">
  <title>11. Do you want to talk about future plans for Faculty of
  1000?</title>
  <p>As I’ve sorted of already hinted, we’re in the middle of a major
  redesign. We have some new features that I hope you’ll find very
  exciting — one of which I really can’t talk about yet! — including
  forums, a re-vamped ‘MyF1000′ site, integration of F1000 Reports, more
  systematic literature scanning, talking to social media sites, RSS (at
  last!), a blog, and a lot of behind the scenes tweaks.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="12-where-can-we-provide-feedback-about-faculty-of-1000">
  <title>12. Where can we provide feedback about Faculty of
  1000?</title>
  <p>Write to me! Or email info@f1000.com. The new site will also have a
  feedback form.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
