<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>FDAAA: Push to open data in clinical
medicine</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2008-08-02">
<day>2</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2008</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>In 2005 registration of clinical trials in publicly available
databases before the first patient was entered became
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611042509/http://www.icmje.org/clin_trial.pdf">mandatory</ext-link>
for papers submitted to the most important medical journals. In
September of last year, U.S. President Bush signed the Federal Drug
Administration Amendment Act (FDAAA) into law. Starting September 2008,
all clinical trials registered in the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611042509/http://www.clinicaltrials.gov/">clinicaltrials.gov</ext-link>
database (with the exception of phase I trials) have to report key
results of the main outcomes no later than 12 months after data for the
last subject were received.</p>
<p>This required reporting of results has so far largely gone unnoticed
in the medical community, but will dramatically change the way research
involving patients is conducted and reported. The 12 month deadline will
probably lead to earlier reporting of many trial results, and not
publishing negative results will be much more difficult. The required
reporting in a standardized format will also facilitate the
meta-analysis of several similar trials.</p>
<p>Reporting of trial results in this format
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611042509/http://www.bmj.com/cgi/content/full/334/7605/1177">will
not be considered previous publication</ext-link> by member journals of
The Internal Committee of Medical Journal Editors (ICMJE).</p>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
