<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Figshare: Interview with Mark Hahnel</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2012-02-16">
<day>16</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<fig>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20161023171633im_/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/files/2012/02/me1.png" xlink:title="me" />
</fig>
<p>fig<bold>share</bold> <italic>allows researchers to publish all of
their research outputs in seconds in an easily citable, sharable and
discoverable manner</italic>. The service was started by Mark Hahnel
last year while still a PhD student. Mark joined
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20161023171633/http://www.digital-science.com/">Digital
Science</ext-link> to work on fig<bold>share</bold> in September and
last month relaunched a much improved version of the service. I asked
Mark a few questions about fig<bold>share</bold> below. I also uploaded
two datasetst to fig<bold>share</bold> and made them publicly
available:</p>
<list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
    <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20161023171633/http://hdl.handle.net/10779/1c48a305c08c717fea3f6fe1687b3eff">CrowdoMeter
    Tweets</ext-link> – all 467 tweets used in the CrowdoMeter
    project</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20161023171633/http://hdl.handle.net/10779/01c28ce592291e7e294ed328208a5869">CrowdoMeter
    Classifications</ext-link> – all 953 classifications from the
    CrowdoMeter project.</p>
  </list-item>
</list>
<sec id="1-what-is-figshare">
  <title>1. What is figshare?</title>
  <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20161023171633/http://figshare.com/">figshare</ext-link>
  is a repository where users can make all of their research outputs
  available in a citable, sharable and discoverable manner. figshare
  allows users to upload any file format so that figures, datasets and
  media can be disseminated in a way that the current scholarly
  publishing model does not allow.</p>
  <fig>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20161023171633im_/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/files/2012/02/screenshot.png" xlink:title="screenshot" />
  </fig>
</sec>
<sec id="2-what-is-the-right-content-for-figshare-and-what-should-rather-go-somewhere-else">
  <title>2. What is the right content for figshare? And what should
  rather go somewhere else?</title>
  <p>Every experiment that is completed without error in the methods is
  valuable. Researchers investigate things because the question is
  interesting and supposedly unanswered. This means that other
  researchers will at some point ask that same question. Just because
  the hypothesis didn’t turn out to be true, doesn’t mean that this data
  should be thrown away.</p>
  <p>With fig<bold>share</bold>, you can share your negative results or
  results that you were not planning to publish. You can make raw data
  available or supplementary material that journals cannot handle linked
  to from the published article. You can even make your papers and
  posters available and citable. People have uploaded whole chapters of
  their PhD thesis to share with the world and make sure that all of
  their hard work is not wasted.</p>
  <p>Currently we are not focusing on handling massive datasets, whilst
  this is an aim for the future. These edgecases seem to be better
  handled by journals set up specifically for publishing these huge
  files, such as the excellent GigaScience.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="3-you-relaunched-figshare-in-january-what-has-changed-to-the-previous-version">
  <title>3. You relaunched figshare in January. What has changed to the
  previous version?</title>
  <p>The old site was a proof of concept based on Mediawiki software.
  The new site has been completely built from scratch so that it is
  rapidly extendable in terms of features and scale. This means that we
  can adapt quickly and easily to the needs of researchers. As well as
  being much more intuitive, the biggest new feature for
  fig<bold>share</bold> is the private space.</p>
  <p>Whilst we would like everyone to make all of their research objects
  available, we appreciate that some researchers would like to keep
  research private for many reasons. Because of this we set about giving
  users their own private repository to store their research objects.
  These objects can be uploaded in seconds and all objects are initially
  held in the private space, from where they can be made publicly
  available when the user decides. All research is easily tagged and
  categorisable, so that researchers can filter through their many files
  to find the one they were looking for in no time at all.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="4-how-important-is-the-user-interface-for-figshare-what-particular-features-do-you-like-the-most">
  <title>4. How important is the user interface for figshare? What
  particular features do you like the most?</title>
  <p>The user interface is essential, researchers are busy enough as it
  it. They haven’t got the time to attend training course on how to use
  a repository. If this was the case with facebook, no one would use
  facebook. For this reason fig<bold>share</bold> is stupidly simple and
  allows users to get their research onto the site in seconds, even the
  PIs. At this point they can choose to make it publicly available and
  immediately citable, sharable and discoverable, or keep it private –
  securely hosted, taggable and accessible when they need it, from
  anywhere in the world.</p>
  <p>This is something we are constantly aiming to improve and we not
  only welcome feedback, we are actively seeking the thoughts of
  researchers on how we can make this a seemless part of their research
  process.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="5-do-you-have-plans-for-a-desktop-version-of-figshare-e-g-to-watch-folders-for-new-figshare-content">
  <title>5. Do you have plans for a desktop version of figshare, e.g. to
  watch folders for new figshare content?</title>
  <p>We do! By creating a desktop uploader, the process becomes even
  more intuitive for researchers, allowing them to make backups of their
  research in the cloud with no effort expenditure. Research data
  management is something I personally was terrible at. My research was
  organised into folders based on the month and the year I did that
  work. I lost days trying to find files that ‘I know I worked on
  sometime last summer’. Hopefully a desktop uploader will add to the
  current simple management system so that researchers like me have no
  excuse when it comes to losing (often expensive) results files.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="6-how-is-figshare-different-from-data-repositories">
  <title>6. How is figshare different from data repositories?</title>
  <p>fig<bold>share</bold> is not limited as many repositories are. It
  caters for all research domains, no matter where your research is
  carried out. Institutional repositories are often limited to members
  of said institution. Also, the majority of institutional repositories
  are built specifically for papers. The Dryad repository has been doing
  some great work making the datasets behind published articles
  available under CC0. fig<bold>share</bold> is not limited by the
  normal constraints of publishing, data generated in the lab can be
  shared and made available to the world as a citable object the same
  day.</p>
  <fig>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20161023171633im_/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/files/2012/02/usermetrics.png" xlink:title="usermetrics" />
  </fig>
  <p>fig<bold>share</bold> also gives the researchers the credit for
  their research. By adding metrics to the public uploads, and putting
  the cumulative metrics of a researcher’s uploads on their profile,
  users can see the true impact and reach of the hard work they put
  in.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="7-you-currently-use-handles-for-figshare-content-what-are-your-thoughts-on-persistent-identifiers-are-the-plans-to-use-dois">
  <title>7. You currently use handles for figshare content. What are
  your thoughts on persistent identifiers? Are the plans to use
  DOIs?</title>
  <p>Persistent identifiers are essential for the long term availability
  of research outputs. One of the reasons I set up figshare was because
  I wanted to cite a video in my thesis. Research data on
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20161023171633/http://figshare.com/blog/A%20YouTube%20%20for%20Scientists/11">YouTube</ext-link>
  is not easily citable, by adding persitent identifiers and an
  organised citation structure, videos as well as any other file format
  can be easily cited. All citations can be exported to
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20161023171633/http://mendeley.com/">Mendeley</ext-link>,
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20161023171633/http://www.endnote.com/">Endnote</ext-link>
  and
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20161023171633/http://www.refman.com/">RefMan</ext-link>with
  one click. We use handles at the moment, but have noticed that
  researchers tend to be more familiar with DOI’s and so will be making
  the move over to them shortly. We’re currently working with
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20161023171633/http://datacite.org/">DataCite</ext-link>
  through the British Library to get this set up.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="8-how-does-figshare-guarantee-long-term-preservation-of-uploaded-data">
  <title>8. How does figshare guarantee long-term preservation of
  uploaded data?</title>
  <p>The long term persistence of this research data is essential. The
  research is backed up locally as soon as it is uploaded. We are
  currently in talks with
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20161023171633/http://www.portico.org/">Portico</ext-link>
  to back up all data and further guarantee this long term
  persistence.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="9-what-are-your-responsibilities-at-figshare-what-did-you-do-before-figshare">
  <title>9. What are your responsibilities at figshare? What did you do
  before Figshare?</title>
  <p>I’m basically responsible for making the platform as useful for
  researchers as possible. I also love going to talk at Universities and
  conferences to researchers directly, to hear their thoughts/opinions.
  As a former life science researcher (I finished my PhD in stem cell
  biology at Imperial College London in September), I understand that
  what makes sense in a rational world does not make sense in the
  scientific world. You just have to look at the established model of
  scientific research dissemination to understand that.
  fig<bold>share</bold> is useful whether you want to make all of your
  research outputs available or none. Science would just be a lot more
  efficient and dynamic if they did.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
