<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>First analysis of software metrics</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2015-02-28">
<day>28</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2015</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Last week
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://martinfenner.ghost.io/2015/02/19/metrics-for-scientific-software/">I
wrote about</ext-link>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://software.lagotto.io/">software.lagotto.io</ext-link>,
an instance of the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/articlemetrics/lagotto">lagotto</ext-link>
open source software collecting metrics for the about 1,400 software
repositories included in
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://sciencetoolbox.org/">Sciencetoolbox</ext-link>.
In this post I want to report the first results analyzing the data.</p>
<p>If you want to follow along, please go to
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/mfenner/software-analysis">https://github.com/mfenner/software-analysis</ext-link>,
this repository holds all the data, as well as the R code used for
analysis. A special thanks goes to
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://scottchamberlain.info/">Scott
Chamberlain</ext-link> who greatly helped me by tweaking the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/ropensci/alm">alm</ext-link>
R package to support URLs instead of DOIs as identifiers.</p>
<p>The first step in the analysis is to get an overview of the external
sources citing or discussing the software package:</p>
<fig>
  <caption><p>Number of software repositories (out of 1,404) with at
  least one event. Data from
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://software.lagotto.io">software.lagotto.io</ext-link></p></caption>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://martinfenner.ghost.io/content/images/2021/01/software.lagotto.io_2.png" xlink:title="" />
</fig>
<p>This is basically the same figure as in the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://martinfenner.ghost.io/2015/02/19/metrics-for-scientific-software/">previous
post</ext-link>, but with two differences: I have added a
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nature.com/opensearch/">Nature.com
OpenSearch</ext-link> data source, and I have found an additional 64
repositories cited in scholarly articles via an Europe PMC fulltext
Search that also includes the reference lists (thanks to
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/about/people/johanna-mcentyre">Jo
McEntyre</ext-link>).</p>
<p>I am not sure why we are not picking up any Wikipedia citations, and
have to take a closer look. The ORCID source also needs tweaking, and
there are some issues with the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://wordpress.com/">Wordpress.com</ext-link>
data that I have to look into as well. Citations in the scholarly
literature are obviously the most interesting data, and we have three
Github repos with more than 25 citations, including
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/najoshi/sickle">https://github.com/najoshi/sickle</ext-link>
with 54 citations. As most repositories in our sample are cited only
once if at all, a correlation with Github stars and forks is not useful.
Sickle is popular on Github (52 stars and 32 forks), but it is not clear
that this activity is correlated to citations (e.g. because there are
more citations than stars).</p>
<p>The vast majority of software repos in this analysis are hosted by
Github, so we have the numbers of stars and forks for those. It is
interesting, although probably not very surprising, that the number of
Github stargazers and forks is highly correlated:</p>
<fig>
  <caption><p>Correlation between Github stargazers and forks, log-log
  scale. Data from
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://software.lagotto.io">software.lagotto.io</ext-link></p></caption>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://martinfenner.ghost.io/content/images/2021/01/github_likes_readers-1.png" xlink:title="" />
</fig>
<p>We can find Facebook activity (likes, comments or shares) for one
third of the repositories. There is a reasonably good correlation
between Facebook activity and number of Github forks:</p>
<fig>
  <caption><p>Correlation between combined Facebook activity and Github
  forks, log-log scale. Data from
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://software.lagotto.io">software.lagotto.io</ext-link></p></caption>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://martinfenner.ghost.io/content/images/2021/01/facebook_github_readers-1.png" xlink:title="" />
</fig>
<p>One interesting analysis would be to look at the repositories that
have been forked much more often relative to their Facebook activity,
e.g.
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/cloudera/impala">Impala</ext-link>
with 1,207 Github stars and 458 forks, but only 5 Facebook shares. One
limitation of the analysis is that we are not tracking Facebook (or
other social media) activity for all forks of a repo.</p>
<p>We found Reddit discussions mentioning one of the repositories in 7%
of cases. Once we have a larger sample size it would be interesting to
correlate this activity with Github stars and forks, similar to what we
did for Facebook. By far the most popular repository from our sample on
Reddit is
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/Bitcoin/Bitcoin">Bitcoin</ext-link>,
followed by
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/jquery/jquery">JQuery</ext-link>.
Twitter activity is notoriously difficult to collect since Twitter
doesn’t keep tweets very long, hence probably the low numbers compared
to Facebook and Reddit.</p>
<p>Feel free to play with the data and scripts provided at
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/mfenner/software-analysis">https://github.com/mfenner/software-analysis</ext-link>,
my next step is probably to include a much larger number of software
repositories.</p>
<p>It has not escaped our notice that the kind of analysis described
above could be applied to any software repository, not just scientific
software.</p>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
