<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Flipboard changes the way we use Twitter</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2010-08-01">
<day>1</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2010</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120628140034/http://www.flipboard.com/">Flipboard</ext-link>
is a <italic><italic>personalized social magazine</italic></italic> for
the iPad. The free application was released on July 22, and instantly
created a lot of buzz. Because of the overwhelming interest, they had to
create a waitlist for the personal features and I could only sign up for
and start using them a few days ago. Flipboard is a true iPad
application, it would not work the same on a laptop computer or mobile
phone.</p>
<fig>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120628140034im_/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/files/2010/11/flipboard3.jpg" xlink:title="" />
</fig>
<p>Flipboard allows you to set up nine sections for different content.
You can select them from a predefined list, but the really interesting
part is to create your own sections from Twitter users or Twitter
lists:</p>
<fig>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120628140034im_/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/files/2010/11/flipboard4.jpg" xlink:title="" />
</fig>
<p>You can also create a section with all the Twitter accounts you
follow. Flipboard will display Tweets in a visually pleasing way.
Flipboard doesn't display all Tweets in your Twitter timeline, but
filters the most popular and interesting tweets.</p>
<fig>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120628140034im_/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/files/2010/11/flipboard1.jpg" xlink:title="" />
</fig>
<p>But Flipboard does something else. Rather than just displaying
tweets, it follows the links provided in your Twitter stream and
displays that information (photos, YouTube videos, blog posts, etc.). It
can't handle all the links and for example has problems with links to
FriendFeed (very common in my Twitter feed).</p>
<fig>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120628140034im_/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/files/2010/11/flipboard2.jpg" xlink:title="" />
</fig>
<p>To filter the information, you can also create sections from Twitter
lists (or individual users). I had created lists with Science Journals
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120628140034/https://twitter.com/mfenner/science-journals">@mfenner/science-journals</ext-link>)
and Nature Network
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120628140034/https://twitter.com/mfenner/nature-network">@mfenner/nature-network</ext-link>)
bloggers in the past.</p>
<fig>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120628140034im_/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/files/2010/11/flipboard5.jpg" xlink:title="" />
</fig>
<p>Twitter lists are great for following meetings (e.g.
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120628140034/https://twitter.com/BoraZ/scienceonline2010">@BoraZ/scienceonline2010</ext-link>),
but unfortunately Flipboard doesn't yet allow to create sections from
Twitter hashtags (e.g.
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120628140034/https://twitter.com/#search?q=%23scifoo">#scifoo</ext-link>).</p>
<fig>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120628140034im_/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/files/2010/11/flipboard6.jpg" xlink:title="" />
</fig>
<p>When you click on an individual entry, you will see a longer text,
and also Tweets referring to that time as well as a link to the fulltext
article.</p>
<fig>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120628140034im_/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/files/2010/11/flipboard7.jpg" xlink:title="" />
</fig>
<p>Flipboard does something similar with your Facebook News Feed. It is
important to understand that Flipboard is not an RSS reader, but rather
a visually pleasing aggregator from News in your Twitter and Facebook
networks. Flipboard doesn't present all the information in these
networks, but rather filters the most popular and “interesting”
stuff.</p>
<p>How is Flipboard relevant to reading scholarly papers? It can be used
out of the box for journals that tweet their table of contents or at
least the most interesting papers. And everybody can create a Twitter
account that retweets interesting papers in a particular subject area or
from a particular institution (ideally this should be integrated with a
bookmarking tool such as CiteULike). Scientific publishers could also
work with Flipboard to integrate their content (you see in the example
above that the scraping used by flipboard sometimes isn't perfect).
Almost all scientific papers have an abstract. The abstract would
display well in Flipboard, and could then link to the full text at the
journal site.</p>
<fig>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120628140034im_/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/files/2010/11/flipboard8.jpg" xlink:title="" />
</fig>
<p><italic><italic>To get started reading science blogs on Flipboard,
add a ResearchBlogging.org section by subscribing to the @ResearchBlogs
Twitter account.</italic></italic></p>
<p>Flipboard is of course also a great tool to follow science blogs. It
probably works best if a new Twitter account is set up just for that
purpose. This account could announce all new posts from a particular
blog, or about a particular topic. Twitter lists could then be used for
blogging networks such as <italic><italic>Nature
Network</italic></italic> or
<italic><italic>Scienceblogs.com</italic></italic>. Flipboard would also
work very well to cover the blogging and tweeting of scientific
conferences. With all these activities we will very soon need more than
the nine sections that Flipboard supports.</p>
<p><italic><italic>Update 08/01/10: Added ResearchBlogging.org
screenshot.</italic></italic></p>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
