<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>From Markdown to JATS XML in one Step</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2013-12-12">
<day>12</day>
<month>12</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>The Journal Article Tag Suite
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/">JATS</ext-link>)
is a NISO standard that defines a set of XML elements and attributes for
tagging journal articles. JATS is not only used for fulltext content at
PubMed Central (and JATS has evolved from the NLM Archiving and
Interchange Tag Suite originally developed for PubMed Central), but is
also increasinly used by publishers.</p>
<p>For many publishers the <italic>version of record</italic> of an
article is stored in XML, and other formats (currently HTML, PDF and
increasingly ePub) are generated from this XML. Unfortunately the
process of converting author-submitted manuscripts into JATS-compliant
XML is time-consuming and costly, and this is a problem in particular
for small publishers.</p>
<p>In a recent blog post
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://blog.martinfenner.org/2013/11/17/the-grammar-of-scholarly-communication/">The
Grammar of Scholarly Communication</ext-link>) I argued that publishers
should accept manuscripts in any reasonable file format, including
Microsoft Word, Open Office, LaTeX, Markdown, HTML and PDF. Readers of
this blog know that I am a big fan of
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://blog.martinfenner.org/tags.html#markdown-ref">markdown</ext-link>
for scholarly documents, but I am of course well aware that at the end
of the day these documents have to be converted into JATS.</p>
<p>As a small step towards that goal I have today released the first
public version of
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/mfenner/pandoc-jats">pandoc-jats</ext-link>,
a
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://johnmacfarlane.net/pandoc/README.html#custom-writers">custom
writer for Pandoc</ext-link> that converts markdown documents into JATS
XML with a single command, e.g.</p>
<preformat>pandoc -f example.md --filter pandoc-citeproc --bibliography=example.bib --csl=apa.csl -t JATS.lua -o example.xml</preformat>
<p>Please see the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/mfenner/pandoc-jats">pandoc-jats</ext-link>
Github repository for more detailed information, but using this custom
writer is as simple as downloading a single
<monospace>JATS.lua</monospace>file. The big challenge is of course to
make this custom writer work with as many documents as possible, and
that will be my job the next few weeks. Two example JATS documents are
below (both markdown versions of scholarly articles and posted on this
blog as HTML):</p>
<list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
    <p>Nine simple ways to make it easier to (re)use your data
    (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://blog.martinfenner.org/2013/06/25/nine-simple-ways-to-make-it-easier-to-reuse-your-data/">HTML</ext-link>,
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://blog.martinfenner.org/files/10.7287.peerj.preprints.7v2.xml">JATS</ext-link>)</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>What Can Article Level Metrics Do for You?
    (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://blog.martinfenner.org/2013/12/11/what-can-article-level-metrics-do-for-you/">HTML</ext-link>,
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://blog.martinfenner.org/files/10.1371.journal.pbio.1001687.xml">JATS</ext-link>)</p>
  </list-item>
</list>
<p>Both JATS files were validated against the JATS DTD and XSD and
showed no errors with the NLM XML StyleChecker - using the excellent
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/PeerJ/jats-conversion">jats-conversion</ext-link>
conversion and validation tools written by Alf Eaton. Markdown is
actually a nice file format to convert to XML - in contrast to HTML
authors can’t for example put closing tags at the wrong places. And a
Pandoc custom writer written in the Lua scripting language is an
interesting alternative to XSLT transformations, the more common way to
create JATS XML. The custom writer has not been tested with other Pandoc
input formats besides markdown, of particular interest are of course
HTML and LaTeX - Microsoft Word .docx is unfortunately only a Pandoc
output format.</p>
<p>This is the first public release and there is of course a lot of room
for improvement. Many elements and attributes are not yet supported -
although
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://orcid.org/blog/2013/03/22/orcid-how-more-specifying-orcid-ids-document-metadata">ORCID
author identifiers</ext-link> are of course included. Please help me
improve this tool using the Github
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/mfenner/pandoc-jats/issues">Issue
Tracker</ext-link>.</p>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
