<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>German Genetics Society Meeting 2009: Session
VI</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2009-09-25">
<day>25</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2009</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p><italic><italic>Another guest post by
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611032254/http://network.nature.com/people/alexander-knoll/profile">Alex
Knoll</ext-link> reporting from the German Genetics Society Meeting in
Cologne.</italic></italic></p>
<p>Saturday had two more sessions before the end of the meeting. Irina
Stancheva from the Wellcome Trust Centre for Cell Biology at the
University of Edinburgh started us into the day with a talk on
epigenetics in mouse development.</p>
<p>One form of epigenetic silencing is methylation of cytosine bases in
DNA. This is done by DNA methyltransferases like Dnmt1 for maintenance
methylation, or Dnmt3a and Dnmt3b for de novo methylation, at CpG
sequences enriched at promoters. During mouse embryonic development, DNA
methylation is essential, for a loss of either of the DNA
methyltransferases is embryonically lethal. Methylation and
demethylation during development is surprisingly dynamic, with loss and
new gain, and differences between the embryo and the trophectoderm.
Besides the Dnmts, there are further proteins involved in the regulation
of methylation levels. One interesting protein here is Lsh, a chromatin
remodelling ATPase belonging to the SNF2 family. It seems to have a low
ATPase activity in vitro, but it cooperates with several known factors
like the DNA methyltransferases and Histone deacetylases. With mouse
promoter microarrays, Irina Stancheva's group compared wildtype and Lsh
knockout cells, and found a reduction in promoter methylation when Lsh
is missing. The patterns of DNA methylation observed in Lsh null cells
suggest that this protein has a role in developmentally-programmed
methylation events in the early mouse embryo.</p>
<p>Dominique Soldati-Favre from the University of Geneva in Switzerland
gave an interesting talk about her work on apicomplexan parasites. This
phylum includes important human and animal pathogens such as Toxoplasma
gondii and Plasmodium falciparum causing toxoplasmosis and malaria
respectively. They belong to the clade of Chromalveolates, whose
ancestor acquired a plastid organelle by the secondary endosymbiosis of
an alga. While some members of this clade are free living organisms or
predators the Apicomplexa have evolved as obligate intracellular
parasites. These parasites have developed an elaborated strategy to
actively penetrate the host cells by a mechanism distinct from
phagocytosis and involving gliding motility. This active mode of entry
is favorable to the parasites, because this way they can evade the host
cell defense mechanisms. To identify and study the molecular components
of the vital process leading to host invasion, the Soldati's group has
developed genetic tools beginning from reliable DNA transfection up to
the establishment of an inducible expression system for the malaria
parasites based on transcription machinery elements similar to those
found in plants. Studies performed on T. gondii have established that
the mechanism of host cell entry is the result of a concerted action of
adhesins involved in the attachment of the parasite to the host cell,
the actin cytoskeleton and myosin motors that relocalize these adhesins
from anterior to posterior pole of the parasite, and proteases that
finally release these adhesins from the parasite surface.</p>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
