<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>German Genetics Society Meeting 2009: Session
IV</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2009-09-21">
<day>21</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2009</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p><italic><italic>Another guest post by
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611032512/http://network.nature.com/people/alexander-knoll/profile">Alex
Knoll</ext-link> reporting from the German Genetics Society Meeting in
Cologne.</italic></italic></p>
<p>The first session on Friday started with a talk by Frauke Melchior
from the ZMBP in Heidelberg on SUMO. Apart from being interesting to
work with, it also is good for some rather funny paper titles</p>
<fig>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611032512im_/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/wp-includes/images/smilies/icon_wink.gif" xlink:title="" />
</fig>
<p>At the start, she gave a short introduction on the proterties of
SUMO. It is similar to Ubiquitin (it stands for Small Ubiquitin-like
MOdifier) and gets covalently bound to lysines of hundreds of proteins
to change their protein or DNA interactions, localization, or activity.
A good example I also know from my work is the yeast DNA repair helicase
Srs2, which only interacts with the SUMOylated form of the replication
protein PCNA at the replication fork to suppress recombination. Many
protein-protein interactions that are dependent on SUMOylation can be
traced back to non-covalent recognition of a SUMO-interaction motif,
SIM.</p>
<p>Like with ubiquitin, there is an enzymatic cascade to bind a SUMO
unit to a target protein; however, there is only one E1 activating and
one E2 conjugating enzyme, and a handful of E3 SUMO ligases (compared to
hundreds for the ubiquitin pathway). Target recognition is not
understood very well, but there is a known consensus site wich is
recognized by the E2 enyzme for SUMOylation. The problem is: many
proteins are SUMOylated at non-consensus sites. Another mechanism turns
the usual direction of the pathway on its head: The target proteins
interacts with SUMO via a SIM, while it is still bound to the E2 enzyme.
This allows the E2 to transfer SUMO to the target protein.</p>
<p>Finally, Frauke Melchior told us about an interesting pair of
proteins that are involved in SUMOylation: RanGAP (RanGTPase activating
protein) interacts with RanBP2 at the nuclear pore complex after it gets
SUMOylated. RanBP2 itself is a SUMO E3 ligase, but not for RanGAP.
Without going into too much detail (unpublished data), the story
unraveled by Frauke Melchior and her coworkers showed a really complex
and intriguing picture of the role SUMO plays in regulating the activity
of this complex and the effect on nuclear transport.</p>
<p>In the second talk of the session, Chris Wylie from the Developmental
Biology division of the Cincinnati Children's hospital threw out the
simple model of germ cell migration in mouse embryos found in the
textbooks: During embryo development, the stem cells of the gametes, the
germ line stem cells, have to migrate to their niche in the gonads. They
start their travels in a structure called the allantois, go through the
hindgut and from there to the genital ridges, where the gonads will
form. Classically, it was thought that long range signals guide their
migration. But this is problematic, because the target organ supposed to
produce the guiding signal is not formed when the germ cells start their
migration, and during the migration the surroundings and distances will
change dramatically! That means there must be short range signals for
guidance.</p>
<p>A nice example to test this is the trip from the midline above the
gut to the genital ridges. Germ cells that stay at the midline will die
by apoptosis. The previously known stem cell survival factor Steel is
involved in preventing apoptosis in the cells. Its concentration
decreases from the ridges to the midline; adding Steel everywhere
experimentally saves the midline germ cells from apoptosis, while
blocking Steel everywhere kills the germ cells laterally. They were able
to show that Steel is not only involved in apoptosis, but also in the
migration and proliferation of the germ cells. Steel is not only
required at the late migration from the midline to the genital ridges;
from the start in the allantois, loss of Steel leads to loss of germ
cell number and migration.</p>
<p>Essentially, this means that not only is Steel one (of probably many)
short range signals, but it also travels with the germ cells along their
migration route, giving them a mobile stem cell niche!</p>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
