<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>German Genetics Society Meeting 2009: Evolution
Session</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2009-09-20">
<day>20</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2009</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p><italic><italic>Another guest post by
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611031744/http://network.nature.com/people/alexander-knoll/profile">Alex
Knoll</ext-link> reporting from the German Genetics Society Meeting in
Cologne.</italic></italic></p>
<p>Just after lunch the next decision: Neurogenetics or Evolution? Here
I went with the topic that is less far from my field, and attended the
evolution session. Welcome to the modern times, because next generation
sequencing and high throughput are the way to go!</p>
<p>These were the methods of choice for Julia Zeitlinger from the
Stowers Institute for Medical Research in Kansas City to compare
transcription factor binding sites between several Drosophila species.
This goes back to the question, which process contributes more to
evolution: mutations in the protein-coding parts of genes, or the
sequences needed for the transcriptional regulation of these genes, the
so-called cis-regulatory elements. There is evidence in some organisms
of a high turnover of transcription factor binding sites, and Julia
Zeitlinger wanted to compare these in the genus Drosophila. This was
done with chromatin immunoprecipitation approaches, where you analyze
the sequence of DNA fragments to which a target protein like a
transcription factor is bound. Earlier, this was followed by
hybidisation of microarrays (ChIP-chip), today these DNA fragments can
be directly sequenced with next generation methods (ChIP-seq). They
chose the dorso-ventral patterning in the Drosophila embryo as a model
system, with transcription factors like Twist that are well studied, and
that have conserved binding sites. Surprisingly, they found that Twist
binds to about 8 times more positions than were expected; sometimes
Twist bound at more than one position at target genes.</p>
<p>Across Drosophila species the binding sites of Twist were very
similar, especially near transcriptional start sites the positions are
mostly conserved. Although movements of binding sites exist, they are
rare. So it seems that there is evolutionary pressure to maintain the
sites.</p>
<p>Also about the evolutionary contributions of cis-regulatory regions
was the talk by Diethard Tautz from the Max Planck Institute for
Evolutionary Biology in Plants, Germany. But he addressed them with
population genetics of wild house mouse strains. With microarray and
qPCR experiments, his lab was able to find that the majority of genes
they looked at follow a neutral evolution. When this is not the case,
most of those genes show only tissue-specific changes in expression,
which points to cis-regulatory elements.</p>
<p>They also found a newly evolved gene in the mouse: In a region that
is completely free of annotated transcripts in other mammals, one
transcript can be found in the mouse. Poldi, as it is called, is
expressed in the mouse testis and encodes a non-protein coding RNA. They
were able to follow its birth in the genus Mus, where it appeared about
2.5 million years ago by changes in promoter regions. And although Poldi
appeared relatively recently, it plays a role in the mouse. A knockout
results in mice with reduced sperm motility and smaller testis, because
several chromatin-regulating proteins show different expression levels
in the absence of Poldi.</p>
<p>Now on to some computational biology by Andrew Hufton from the Max
Planck Institute for Molecular Genetics in Berlin. He analyzed a special
kind of cis-regulatory elements: the so-called conserved non-coding
elements (CNEs), that don't show much chance even over great
evolutionary distances. Why do they exist? There are two competing
hypotheses; either the CNEs repress genome rearrangements, or they
promote the retention of duplicate genes nearby. To test both
hypotheses, Andrew Hufton identified so-called phylogenetically
conserved non-coding elements. These are elements associated with gene
families and are not biased for one of the hypotheses. With experiments
in zebrafish, he found that most of the PCNEs are enhancers, sequences
involved in the regulation of gene expression.</p>
<p>Concerning the two competing hypotheses, he found a strong
association between PCNE and synteny conservation – the first
hypothesis: the PCNEs are enriched around genes with an ancient gene
order. For the retention of duplicated genes, he showed us an
alternative model.</p>
<p>In the last short talk of this session, Stephan Greiner told us about
a plant with a strange inheritance. At the Max Planck Institute for
Molecular Plant Physiology at Potsdam-Golm in Germany, he is working on
the Evening Primrose Oenothera. It combines some very interesting
genetic features like easy crossings between species, fertility of the
resulting hybrids, biparental transmission of chloroplasts (that are
usually inherited maternally) and something very strange called
permanent-translocation heterozygosity: The chromosomes of Oenothera
easily break at the centromeres, so that translocations of chromosome
arms happen. This leads to rings or chains of chromosomes during meiosis
that suppress homologous recombination and the intermixing of haploid
chromosomes. In the end, there are a handful of stable genomes that a
transmitted stably, and a hybrid plant with a combination of two of
these genomes will always have hybrid offspring.
Add in the possibility to exchange one of several different chloroplast
genomes in only two generations, and you will be able to generate
compatibility charts of nuclear and chloroplast genomes, where lethal
combinations and less severe phenotypes occur. Taken one step further,
it is possible to identify speciation genes in the chloroplast
genome.</p>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
