<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>German Research Foundation says that numbers aren’t
everything</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2010-03-01">
<day>1</day>
<month>3</month>
<year>2010</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Last Tuesday the <italic><italic>German Research
Foundation</italic></italic> (DFG)
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611102053/http://www.dfg.de/en/service/press/press_releases/2010/pressemitteilung_nr_07/index.html">announced</ext-link>
changes to the grant application process, going in effect in July.
Researchers are no longer allowed to list all their publications in
their grant proposals. The number of publications is limited to five per
researcher and to two per year of planned funding (e.g. 6 papers for a
3-year grant). Publications submitted but not yet accepted for
publication will no longer be allowed.</p>
<fig>
  <caption><p>Flickr image by CarbonNYC.</p></caption>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611102053im_/http://farm1.static.flickr.com/37/76463757_24a1858d2e_m_d.jpg" xlink:title="" />
</fig>
<p>Some of the reasoning behind this change was explained in the press
conference where the policy change was announced. The DFG wants to put
more emphasis on quality instead of quantity, in other words counteract
the trend to publish several small pieces of incremental research
findings (the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611102053/http://scienceblogs.com/drugmonkey/2009/01/repost_thoughts_on_the_least_p.php">least
publishable unit</ext-link> or <italic><italic>LPU</italic></italic>).
The DFG didn't say so, but this might also reduce the practice of
“honorary coauthorship” with some researchers being coauthors of 20 or
even 50 papers per year. And the DFG is not happy with the increasing
use of the Journal Impact Factor and other metrics as a token measure
for the quality of research output. And as a reaction to problems with
publication lists in
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611102053/http://www.spiegel.de/unispiegel/studium/0,1518,622474,00.html">G&amp;Atilde;¶ttingen</ext-link>
they want to stop the practice of including unpublished work in
reference lists for grant applications.</p>
<p>These changes will decrease the administrative workload of the
applicant, reviewer and the DFG. With much shorter reference lists in
grant applications, reviewers will have it much easier to take a closer
look at the research output of the applicant, instead of relying on an
unfortunate proxy such as the <italic><italic>Journal Impact
Factor</italic></italic>. Researchers seeking funding from the DFG will
now probably be more likely to write fewer but more substantial papers.
And research that doesn't have the potential for a substantial paper,
but is nevertheless worth publishing, can be quickly published in a
reasonable journal instead of going through several rounds of
submissions to a number of journals.</p>
<p>But how do you select your five best publications (assuming you have
written more than five)? Choices include:</p>
<list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
    <p>publication date, e.g. a list of the five most recent
    publications</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>Journal Impact Factor</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>citation counts, page views, downloads or other article-level
    metrics</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>personal preference</p>
  </list-item>
</list>
<p>Using my personal preference (and not too much thought), I picked
four papers and one correspondence:</p>
<list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
    <p><italic><italic>Shioda T, Fenner MH, Isselbacher
    KJ</italic></italic> Msg1, a novel melanocyte-specific gene, encodes
    a nuclear protein and is associated with pigmentation.
    <italic><italic>PNAS</italic></italic> 1996
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611102053/http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC37985/?tool=pubmed">PubMed
    Central</ext-link>
    The first paper from my postdoctoral research project. We identified
    and cloned a new gene thought to be involved in cancer metastasis,
    using a technology called differential display to compare the gene
    expression profile of two melanoma cell lines. This was before the
    mouse and human genomes were sequenced, and before microarrays
    became available. What took us two years of work 15 years ago can
    now probably be done in a few weeks.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p><italic><italic>Sado T, Fenner MH, Tan SS Tam P, Shioda T, Li
    E</italic></italic> X Inactivation in the Mouse Embryo Deficient for
    Dnmt1: Distinct Effect of Hypomethylation on Imprinted and Random X
    Inactivation. <italic><italic>Dev Biol</italic></italic> 2000
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611102053/http://dx.doi.org/10.1006/dbio.2000.9823">doi:10.1006/dbio.2000.9823</ext-link>
    I spent most of my time as a post-doc generating a knockout mouse
    for the gene identified in the previous paper. As the knockout mouse
    had no obvious phenotype, it took another post-doc (the first
    author) to finish the project.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p><italic><italic>Krege S et al.</italic></italic> European
    consensus conference on diagnosis and treatment of germ cell cancer:
    a report of the second meeting of the European Germ Cell Cancer
    Consensus group (EGCCCG): part I. <italic><italic>Eur
    Urol</italic></italic> 2008
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611102053/http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.eururo.2007.12.024">doi:10.1016/j.eururo.2007.12.024</ext-link>
    This paper summarizes the conclusions of a consensus conference on
    the diagnosis and treatment of testicular cancer, and is the best
    review on the subject. I am one of over 80 coauthors, something I
    haven't done before or since. The journal published this as two
    papers because of length. This would have been a perfect paper for
    an Open Access journal, I hope I can convince the coauthors to do so
    when we update this in 2011.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p><italic><italic>Fenner MH, Beutel G, Gruenwald
    V.</italic></italic> Targeted therapies for patients with germ cell
    tumors. <italic><italic>Expert Opin Investig Drugs</italic></italic>
    2008
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611102053/http://dx.doi.org/10.1517/13543784.17.4.511">doi:10.1517/13543784.17.4.511</ext-link>
    Testicular cancer is one of the few chemotherapy success stories, as
    most patients with advanced metastatic disease can be cured.
    Targeted therapies have become important treatment options in many
    cancers. This is the first review to look at the evidence for the
    use of targeted therapies in testicular cancer.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p><italic><italic>Fenner MH.</italic></italic> Duplication: stop
    favouring applicant with longest list.
    <italic><italic>Nature</italic></italic> 2008
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611102053/http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/452029a">doi:10.1038/452029a</ext-link>
    This is a <italic><italic>Nature</italic></italic> correspondence,
    included here only to show that comments made in a Nature Network
    forum can end up in <italic><italic>Nature</italic></italic>. And
    because it is relevant to this blog post, as I suggested to
    <italic><italic>ask applicants to select their best three, five or
    ten papers</italic></italic> instead of giving grants or jobs to
    those with the longest publication list.</p>
  </list-item>
</list>
<p>The Wellcome Trust last year
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611102053/http://www.wellcome.ac.uk/Funding/investigator-awards/Implementation/index.htm">announced</ext-link>
a different change to they grant application process. Starting later
this year, they will stop accepting proposals for project grants, and
rather evaluate the reaseach output of the scientist asking for funding
(<italic><italic>Investigator Awards</italic></italic>). They argue that
researchers that alrady have shown excellence in the past shoudn't be
burdened with the administrative overhead and restrictions of writing a
detailed project proposal every three years.</p>
<p>It will be interesting to see how institutions and other research
funders in Germany (e.g.
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611102053/http://www.helmholtz.de/en/">Helmholtz</ext-link>
or
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611102053/http://www.wgl.de/">Leibniz</ext-link>)
or elsewhere react to this DFG policy change. I would be happy if this
is a step towards more reasonable publication policies. And I hope that
the upcoming unique author identifier
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611102053/http://www.orcid.org/">ORCID</ext-link>
will not be used for even more complicated bibliometric calculations,
but rather as a tool for researchers to showcase their most interesting
work.</p>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
