<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>German Genetics Society Meeting 2009: Session Plant
Genetics II</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2009-09-24">
<day>24</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2009</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p><italic><italic>Another guest post by
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611033114/http://network.nature.com/people/alexander-knoll/profile">Alex
Knoll</ext-link> reporting from the German Genetics Society Meeting in
Cologne.</italic></italic></p>
<p>As promised, I attended the second Plant Genetics session of the
meeting, thus missing the Epigenetics session.</p>
<p>I learned an important lesson at the first talk by Juliette de Meaux
from the Max Planck Institute for Plant Breeding Research: Bring sweets
for the audience, and you have everyone on your side! Her research is on
the molecular basis of variation in the life cycle of the model plant
species <italic><italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></italic>. Natural
Arabidopsis strains grow in very different climates, and therefore have
to adapt their annual life cycle to the environmental conditions:
germinating their seeds early or late, flowering quickly after
germinating or growing vegetatively for months. The ability not to
germinate although there are good conditions is called seed dormancy.
This can be a very important trait, for example if the Arabidopsis
strain grows at a location where a short favorable period is followed by
a recurring period detrimental to the growth of the plant. Then the
plants which did not germinate even during the short favorable period
have an advantage. But such changes in seed germination time need the
whole life cycle to be fine-tuned: For the seeds of the following season
to be ready before winter, the growth rate has to faster, or the
flowering time shorter.</p>
<p>Because of the varying locations where Arabidopsis grows, there
should be variation in life history strategies to be found for selection
to act upon. For the model system of germination rate, Juliette de
Meaux' lab found a high variations in 180 natural genotypes they looked
at. Some strains germinated at the day of harvest, while others didn't
germinate at all even 250 days after harvest, and most somewhere in
between. If seeds were exposed to a cold treatment 250 days after
harvest (to simulate winter), the strains that didn't germinate after
the 250 days suddenly started to germinate, while others decreased in
their germination rate at longer times of cold exposure. Such and other
measurements allowed for the analysis of a very complex dataset to
derive the different strategies of life history in Arabidopsis. For
example, there is a correlation of growth rate and flowering time to be
found, but only in strains growing to the north (of Europe), not in the
southern strains. They also looked at the molecular basis of this life
history variation, and the consequences of it, which were interesting
parts of the talk in and of themselves.</p>
<p>The second talk was by R端diger Simon from the Institute of Genetics
at the University of D端sseldorf. Plants also possess stem cells, and
they are located in niches (in plants called meristems) at the tips of
the shoot and the root. For the shoot apical meristem (SAM), it is
already known that it is composed of the stem cells and an organizing
center underneath. The stem cell proliferation is regulated by a
negative feedback loop: Cells in the organizing center express Wuschel,
which promotes stem cell fate, but stem cells express Clavata3, that
represses Wuschel via the receptors Clavata1 and Clavata2. Apart from
that, there is a second negative feedback mechanism of regulating
Wuschel activity known. But according to computer simulations by R端diger
Simon and his colleagues, there are further factors needed to explain
the observed distributions of cells and gene expression. They looked for
such factors, and found the coryne mutant, which resembles known clavata
mutants; it must be in the same pathway.</p>
<p>R端diger Simon's lab also looked at the root tip stem cell niche, if
it is perhaps also regulated by a Clavata-like pathway. Interestingly,
they were able to find a Clavata3-related peptide in Cle40, that
regulates the Wuschel homolog WOX5. While this is similar to the
situation in the SAM, there are also differences: WOX5 is produced in
the QC, which resembles the organizing centre that expresses Wuschel ,
but Cle40 is not produced by the stem cells, but by already
differentiated cells derived from those stem cells.</p>
<p>Next, Bhupendra Chaudary from Gautam Buddha University in Greater
Noida, India, gave a short presentation on the fate of duplicated genes
in polyploid cotton. After a genome duplication event, the evolutionary
constraints on duplicated genes are relaxed, and one way change is
possible is by generating differences in expression, allowing for
subfunctionalization or neofunctionalization. They looked at expression
differences in homoeologous genes (pairs of genes duplicated by a
polyploidization event) in species of the cotton Gossypium, where
parental diploid genomes as well as allopolyploids can be found.
Interestingly, none of the parental genomes showed a dominant expression
in the hybrids globally, but some tissue-specific transcriptional
subfunctionalization.</p>
<p>The last talk of the session was given by Frank Kempken from the
University of Kiel on mitochondrial mRNA editing in plants. Mitochondria
possess their own rudimentary transcription and translation machinery,
and in between they change the mRNAs in a way the nucleus doesn't: they
edit the mRNA sequence, usually by exchanging a C for an U to create
novel stop codons, or to modify the amino acid sequence. How this is
done is largely unknown.</p>
<p>Frank Kempken's lab developed a system to work with isolated
mitochondria, because genetic engineering of them in plants is not
possible, and <italic><italic>in vitro</italic></italic> approaches have
serious drawbacks. In their '<italic><italic>in
organello</italic></italic>' system, they can electroporate the isolated
mitochondria in buffer, and observe the editing done to the expressed
mRNAs. This allowed them to observe correct recognition of editing sites
of Arabidopsis mRNAs in the mitochondria of maize, for example, or that
mRNAs from chloroplasts are not edited in mitochondria. This would at
least partially be expected, but somehow the plastid transcripts are not
recognized by the editing machinery in the mitochondria.</p>
<p>Using a novel binding assay (which requires 10 liters of Arabidopsis
cell culture per experiment, whew!) they were able to find proteins that
bind to mRNAs at editing sites. A knockout mutant of one of them leads
to growth retardation and smaller plants, exactly what one would expect
when mitochondria don't function properly anymore.</p>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
