<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>German Genetics Society Meeting 2009: Session V and
VII</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2009-09-29">
<day>29</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2009</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p><italic><italic>The final guest post by
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611031645/http://network.nature.com/people/alexander-knoll/profile">Alex
Knoll</ext-link> reporting from the German Genetics Society Meeting in
Cologne.</italic></italic></p>
<sec id="session-v">
  <title>Session V</title>
  <p>Friday ended with two talks in session V, the first by Tony Hyman
  from the Max Planck Institute for Cell Biology and Genetics in
  Dresden. He looked at the ways that cells structure and organize their
  cytoplasm by comparison with non-biological systems.</p>
  <p>Next up was a talk on the innate immune response against the
  influenza virus by University of Freiburg's Otto Haller. When viruses
  infect mammalian hosts, a battle between interferons and virulence
  factors starts to rage. The interferon-induced GTPase Mx1 is an
  important resistance factor against influenza A viruses in mice. Most
  lab mouse strains are natural knockouts for Mx1, so they needed to
  create congenic, wild-type Mx1-expressing mice to research its
  function.</p>
  <p>Interestingly, Mx1 expression protects mice against the usually
  lethal 1918 Spanish flu influenza A, even at high doses. Mx proteins
  are highly conserved in mammalian species and belong to the dynamin
  superfamily of large GTPases. Otto Haller presented new and
  unpublished data (obtained in collaboration with Oliver Daumke's group
  at the Berlin Max Delbrück Center for Molecular Medicine) on the role
  of the structure of the human MxA GTPase in repressing the virus.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="session-vii">
  <title>Session VII</title>
  <p>The final session of the meeting started with a talk by Andrew
  McMahon from the Harvard Stem Cell Institute in Cambridge, US, that I
  sadly missed. But one missed talk during the whole meeting is not that
  bad now, don't you think?
  Ueli Grossniklaus then talked about epigenetics in the struggle
  between the two parental genomes of an Arabidopsis embryo. At the
  University of Zürich in Switzerland, his group is looking at the
  timing of expression of paternal alleles and their phenotypic
  consequences, all controlled by the maternal genome.</p>
  <p>The last talk was given by Bruce Beutler from the Scripps Research
  Institute in La Jolla, US. He is looking into the ways in which the
  mammalian immune system is able to recognize microbes as foreign, and
  then mount an adequate response. A first answer was found when the
  receptor for LPS, a component of all Gram-negative microbes, was
  identified by positional cloning as Tlr4, a Toll-like receptor. You
  perhaps know Toll as a developmental gene in the Drosophila embryo,
  but in adult flies, it is required for the immune response to fungal
  and bacterial infections. So perhaps other Toll-like receptors also
  recognize other microbial ligands? Yes, and Bruce Beutler's group has
  been looking into the signaling pathways that lead from recognition by
  a Toll-like receptor to the induction of cellular responses. He and
  his group have used a forward genetic screen of randomly mutagenized
  mice. To date, they have generated over 100,000 mutant lines, and
  identified 32 mutations affecting Toll-like receptor signaling. This
  allowed them to deduce biochemical pathways that mediate much of the
  innate immune response. A similar feat was done with the genes
  involved in the resistance against mouse cytomegalovirus, with
  susceptibility mutations found in sensing and signaling pathways, but
  also in homeostasis and in development.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
