<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>German Genetics Society Meeting 2009: Session
I</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2009-09-18">
<day>18</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2009</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p><italic><italic>The second guest post from fellow science blogger
Alex Knoll reporting from the German Genetics Conference currently held
in Cologne.</italic></italic></p>
<p>The first session was all over the place in terms of topics.</p>
<p>Starting off the meeting, Linda Partridge from the Institute of
Healthy Ageing in London and the Max Planck Institute for Biology of
Ageing in Cologne told us about the Genetics of Ageing.</p>
<p>Looking back, there has been a linear increase of life expectancy in
humans for a rather long time now, with about 2.5 years added every
decade. That comes down to about 6 hours of increased life expectancy
per day!</p>
<p>While there is no single cause for ageing, it is nonetheless
controlled by genes and can evolve. And although life expectancy is
generally correlated with the body size of animals, there are several
exceptions like the little Brandt's bat that can live for 38 years, and
there are also some organisms that don't seem to age at all!</p>
<p>At first it was thought that the research of ageing in model
organisms would not be too relevant for the understanding of human
ageing, because there were many unique pathways in the different
animals. Interestingly, in many model organisms like the worm
Caenorhabditis elegans, the fly <italic><italic>Drosophila
melanogaster</italic></italic> and also the mouse, the insulin pathway
plays a big role: When components of this pathway are knocked out, the
lifespan of the animal increases. This means the healthy lifespan, the
organisms spend more time in the prime of their life instead of just
being old and sick for a longer time. Even in humans, population
genetics studies found homologues of some of these genes as candidates.
The implication of the insulin pathway fits nicely to earlier
observations of dietary restriction: If you put an organism on a diet
with less calories than it usually eats, it will live longer. This is
rather easy to do in the fly: just dilute the sugar solution it eats.
This way it was possible for the people in Linda Partridge's lab to
compare putative genes implicated in ageing with dietary
restriction.</p>
<p>They then asked the question: how deeply is the genetics of ageing
conserved between organisms? By using comparative microarray studies
with worm, fly and mouse, they were able to identify functional
categories of genes that are up- or downregulated in ageing.</p>
<p>Frank Grosveld from the Erasmus Medical Center in Rotterdam talked
about a systems biology approach to understand the transcriptional
regulation of globin genes in the mouse. During the development of red
blood cells, several large multiprotein complexes act as transcription
factors and bind to regulate the proliferation and differentiation. With
a systems biology procedure, Frank Grosveld's lab tried to find and
identify binding partners of known transcription factors during early
and late stages of erythrocyte differentiation. For example, GATA1 makes
several different complexes that very early on repress non red cell
genes to prime the lineage, later another complex with GATA1 represses
proliferation as a requirement for differentiation.</p>
<p>Interestingly, the globin locus that is expressed during erythrocyte
development, lies in between many olfactory genes. With the help of
several proteins binding at a number of regulatory regions, the
structure of the chromatin is altered so that these olfactory genes are
looped out and the components of the globin locus come to lie near each
other. This also enables long range interactions of elements that are
farther away, sometimes several megabases! The chromatin loops also
change depending on the tissue: the globin locus is expressed in the
fetal liver, and there it contacts other actively expressed genes. In
the fetal brain, on the other hand, the globin locus is inactive, and it
contacts mostly other inactive genes. The looping can even be shown
microscopically by measuring the volume of the the globin locus. In
expressing tissue the volume decreases, which indicates extra looping.
Another interesting aspect of Frank Grosveld's work touches blood
disorders like thalassemia and sickle cell anemia. These result from
defects in the beta-globin gene and are hard to treat. The idea here is
great: in fetal tissues, the gamma-globin genes are expressed, but they
are repressed perinatally. They have been able to identify a handful of
proteins that are responsible for this repression in mice, and
downregulation of these proteins leads to an upregulation of
gamma-globin expression and a downregulation of beta-globin. These
repressors are now novel targets to develop a new type of treatment for
these anemias.</p>
<p>Finally, Marjori Matzke from the Gregor Mendel Institute in Vienna
spoke about epigenetics in plants. Specifically, she told us about her
research into RNA-dependent DNA methylation (RdDM) as a way to regulate
transcription in plants, where not only repeats and other such elements
are processed, but also single genes. This is done via small RNAs and
the action of the two RNA polymerases PolIV and PolV. These are related
to the standard RNA polymerase PolII, but possess different C-terminal
domains that are responsible for their functional diversification. After
24-nt long siRNAs are produced, they lead to de novo methylation and
thus inactivation of target sites with the help of PolV and other
factors. From this inactivated locus then further siRNAs are produced
with PolIV to keep the methylated state. Using a silenced GFP expression
system, the Matzke lab searched for mutants with defects in RdDM, and
found several until now.
RNA-dependent DNA methylation as a further method of transcriptional
regulation in the cell, for example for stress responses in plants that
can't run away from the stress arrived at an interesting time in plant
evolution. The group of flowering plants appeared rather abruptly in the
fossil record, prompting Charles Darwin famously to speak about an
'abominable mystery'. PolV and other factors involved in RdDM are only
to be found in flowering plants, which could let one conclude that the
newly evolved epigenetic plasticity played at least a part in the
evolution of this successful group.</p>
<p>The first day of the meeting ended with a public lecture by Peter
Propping from Bonn in Germany. His talk in German was about the history
and future of human genetics (“Der Mensch und seine Gene in der Welt von
morgen”). He started by telling us about the problematic standing of
human genetics in the middle of the last century, mostly because of
concerns stemming from the earlier decades with eugenics, sterilizing
and killing people because of genetic concerns.</p>
<p>The big successes then came with the research into monogenetic
diseases, which firstly were reached by methods such as positional
cloning. Now is the time to study multifactorial diseases, which are
much harder to tackle; here we have many genes which only contribute a
small amount to the phenotype, and environmental effects contributing as
well. A nice example of a new kind of genetic defect are copy number
variants, where a sequence is repeated a different number of times
between individuals. But this is not well understood for now, because
the same CNVs can be found in diseased patients, but also in healthy
people.</p>
<p>In the future a lot of work will be done with next generation
sequencing, which will hopefully put a lot of data into the hands of the
researchers. On the other hand, this means that a lot of money will be
spent – a criticism that can be heard already now.</p>
<p>Another part of his talk was about the possibilities of and problems
of prenatal screening. It was rather surprising for me to hear that in
Germany in about 10% of pregnancies a screening is done, mostly to look
for chromosomal mutations like trisomy 21 (that is responsible for Down
syndrome)! Pre-implantation diagnostics in the course of in
vitro-fertilization, however, is not allowed in Germany, which lead to a
PID tourism into other European countries.</p>
<p>Finally Peter Propping also talked about the new law for genetics
diagnostics in Germany, which has some problems. For example, genetic
analysis is defined by methods in the law, which leads to the curious
case that even simple biochemical work such as blood group determination
falls under the regulations of the new law!</p>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
