<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>German Genetics Society Meeting 2009: Session
III</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2009-09-24">
<day>24</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2009</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p><italic><italic>Another guest post by
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611033341/http://network.nature.com/people/alexander-knoll/profile">Alex
Knoll</ext-link> reporting from the German Genetics Society Meeting in
Cologne.</italic></italic></p>
<p>The last session on Thursday was split into two talks by Philippe
Sansonetti from the Institute Pasteur in Paris and Julian Parkhill from
the Sanger Institute in Hinxton, Great Britain. Both talked about
pathogenic microbes, but from a different perspective.</p>
<p>After Philippe Sansonetti told us about
<italic><italic>Shigella</italic></italic> and the innate immune system
during invasion of the gut epithelium, Julian Parkhill gave us some
insights into two (genomically) very different organisms.
<italic><italic>Salmonella typhi</italic></italic>, responsible for
typhoid fever, has evolved relatively recently by changing its niche; it
went from being a gut pathogen to a systemic pathogen. This can be seen
in its genome, because its evolution is not characterized by the gain of
genes, but actually by the loss of many genes through single mutations.
For bacteria, <italic><italic>Salmonella typhi</italic></italic> is
rather strange: There is almost no recombination between strains, so
there are very few SNPs that can by typed. By looking at 200 genes in
about 200 strains, they found 88 SNPs in total! Evolutionarily, their
data point to mostly long-term neutral mutations, with only very few
genes to be found that show evidence of positive selection. But the SNP
data they acquired could be put to good use nonetheless: They were able
to do an epidemiological analysis in the field by collecting S. typhi
strains around Kathmandu.</p>
<p>The opposite of <italic><italic>S. typhi</italic></italic> in terms
of recombination and SNPs is <italic><italic>Staphylococcus
aureus</italic></italic>, which comprises a hugely diverse group of
freely recombining strains. With next generation sequencing, they were
able to track the appearance and travels of a specific strain around the
world. They even got enough SNPs in their dataset to be able to
distinguish strains from different wards in a single hospital!
The talk was also a lesson in technological progress: While the
sequencing of the <italic><italic>Salmonella typhi</italic></italic>
genome a few years ago took 1.5 years, the next generation sequencing of
<italic><italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic></italic> allowed the
analysis of 66 genomes per run and week. Finally, we had a glimpse into
the future: They are getting into single cell genome sequencing by doing
laser capture microsdissection, and are already able to reach about 98%
coverage!</p>
<p>Following this last talk of the day, the German Genetics Society
awarded the honorary membership to Rolf Knippers. At least German
speaking biologists should know him by name because of his well-known
(and great, in my opinion) textbook <italic><italic>Molekulare
Genetik</italic></italic> (Molecular Genetics), which first appeared in
the early 1970s. But that was not the only reason for the award.
Actually, Rolf Knippers has been a very good researcher and teacher,
too! I didn't know him apart from his textbook before, but the laudatio
and his acceptance speech (which he started by humbly asking if he
deserved the award) made me wish I had met him earlier, perhaps as a
student or even as a member of his lab.</p>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
