<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>German Genetics Conference 2009: Session
II</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2009-09-18">
<day>18</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2009</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p><italic><italic>Another guest post from Alex Knoll reporting from the
German Genetics Conference in Cologne.</italic></italic></p>
<p>Dusko Ehrlich fom Jouy en Josas in France started off the second
session of the meeting. He is working with the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003105714/http://www.metahit.eu/">MetaHIT
project</ext-link>, which tries to do a metagenomic analysis of the
human intestinal tract. This is interesting because each individual
human carries about ten times more microbial cell in the gut than there
are human cells in the whole body! These microbes provide the interface
between the food we take in and the epithelial cells of the gut. There,
they play many roles not only in metabolising materials and molecules we
are not capable of, but they also produce vitamins for us and help the
immune system. It is therefore very important to understand this further
organ of our body, as Dusko Ehrlich called it.</p>
<p>The MetaHIT project takes many approaches to understand the
interaction between the human intestinal microbes and human phenotypes
like obesity ore bowel diseases. For example, they want to sequence a
reference gene set and then look for associations of these genes with
diseases. The reference gene set is produced by Solexa paired-end
sequencing of samples from 124 individuals, which produced almost 0.6
terabases of sequence in total already! From these sequences contigs are
produced and ORFs are predicted, which are almost completey of bacterial
origin. This then allows for the comparison of bacterial genes and
genomes between the sampled individuals, and also the establishment of a
'minimal metagenome' of the gut ecosystem for absolutely required
functions.</p>
<p>The second talk was really interesting to me: In
<italic><italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic></italic> the male flies
perform a courtship dance to win over the female. Barry Dickson from the
Institute of Molecular Pathology in Vienna is looking for the genetic
neurobiologic basis of this behaviour.</p>
<p>The fruitless gene, which produces a transcription factor, is
absolutely required for the courtship of male flies; females don't
produce a protein product due to alternative splicing. But when females
carry the male form of the fru gene, they show the typical male
courtship behaviour. This means fruitless is some kind of molecular
switch for male behaviour in Drosophila by programming the nervous
system. So they looked at neurons that express the fru gene with the
help of reporter genes and found sensory, central and motor neurons that
need to be active for male courtship. Dickson's lab was able to assemble
a digital atlas of fru neurons, with stunning pictures, and were able to
derive a 'wiring diagram'. Just six easy steps: Starting from
fru-expressing olfactory receptor neurons that specifically sense
pheromones it only takes this few neural connections to motor output in
wing muscles that are required for the courtship song!</p>
<p>Now the group is trying to go the high throughput route by teaching a
computer to analyze the courtship behaviour by itself, and the first
results look very promising.</p>
<p>The third talk by Andrei Lupas of the Max Planck Institute for
Developmental Biology in Tübingen, Germany, was about the genetic basis
of protein fold evolution. Autonomously folding units in proteins are
called domains, and usually the fold of a domain is conserved with a
high evolutionary permanence.</p>
<p>Surprisingly for me, there are only about 10Â³ basic folds, that all
were established around the time of the last universal common ancestor
of all living organisms.
But there is the potential for a fold change in domains by specific
alterations that go back to point mutations, deletions, insertions or
recombination at the level of DNA. To understand how these changes come
about, Lupas' group is looking at experimental changes and their
outcome. For example, beta-propellers are structures that arise by
repeating a single 'blade' a certain number of times. Actually, all
present beta-propellers probably all go back to one ancestral blade that
was amplified several times. How large can a propeller domain become?
The biggest propeller in databases has 10 blades, a 14-blade propeller
in yeast forms a split between blades 7 and 8. But Lupas was able to
produce a 12-bladed propeller.</p>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
