<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>German Genetics Society Meeting 2009: Session Cellular
Genetic Mechanisms</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2009-09-22">
<day>22</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2009</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p><italic><italic>Another guest post by
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611032931/http://network.nature.com/people/alexander-knoll/profile">Alex
Knoll</ext-link> reporting from the German Genetics Society Meeting in
Cologne.</italic></italic></p>
<p>Both sessions had some interesting talks, so it was really hard to
decide between attending Cellular Genetic Mechanisms or Human Genetics,
but in the end I went to the former.</p>
<p>The first talk by Marina Rodnina from the Max Planck Institute for
Biophysical Chemistry is not easy to put into words. Not because of a
bad presentation, I should add! Her work on biochemical properties of
translation involves kinetic data of a row of proteins involved in the
phases of translation: initiation, elongation, termination and ribosome
recycling.</p>
<p>I'll give you a short summary of the initiation of translation in
bacteria: First the 30S subunit of the ribosome binds a mRNA and the
initiator tRNA with the help of effector proteins to form the 30S
initiation complex. The 50S subunit then binds to that to form the 70S
initiation complex. By fluorescently labelling all of the components of
the complex, they were able to measure the rate constants (how do they
bind and dissociate from the ribosome) and then calculate the binding
rates to find the order of binding. This is hardest to establish for the
mRNA, because of control elements like the composition of the
Shine-Dalgarno sequence or secondary structures. But ignoring all of
these elements, the most significant factor at this step is the mRNA
concentration. Looking at secondary structure, the unfolding of the mRNA
is the slow step after a quick binding. This represents a kind of
stability switch to enable correct start codon recognition. Not only
during initiation, but also for elongation Marina Rodnina's lab could
show that a lot of checks are kinetic in nature. Essentially, this can
be summarized by the concept of induced fit: correct substrates are
selectively stabilized by accelerating their forward steps.</p>
<p>Following was a short presentation by Matthias Schäfer on unpublished
research. At the ETH Zürich in Switzerland, he is looking into the
molecular role of protection against reactive oxygen species (ROS) in
the epidermis.</p>
<p>Aria Baniahmad fom the Jena University Hospital, Germany, talked
about an interesting connection of telomerase activity and androgens in
prostate cancer. There, telomerase is usually active, as in many cancers
to allow the cancer cell to divide indefinitely. Androgens repress
telomerase activity, which is probably one reason why prostate cancer
occurs later in life, when androgen levels decrease in men.</p>
<p>The decrease of telomerase activity is based on binding of the
androgen receptor to the promoter of the catalytic telomerase subunit
hTERT. In many prostate cancers, an androgen receptor with a specific
point mutation can be found. This mutated AR's binding to the telomerase
promoter is weaker, which results in increased telomerase
expression.</p>
<p>The session was closed with a talk by Thorsten Hoppe from the
Institute for Genetics of Köln University, who presented intruiging, but
unpublished data about his research on ubiquitin and ageing in
<italic><italic>C. elegans</italic></italic>.</p>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
