<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Goodbye PLOS Blogs, Welcome Github Pages</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2013-06-15">
<day>15</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>This is the last
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner">Gobbledygook</ext-link>
post on PLOS Blogs, and at the same time the first post at the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://blog.martinfenner.org/">new
Github blog location</ext-link>. I have been blogging at PLOS Blogs
since the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://blogs.plos.org/blogosphere/">PLOS
Blogs Network</ext-link> was launched in September 2010, so this step
wasn’t easy. But I have two good reasons.</p>
<p>In May 2012 I started to work as technical lead for the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://article-level-metrics.plos.org/">PLOS
Article-Level Metrics</ext-link> project. Although this is contract
work, and I also do other things - including spending 5% of my time as
clinical researcher at Hannover Medical School - this created the
awkward situation that I was never quite sure whether I was blogging as
Martin Fenner or as someone working for PLOS. This was all in my head,
as I never had any restrictions in my blogging from PLOS. With the
recent launch of the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://blogs.plos.org/tech/">PLOS
Tech Blog</ext-link> there is now a good venue for the kind of topics I
like to write about, and I have started to work on two posts for this
new blog.</p>
<p>There will always be topics for which the PLOS Tech Blog is not a
good fit, and for these posts I have launched the new personal blog at
Github. But the main reason for this new blog is a technical one: I’m
moving away from blogging on Wordpress to writing my posts in
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/">markdown</ext-link>
(a lightweight markup language), that are then transformed into static
HTML pages using
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jekyllrb.com/">Jekyll</ext-link>
and
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://johnmacfarlane.net/pandoc/">Pandoc</ext-link>.
Last weekend I co-organized the workshop
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/scholmd/markdown_science/wiki"><bold><bold>Scholarly
Markdown</bold></bold></ext-link> together with
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://twitter.com/houshuang">Stian
Håklev</ext-link>. A full workshop report will follow in another post,
but the discussions before, at and after the workshop convinced me that
<bold><bold>Scholarly Markdown</bold></bold> has a bright future and
that it is time to move more of my writing to markdown. At the end of
the workshop each participant suggested a
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/scholmd/markdown_science/wiki/Todo-list-from-workshop">todo
item</ext-link> that he/she would be working on, and my todo item was
“Think about document type where MD shines”. Markdown might be good for
writing scientific papers, but I think it really shines in shorter
scientific documents that can easily be shared with others. And blog
posts are a perfect fit.</p>
<p>The new site is work in progress. Over time I will copy over all old
blog posts from PLOS Blogs, and will work on the layout as well as
additional features. Special thanks to
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://carlboettiger.info/">Carl
Boettiger</ext-link> for helping me to get started with Jekyll and
Github pages.</p>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
