<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Google Scholar Citations, Researcher Profiles, and why we
need an Open Bibliography</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2011-07-27">
<day>27</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2011</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Last week Google Scholar
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120610140256/http://googlescholar.blogspot.com/2011/07/google-scholar-citations.html">announced
a new feature</ext-link> on the Google Scholar Blog: <bold><bold>Google
Scholar Citations</bold></bold>. The stated purpose of this tool is to
allow researchers to calculate their citation metrics, e.g. their
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120610140256/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2007/08/17/do_you_know_your_hirsch_number/">Hirsch
index</ext-link> (H-index).</p>
<fig>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120610140256im_/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/files/2011/07/SafariSnapshot001-500x306.jpg" xlink:title="SafariSnapshot001" />
</fig>
<p>This is an interesting new service, that not only helps with
calculating citation metrics, but also shows you who is citing your
papers – a great discovery tool. Signup to Google Scholar Citations is
currently limited, but I was able to create a profile
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120610140256/http://scholar.google.com/citations?user=N05QljgAAAAJ&amp;hl=en">here</ext-link>.</p>
<p>The problem? We have this service already.
<bold><bold>Scopus</bold></bold>, <bold><bold>Researcher
ID</bold></bold> and others have provided this information for some
time, and Google Scholar Citations looks very much like a response to
the recently launched Microsoft Academic Search:</p>
<fig>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120610140256im_/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/files/2011/07/SafariSnapshot002-500x349.jpg" xlink:title="SafariSnapshot002" />
</fig>
<p>Will we soon see a similar offering from
<bold><bold>Mendeley</bold></bold> or
<bold><bold>ResearchGate</bold></bold>? There is of course nothing wrong
with competition, and there is no reason why we can’t have more than one
place that provides researcher profiles. But as I have
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120610140256/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/scientific-attribution-principles/">argued
before</ext-link>,</p>
<p><bold><bold>Systems that measure and evaluate scientific
contributions can and should be separate from the databases that hold
the scholarly record.</bold></bold></p>
<p>It is not only a waste of resources (both Google Scholar’s and the
individual researchers’ who maintain their profiles) to many many
different bibliographic databases, but it also makes it impossible to
compare citation metrics. In the examples above Alonzo Church has a
H-index of 19 at Google Scholar, but only 11 at Microsoft Academic
Search (and probably again a different one somewhere else). This means
that we can only use an H-index when we mention where (and when) it was
calculated.</p>
<p>The better solution is a common
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120610140256/http://3lib.org/">open
bibliography</ext-link>, and the difference between the various service
would be how they calculate the citation metric or present the
bibliographic data – you can see the different approaches taken by
Google Scholar and Microsoft Academic Search in the screenshots above.
This is a difficult task, but not impossible to do. The first step would
be to realize that having a common open bibliography would create
tremendous value for everybody as we can start building tools on top
this bibliography without requiring to collect all the bibliographic
data ourselves. We see something like this happening in smaller domains,
and the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120610140256/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2011/04/29/web-tools-for-searching-the-biomedical-literature-part-i/">tools
using the PubMed database</ext-link> are a good example.</p>
<p>From a researcher perspective it makes little sense to have many
different places where you can maintain your publications. It makes much
more sense to do this once and then see the information reused in
different services. This is the approach the Open Researcher &amp;
Contributor ID initiative is
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120610140256/http://www.orcid.org/principles">taking</ext-link>:</p>
<p><bold><bold>All profile data contributed to ORCID by researchers or
claimed by them will be available in standard formats for free download
(subject to the researchers’ own privacy settings) that is updated once
a year and released under the CC0 waiver.</bold></bold></p>
<p><italic><italic>Disclaimer: I sit on the Board of Directors of the
Open Researcher &amp; Contributor ID (ORCID) initiative which aims to
help solve this and related problems.</italic></italic></p>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
