<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Having fun with citations at
ScienceOnline2011</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2011-01-11">
<day>11</day>
<month>1</month>
<year>2011</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611072611/http://scienceonline2011.com/">ScienceOnline2011</ext-link>,
the fifth annual international meeting on Science and the Web, is only
two days away. I am very excited for many reasons, most importantly
because it gives me the chance to meet many online friends in person –
again or for the first time.</p>
<p>On Saturday I will help moderate two (related) sessions:
<bold><bold>How is the Web changing the way we identify scientific
impact</bold></bold> and <bold><bold>Having fun with
citations</bold></bold>. The first session will be about alternative
ways to measure scientific impact, and about the alternative types of
publications we can measure. The second session is all about citations.
We use them all the time in scholarly communications, but we don’t
really think about them. To give a couple of examples: why are there so
many different citation styles, why is it so difficult to find open
bibliographic data, how can we describe why we decided to cite
something, or how can we cite things that are not publications?</p>
<p>Since I suggested this session a few months ago, my thinking about
citations has changed. Citations should be easy to use, wherever we need
them. Even though he have a number of clever
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611072611/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/reference-manager-overview/">reference
management tools</ext-link>, the process is still too complicated. What
would really help is an easier format for references, and the best
format I can think of is the ubiquitous internet link. I have
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611072611/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2010/12/11/citations-are-links-so-where-is-the-problem/">written
about links</ext-link> before, and I have spent the last few weeks to
work on WordPress plugins to better handle links for scholarly works.
Today I released the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611072611/http://wordpress.org/extend/plugins/link-to-link/">Link
to Link</ext-link> plugin:</p>
<fig>
  <caption><p><italic><italic>Some science-related references in my
  WordPress Links Manager.</italic></italic></p></caption>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611072611im_/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/files/2011/01/screenshot-1-500x432.png" xlink:title="screenshot-1" />
</fig>
<p>The Link to Link window in the WordPress editor should look familiar
to users of traditional reference managers. You search for references
and then insert them into the text. The references are stored in the
WordPress Links Manager, and you can get them in there using the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611072611/http://wordpress.org/extend/plugins/bibtex-importer/">BibTeX
Importer</ext-link> plugin I wrote two weeks ago. Both plugins are
available from the WordPress plugins directory and can be installed
directly from WordPress.</p>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
