<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>How do you read papers? 2010 will be
different</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2010-01-10">
<day>10</day>
<month>1</month>
<year>2010</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>In November 2008 I wrote a blog post called
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611111551/http://network.nature.com/people/mfenner/blog/2008/11/02/how-do-you-read-papers">How
do you read papers?</ext-link> The blog post was actually about
different strategies to <italic><italic>find</italic></italic>
interesting papers, e.g. browsing journal tables of content (TOC),
different search strategies, filtering by papers others read, or
filtering by experts (e.g. <italic><italic>Faculty of
1000</italic></italic>). A paper by
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611111551/http://network.nature.com/people/duncan/profile">Duncan
Hull</ext-link> et al. published around that time in
<italic><italic>PLoS Computational Biology</italic></italic>
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611111551/http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000204">Defrosting
the Digital Library: Bibliographic Tools for the Next Generation
Web</ext-link>) also talked about finding strategies and the best tools
for this.</p>
<p>In this blog post I want to talk about the actual reading of
scientific papers that you found with one of the strategies mentioned
above. There are some interesting recent developments, and I think we
will see some significant changes in how we read papers in 2010.</p>
<sec id="printed-journal">
  <title>Printed journal</title>
  <p>Holding the printed journal in your hands is probably still the
  most satisfying reading experience because of professional typesetting
  and color reproduction. But unless you have a personal journal
  subscription, it is not convenient as you would have to go to the
  library to read the paper. Plus, many journals no longer produce a
  printed version, or the library has only an electronic
  subscription.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="photocopy">
  <title>Photocopy</title>
  <p>This used to be the most common way to read papers 20 years ago.
  But the quality of photocopies is usually worse than a printout of an
  electronic version, and photocopies are far more inconvenient to
  obtain. Reading photocopied papers will only be necessary for the
  small number of journals that produce no electronic version, or for
  older
  papers.<sup><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611111551/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2010/01/10/how_do_you_read_papers_2010_will_be_different/#fn1">1</ext-link></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="pdf-printout">
  <title>PDF printout</title>
  <p>This is the way most people read scientific papers today, unless
  they just want to look up small parts of it. Quality color printers
  have become affordable, and the reading experience is similar to the
  printed journal with the added convenience of electronic distribution.
  Most people use PDF printouts for reading, and later discard the paper
  copy, sometimes even the same day. This is not only more expensive
  than reading on an electronic device, but also not very friendly to
  the
  environment.<sup><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611111551/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2010/01/10/how_do_you_read_papers_2010_will_be_different/#fn2">2</ext-link></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="reading-pdfs-on-a-computer">
  <title>Reading PDFs on a computer</title>
  <p>This approach appears to be very common for reading just parts of a
  paper, e.g. to look up experimental details, a figure or reference.
  Most people now store papers as PDF (hopefully with an intelligent
  program such as
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611111551/http://mekentosj.com/papers/">Papers</ext-link>)
  and not the PDF printouts. Looking at the PDF on the screen is
  therefore often the first step, and then the decision is made whether
  or not to print out the paper to read it in more detail. Reading PDFs
  on screen is possible, but not really convenient for longer texts.
  Screen sizes are often too small for the PDF format (A4 or US letter).
  Many people don't like the eye strain from looking at a screen for
  longer periods of time, although this is probably more relevant for
  reading books rather than reading a scientific paper.</p>
  <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611111551/http://getutopia.com/documents/overview">Utopia</ext-link>
  is a PDF viewer launched in December by the University of Manchester
  that enhances PDF files of the <italic><italic>Semantic Biochemical
  Journal</italic></italic> with interactive content and live linking to
  web resources.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611111551/http://duncan.hull.name/2009/12/11/utopia/">Read
  more about Utopia</ext-link> at <italic><italic>Duncan
  Hull</italic></italic>'s blog.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="reading-on-a-mobile-device">
  <title>Reading on a mobile device</title>
  <p>Many mobile devices such as the iPhone can open PDFs and
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611111551/http://mekentosj.com/papers/iphone/">Papers
  for iPhone</ext-link> makes this process convenient. But PDFs in an A4
  or US letter format are almost impossible to read on a small
  screen.</p>
  <p>The
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611111551/http://river-valley.tv/epub-is-the-only-format-we-need/">ePub
  format</ext-link> is more suitable for smaller screens found on mobile
  devices. ePub is usually used for e-Books, but the Open Access
  publisher Hindawi
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611111551/http://www.hindawi.com/epub.html">since
  2008 provides papers also in that format</ext-link>. Although ePub is
  more suitable than PDF for mobile devices, it doesn't solve the
  problem that figures and tables are simply difficult to show on a
  small screen. Mobile devices are probably great for reading journal
  table of contents or the abstract of a paper (and an RSS reader such
  as
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611111551/http://www.newsgator.com/individuals/netnewswireiphone/default.aspx">NetNewsWire
  for iPhone</ext-link> is perfect for this), but not fulltext
  papers.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="reading-on-an-e-reader">
  <title>Reading on an e-Reader</title>
  <p>The screen of an e-Reader uses
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611111551/http://river-valley.tv/electronic-paper-technology/">electronic
  ink</ext-link> which not only means a much longer battery life, but
  also a very pleasing reading experience, including reading in direct
  sunlight. Electronic ink is black &amp; white, which is not a problem
  for fiction books, but limits the use for scholarly papers (and
  scientific textbooks). Ideally an e-Reader should have a 10″ screen,
  similar in size to A4 or US letter paper.</p>
  <p>The
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611111551/http://www.techcrunch.com/2009/05/07/how-big-can-the-kindle-get/">Kindle
  DX</ext-link> from Amazon was announced in May 2009 and is currently
  the most popular e-Reader. The Kindle uses its own file format, but a
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611111551/http://www.amazon.com/gp/help/customer/display.html?ie=UTF8&amp;nodeId=200324680">recent
  software update</ext-link> now allows the Kindle to open PDF files.
  Some journals (e.g. the <italic><italic>New England Journal of
  Medicine</italic></italic>) offer Kindle subscriptions, but that
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611111551/http://patrickmd.net/blog/2009/05/22/cancelled-kindle-subscription-to-nejm/">doesn't
  include early release articles</ext-link> and no subscriber access to
  the journal website. A
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611111551/http://www.nytimes.com/2010/01/09/technology/personaltech/09reader.html">number
  of similar devices</ext-link> were demonstrated this week at the
  Consumer Electronics Show in Las Vegas. The Kindle is primarily an
  e-Book reader, and <italic><italic>David Crotty</italic></italic> over
  on the Scholarly Kitchen blog
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611111551/http://scholarlykitchen.sspnet.org/2010/01/06/doing-the-kindle-math-does-amazons-opacity-conceal-a-shameful-truth">is
  skeptical</ext-link> about dedicated e-readers, because he thinks that
  market is just too small.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="apple-islate">
  <title>Apple iSlate</title>
  <p>Unless you have been on a remote island for the last three months,
  you will know that Apple will announce a
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611111551/http://daringfireball.net/2009/12/the_tablet">tablet
  computer</ext-link> later this month. There is wide speculation about
  the technical details, but it looks like this will be a very
  interesting device for reading scholarly papers. In contrast to
  e-Readers it will not use electronic ink. This means a shorter battery
  life, but allows color documents and many other more traditional
  computer uses. Based on the iPod and iPhone experience, many people
  think that the iSlate will change the way we use tablet computers. One
  of them is <italic><italic>Kent Anderson</italic></italic>
  (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611111551/http://scholarlykitchen.sspnet.org/2009/10/02/game-over-man-has-the-disruption-of-publishing-already-occurred/">Game
  Over, Man – Has the Disruption of Publishing Already
  Occurred?</ext-link>).</p>
  <p>Sports Illustrated did a very nice
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611111551/http://sportsillustrated.cnn.com/2009/magazine/12/02/tablet/index.html">demo
  of a fictional tablet computer</ext-link> in December, and it is
  obvious that many of these concepts can also be applied to scholarly
  publishing.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="reading-web-pages">
  <title>Reading Web Pages</title>
  <p>Most examples mentioned above try to reproduce the experience of
  reading something printed on paper on an electronic device. An
  alternative approach would move beyond the traditional format of a
  paper and rather takes advantage of the electronic medium. And it
  looks like the web technologies HTML5 and Flash are best suited for
  this. Cell Press was
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611111551/http://network.nature.com/people/mfenner/blog/2009/07/26/how-does-the-article-of-the-future-look-like">experimenting
  with this approach</ext-link> in 2009, and officially launched their
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611111551/http://beta.cell.com/index.php/2010/01/cell-launches-article-of-the-future-format/">Article
  of the Future</ext-link> with the first 2010 issue of Cell (all papers
  will be available without subscription for 60 days, you can provide
  feedback
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611111551/http://beta.cell.com/index.php/feedback-cell-press-new-article-format/">here</ext-link>).
  The basic idea of the Article of the Future is to break away from the
  concept of reading a paper from beginning to end, and to make
  navigation between the different parts of a paper much easier.</p>
  <p>Whereas the <italic><italic>Article of the Future</italic></italic>
  tries to make navigation with a paper easier, the
  <italic><italic>PLoS</italic></italic>
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611111551/http://network.nature.com/people/mfenner/blog/2009/08/15/plos-one-interview-with-peter-binfield">article-level
  metrics</ext-link> help with navigating to related content: citations,
  blog posts, reader comments, etc. The
  <italic><italic>Notes</italic></italic> feature lets registered users
  highlight text for specific comments – very much what you would do on
  a printed paper (but with the added benefit that everybody can see
  this note).</p>
  <p>I'm most excited about projects that enhance the scientific paper
  instead of recreating an exact electronic version of the traditional
  paper. And HTML is a more promising format than PDF for these
  approaches. <italic><italic>Michael Clarke</italic></italic> (with
  whom I had the pleasure to do a session at SciFoo 2009) reminded us
  that <italic><italic>Tim Berners-Lee</italic></italic> invented the
  WWW in 1991 to facilitate scientific communication (with HTML and
  navigation both within and between documents as central concepts), but
  papers and journals have changed surprisingly little in the last 18
  years
  (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611111551/http://scholarlykitchen.sspnet.org/2010/01/04/why-hasnt-scientific-publishing-been-disrupted-already/">Why
  Hasn't Scientific Publishing Been Disrupted Already?</ext-link>).</p>
  <p>fn1. Many journals are scanning their older papers and make them
  available in electronic form, e.g.
  <italic><italic>Nature</italic></italic>. The first issue of
  <italic><italic>Nature</italic></italic> from 1869 can be seen
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611111551/http://www.nature.com/nature/about/first/index.html">here</ext-link>.</p>
  <p>fn2. We all know that computers haven't brought us the paperless
  office, but that we all use more paper than 10 years ago.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
