<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>How technology can help you to survive a
meeting</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2008-06-02">
<day>2</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2008</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>I'm currently in Chicago at the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611092305/http://www.asco.org/ASCO/Meetings/ASCO+Annual+Meeting">annual
meeting</ext-link> of the American Society of Clinical Oncology (ASCO).
This is a large meeting on clinical cancer research with about 30.000
people attending. Rather than writing about the specific research
presented and discussed at the meeting, I would like to talk about how
(web) technology can help in having a better conference. I will focus on
two (obvious) issues:</p>
<list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
    <p>How do I find the relevant information out of thousands of
    abstracts and sessions?</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>How can I benefit from the meeting even if not physically
    present?</p>
  </list-item>
</list>
<p>ASCO has done a number of things to help. All
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611092305/http://www.abstract.asco.org/">meeting
abstracts</ext-link> where made available a few weeks before the
meeting. The meeting program is available online, and you can create
your person schedule that you can print out or export to you calendar
software. The schedule is also available for Palm users. At the meeting,
you find free WiFi throughout the conference. Most talks are made
available as videocasts (for a fee now, made publicly available October
1) or podcasts. ASCO also even has an educational session with three
talks titled <italic><italic>Using the Internet to Keep Current: From
Podcasts to Virtual Meetings to RSS</italic></italic>.</p>
<p>Information about the meeting is difficult to find. With the
exception of blogs and websites that cover the meeting form a business
perspective – results from clinical trials presented at the meeting can
have a profound impact on the stock performance – there isn't a lot of
blogging about the meeting (as discussed
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611092305/http://network.nature.com/blogs/user/mfenner/2008/05/17/scientific-meetings-need-more-bloggers">here
before</ext-link>). This means that the filtering out of the interesting
information still has to be done the traditional way, basically going
through the 5000+ abstracts.</p>
<p>Conclusion: The meeting organizers provide a number of wonderful
tools, but they haven't yet discovered Web 2.0. More blogging or online
discussion would make the meting much more interesting. And the function
to create a personal schedule could be greatly enhanced by using user
input, e.g. listing the most popular talks or allowing you to share your
schedule with a colleague. You can get a lot out of the meeting even if
you are not physically present, but the information filtering has still
a way to go.</p>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
