<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>How do researchers use online journals?</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2010-03-08">
<day>8</day>
<month>3</month>
<year>2010</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<fig>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611102310im_/http://www.researchblogging.org/public/citation_icons/rb2_large_gray.png" xlink:title="" />
</fig>
<p>Last Monday I was listening to a very interesting presentation by
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611102310/http://www.ucl.ac.uk/infostudies/ian-rowlands/">Ian
Rowlands</ext-link>, reader in scholarly communication in the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611102310/http://www.infostudies.ucl.ac.uk/">Department
of Information Studies</ext-link> at University College London. He and
his colleagues are interested in how researchers find and use
information, and how this has changed with the internet, especially for
the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611102310/http://www.jisc.ac.uk/whatwedo/programmes/resourcediscovery/googlegen.aspx">Google
Generation</ext-link> (people born after 1993). If you want to be part
in this research (and have some fun), you can take part in the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611102310/http://www.bbc.co.uk/labuk/experiments/webbehaviour">BBC
Web Behaviour Test</ext-link>. The test will help you discover which
species of web animal you are (I'm a <bold><bold>fox</bold></bold>).</p>
<fig>
  <caption><p>Flickr photo by Craig Anderson.</p></caption>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611102310im_/http://farm1.static.flickr.com/14/17071467_11820b826c_d.jpg" xlink:title="" />
</fig>
<p>In another project, funded by the Research Information Network
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611102310/http://www.rin.ac.uk/">RIN</ext-link>),
Ian and his colleagues are studying how researchers are using electronic
journals. The findings of the first part of the project were presented
and discussed in a
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611102310/http://www.rin.ac.uk/news/events/e-journals-revolution-how-use-scholarly-journals-shaping-research">workshop
last July</ext-link>. The presentations are available as PDF download,
and as
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611102310/http://www.rin.ac.uk/resources/rin-publications/podcasts/e-journals-revolution-podcast">podcast</ext-link>
with interviews of the speakers. The findings were summarized in a paper
also published last July: <bold><bold>Online use and information seeking
behaviour: institutional and subject comparisons of UK
researchers</bold></bold>.</p>
<p>In the paper, the use of
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611102310/http://www.oxfordjournals.org/">Oxford
Journals</ext-link> by 10 major UK research institutions was analyzed in
the fields of life sciences, economics and history, using the server
logs for the full year 2007. Some of the key findings of the study
include:</p>
<sec id="one-third-of-users-access-oxford-journals-outside-business-hours">
  <title>One third of users access Oxford Journals outside business
  hours</title>
  <p>9.7% of uses happened on a Saturday/Sunday and 30.1% between 6 PM
  and 9 AM. This means that about one third of users accessed Oxford
  Journals outside typical business hours, either working late or from
  home (the study didn't distinguish between these two). These numbers
  indicate that remote access (from home, but probably also when
  traveling) is important for many users. This is obviously not an issue
  for Open Access journals, but institutions need to provide practical
  solutions
  (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611102310/http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Virtual_private_network">VPN</ext-link>,
  etc.) for subscription journals. From personal experience this remote
  access is still overly complicated. And these numbers also mean that
  librarians will not be available for support questions one third of
  the time.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="around-40-of-sessions-originated-from-a-google-search">
  <title>Around 40% of sessions originated from a Google Search</title>
  <p>In 2004 Oxford Journals opened up to Google for indexing. I didn't
  expect this important role that Google seems to play in finding
  scholarly papers, and I would be very interested in feedback from blog
  readers. Only 4% of sessions originated from Google Scholar (22% in
  economics). These results probably explain why Google Scholar hasn't
  seen that much development since it was launched. The search function
  at Oxford Journals was rarely used.</p>
  <p>43% of users of history journals, but only 16% of users of life
  sciences journals used navigational tools (table of contents, etc.)
  provided by the journal. This statistic obviously doesn't look at
  users getting the table of contents via email or RSS, but it again
  shows that access via search now probably is more common than via
  browsing.<sup><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611102310/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2010/03/08/evaluating_usage_patterns_of_online_journals/#fn1">1</ext-link></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="most-users-spend-little-time-on-journal-webpages-but-return-often">
  <title>Most users spend little time on journal webpages, but return
  often</title>
  <p>The average number of articles viewed per session was 1.1, and the
  average session time was just over 4 minutes. Users rather return
  often, usually via a search. These numbers indicate that journal
  webpages are not a place where users spend a lot of time. Unless
  journals change this (e.g. by more active involvement of users via
  comments and other social networking features, etc.), they probably
  can't expect to generate significant revenue from online advertising.
  The internet has not only dramatically changed the role of
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611102310/http://blogs.nature.com/mfenner/2010/01/24/scientists-and-librarians-friend-or-foe">libraries</ext-link>,
  but also for journals, as users are mostly interested in single
  articles, rather than the journal as a whole.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="the-median-age-of-articles-was-48-months-life-sciences-73-months-economics-and-90-months-history-">
  <title>The median age of articles was 48 months (life sciences), 73
  months (economics), and 90 months (history)</title>
  <p>In the life sciences only 25% of the articles were no more than 16
  months old, but another 25% were over 104 months old. I would have
  expected that the median age of articles would be much lower in the
  life sciences (it was two years in a similar study with
  ScienceDirect<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611102310/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2010/03/08/evaluating_usage_patterns_of_online_journals/#fn2">2</ext-link>).
  It seems as if most papers are not accessed when they are published
  (in the first few months after publication), but rather as the result
  of a search strategy, e.g. when writing a paper.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="life-sciences-users-rarely-read-abstracts-on-publisher-platforms">
  <title>Life sciences users rarely read abstracts on publisher
  platforms</title>
  <p>This should not come as a surprise, as life sciences users
  typically read abstracts in specialized databases, particularly
  <bold><bold>PubMed</bold></bold>. But maybe Journal publishers should
  stop displaying papers in an abstract view, saving users and
  themselves some effort. <italic><italic>PLoS</italic></italic>
  journals don't have an abstract view, but the <italic><italic>Biomed
  Central</italic></italic> journals (which are also Open Access) do.
  Subscription journals (including
  <italic><italic>Nature</italic></italic>) typically display the
  abstract instead of full-text to users without subscription access, so
  there is also no need for a separate abstract view for them.</p>
  <p>The number of PDF views was higher than the number of full-text
  HTML views (178,152 vs. 106,582). This difference was much more
  pronounced in economics and history journals, probably indicating that
  here most papers were printed out and
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611102310/http://blogs.nature.com/mfenner/2010/01/10/how-do-you-read-papers-2010-will-be-different">not
  read on the computer</ext-link>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="references">
  <title>References</title>
  <p>Nicholas, D., Clark, D., Rowlands, I., &amp; Jamali, H. (2009).
  Online use and information seeking behaviour: institutional and
  subject comparisons of UK researchers <italic>Journal of Information
  Science, 35</italic> (6), 660-676
  https://doi.org/<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611102310/http://dx.doi.org/10.1177/0165551509338341">10.1177/0165551509338341</ext-link></p>
  <p><sup>1</sup> My July 2008 blog post
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611102310/http://blogs.nature.com/mfenner/2008/07/19/do-online-journals-narrow-science-and-scholarship">Do
  online journals narrow science and scholarship?</ext-link> discussed
  potential consequences.</p>
  <p><sup>2</sup> CIBER, Evaluating the usage and impact of e-journals
  in the UK. Working paper 5. Available at
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611102310/http://www.ucl.ac.uk/infostudies/research/ciber/">http://www.ucl.ac.uk/infostudies/research/ciber/</ext-link></p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
