<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>How do you read papers?</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2008-11-02">
<day>2</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2008</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Working in science is as much about reading papers as it is about
writing papers. There are usually two ways you can come across an
interesting scientific paper:</p>
<list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
    <p><italic><italic>Active Searching</italic></italic>. Literature
    search on a particular topic</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p><italic><italic>Passive Browsing</italic></italic>. Scanning the
    literature in regular intervals for papers of interest</p>
  </list-item>
</list>
<p>The focused active search is typically used when you collect
information for a research project or write a paper or grant proposal.
This is stuff for another blog post and can be better explained by a
science librarian like
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003123041/http://network.nature.com/people/obst/profile">Oliver
Obst</ext-link> or
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003123041/http://network.nature.com/people/U81B5C465/profile">Frank
Norman</ext-link>. Now I want to talk about different ways to keep track
of the current literature in your field. I would assume that most if not
all people involved in science do this in one way or another, and I also
think that many people are struggling with the best strategy (see
Richard's related post on this topic:
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003123041/http://network.nature.com/people/rpg/blog/2008/10/27/too-many-fish-in-the-sea">Too
many fish in the sea</ext-link>).</p>
<p>The basic concept behind browsing is that it is a passive activity
where the scientific papers come to you regularly in one way or another.
A good strategy should be efficient (not involve too much of your time),
cost-effective and should have a good signal to noise ratio (i.e. finds
many interesting papers without going through too much uninteresting
stuff).</p>
<sec id="journal-subscriptions">
  <title>Journal Subscriptions</title>
  <p>The old-fashioned way. You receive a print copy of journals of
  interest in regular intervals and flip through the journal. This
  strategy works for a few journals, but is usually too expensive and
  too unfocused as a general strategy. I currently have three personal
  journal subscriptions, but the main reasons are that I either can't
  get them in electronic form or have no institutional subscription.
  Departmental subscriptions that are circulated around help saving some
  costs. But I have to confess that I haven't been to a library to flip
  through a few journals for more than 10 years. I very much like the
  feeling of a printed journal in my hands, but browsing in electronic
  form is not only cheaper but also much faster (even more so with
  articles released early in electronic form). Many journals now exist
  only in electronic form or
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003123041/http://resources.bmj.com/bmj/about-bmj/the-bmjs-publishing-model">publish
  articles continously</ext-link> rather than in a weekly or monthly
  schedule.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="journal-tables-of-content-toc-by-email-or-rss">
  <title>Journal tables of content (TOC) by email or RSS</title>
  <p>I would guess that this is currently the most popular browsing
  strategy. I prefer RSS to email because it means less clutter in my
  email inbox and because every journal article is a separate item that
  can be saved for later. I currently follow 8 journals.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003123041/http://mekentosj.com/papers/">Papers</ext-link>
  also uses this strategy, but this feature could be refined in future
  versions of the program. The TOC strategy probably works best for the
  leading journals in your field of research, but isn't very efficient
  for journals with only 1-2 interesting articles per issue, e.g. high
  volume general interest journals such as
  <italic><italic>PNAS</italic></italic>. Podcasts (e.g. the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003123041/http://www.nature.com/nature/podcast/">Nature
  Podcast</ext-link>) are basically extended TOCs in audio format.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="filtering-by-experts">
  <title>Filtering by experts</title>
  <p>You let someone else do the filtering for you. The traditional
  approach is the review article. The major drawback is of course the
  delay between publication of the original research and the publication
  of the review. A different – and faster – approach is used by
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003123041/http://www.f1000biology.com/">Faculty
  of 1000 Biology</ext-link> (they also have a similar service for
  medicine). The most interesting papers are highlighted and reviewed by
  leading researchers in the field. <italic><italic>Research
  Highlights</italic></italic> in
  <italic><italic>Nature</italic></italic> and similar features in other
  journals try to do the same on a much smaller scale.</p>
  <p>Filtering by experts is a resource-intensive and subjective
  process, and it is very possible that very exciting research published
  in an obscure journal might be missed. Most will remember that
  internet search started out with expert filtering, exemplified by
  Yahoo. It didn't work.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="filtering-by-author-or-keyword">
  <title>Filtering by author or keyword</title>
  <p>A good browsing strategy should consider the papers you have read
  already. In the approaches mentioned above this happens in your mind
  when you flip through the table of contents of a journal. A smarter
  approach is to regularly receive customized searches (again delivered
  via email or RSS). This is a popular strategy (explained
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003123041/http://www.nlm.nih.gov/pubs/techbull/mj05/mj05_rss.html">here</ext-link>
  for PubMed) and can involve keywords (e.g. the molecule or organism
  you work on) or authors (your colleagues and competitors).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="filtering-by-papers-you-read">
  <title>Filtering by papers you read</title>
  <p>A more systematic approach would not just pick a few keywords, but
  would use the information from all the papers you've read already,
  particulary those that you liked. Social bookmarking tools such as
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003123041/http://www.connotea.org/">Connotea</ext-link>
  or
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003123041/http://www.citeulike.org/">CiteULike</ext-link>
  have this information, but only if you give type in all those papers.
  It is more convenient to use that information directly from your
  reference manager where you have stored references or even fulltext
  PDFs to your most important papers anyway. Reference managers are
  usually used for writing papers and unfortunaly don't yet use this
  information to help you find interesting papers. One reason I like
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003123041/http://network.nature.com/people/mfenner/blog/2008/10/03/interview-with-alexander-griekspoor">Papers</ext-link>
  and
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003123041/http://network.nature.com/people/mfenner/blog/2008/09/05/interview-with-victor-henning-from-mendeley">Mendeley</ext-link>
  is that they both have the potential to fill this gap.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="filtering-by-papers-others-read">
  <title>Filtering by papers others read</title>
  <p>You probably have guessed that this blog post would somehow suggest
  a Web 2.0 solution to this problem. The papers stored in the reference
  manager of other scientists can of course be used to find papers that
  might also interest you. This process can of course be automated
  (rather than the personal recommendation from a colleague) and should
  be anonymous. But neither Connotea nor CiteULike do that, and I don't
  know of any other online tool currently available.</p>
  <p>In 2010 I want to use a tool that scans Pubmed or other databases
  for papers of interest based on the papers stored in my reference
  manager. The tool would give me a weekly report that can also be
  printed out for reading and note taking.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
