<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>How to use Citation Typing Ontology (CiTO) in your blog
posts</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2011-02-14">
<day>14</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2011</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>One of the annoyances with bibliographies as we use them for
scholarly papers is that is usually unclear why a particular paper was
cited. It is often possible for readers to gather this information by
looking at the citation in the context of the surrounding text, but this
is very difficult to automate. A highly cited paper might contain a
method that everybody uses, might be a review, or it might contain
information that everybody disagrees with. David Shotton has thought a
lot about this problem and has come up with
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611093455/http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/2041-1480-1-S1-S6">CiTO</ext-link>,
the Citation Typing Ontology:</p>
<p specific-use="wrapper">
  <disp-quote>
    <p>CiTO, the Citation Typing Ontology, is an ontology for describing
    the nature of reference citations in scientific research articles
    and other scholarly works, both to other such publications and also
    to Web information resources, and for publishing these descriptions
    on the Semantic Web.</p>
  </disp-quote>
</p>
<p>Using CiTO obviously means extra work for the author, so for
widespread use it is very important that CiTO is as easy to use as
possible. The first step would be to reduce the number of possible
relationships to a manageable number, e.g. not more than ten (CiTO
defines more than 20 relationships). Following a dinner discussion at
the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611093455/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2010/11/06/beyond-the-pdf-it-is-time-for-a-workshop/">Beyond
the PDF</ext-link> workshop, David Shotton kindly provided 10 popular
CiTO relationships to Alex Wade from Microsoft Research and me. I made
three little changes to the list: added “cites” as the default generic
relationship, dropped “shares authors with”, as this can be done better
with
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611093455/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2010/09/07/orcid-as-unique-author-identifier-what-is-it-good-for-and-should-we-worry-or-be-happy/">unique
author identifiers</ext-link>, and added “disagrees with” to have at
least one relationship that expresses disagreement.</p>
<p>In the next step I added these relationships to my
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611093455/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2011/01/11/having-fun-with-citations-at-scienceonline2011/">Link
to Link</ext-link> WordPress plugin, and I released the updated version
(1.1) today. Using CiTO is an option that can be turned off, but the
plugin makes it very easy to use CiTO relationships when inserting
references into a blog post:</p>
<fig>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611093455im_/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/files/2011/02/cito-500x433.jpg" xlink:title="cito" />
</fig>
<p>The CiTO relationship is stored in the <bold><bold>rel</bold></bold>
attribute of the link that is created – currently as free-form text, but
this can be changed to the <bold><bold>cito:DisagreesWith</bold></bold>
format. This information can easily be extracted by computers, or made
available in the bibliography to readers. The Reference Manager
CiteULike is
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611093455/http://opencitations.wordpress.com/2010/10/21/use-of-cito-in-citeulike/">also
supporting CiTO</ext-link>, but we need many more CiTO tools for
authors.</p>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
