<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>How to close the digital divide among
scientists</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2009-06-14">
<day>14</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2009</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>The term <italic><italic>digital divide</italic></italic> usually
describes <italic><italic>the troubling gap between those who use
computers and the Internet and those who do not</italic></italic>
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151001173737/http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Digital_divide">Wikipedia</ext-link>).
Many if not most scientists are experienced users of computers and the
internet, and use email or public databases such as
<italic><italic>PubMed</italic></italic> on a daily basis. But few
scientists regularly use Web 2.0 tools, which would include both general
tools such as <italic><italic>Twitter</italic></italic>,
<italic><italic>FriendFeed</italic></italic> or
<italic><italic>Facebook</italic></italic>, as well as tools
specifically targeted at scientists (and this would of course include
<italic><italic>Nature Network</italic></italic>).</p>
<p>Regular readers of this blog know that I am fascinated by technology,
especially if this technology makes it easier to publish scientific
papers. And like others I sometimes get carried away
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151001173737/http://network.nature.com/people/mfenner/blog/2009/05/28/google-wave-dont-forget-the-scientists">Google
Wave</ext-link> is a good recent example). Even among those scientists
open to blogs, wikis, etc., not everybody wants to follow every
technology trend. This could simply be because that would take too much
time, but most people probably just don't care that much about
technology.</p>
<p>So what can we do about this digital divide among scientists? Science
is often very specialized, and sometimes only a few people participate
in a discussion about a particular topic.
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151001173737/http://radar.oreilly.com/">Tim
O'Reilly</ext-link> has coined the term <italic><italic>alpha
geek</italic></italic> for people that are the first to use new
technologies, and there certainly is a place for <italic><italic>science
alpha geeks</italic></italic>. But Science Online is about science
communication, and communication tools that are used by only a handful
of people usually don't fulfill their purpose.</p>
<p>One easy solution would be to simply wait 10-20 years until most
senior scientists are
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151001173737/http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Digital_native">digital
natives</ext-link> (those that have grown up with digital technology
such as computers, the Internet or mobile phones), but that seems to be
an awfully long time for something this important.</p>
<p>We could build better tools. Good tools simply work and don't need a
lot of explanations. For me
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151001173737/http://mekentosj.com/papers/">Papers</ext-link>
is such a tool, but strictly speaking not really Web 2.0, because it has
no collaboration features. <italic><italic>Google Wave</italic></italic>
could be another example, but only the next few months will tell. What
makes a good Web 2.0 tool for scientists? Most importantly, that the
tool solves an important everyday problem. Equally important, that there
aren't high hurdles in using this tool in terms of cost and learning
curve. Another hurdle: some Web 2.0 tools only start to become useful
once they have signed up a large enough number of users.</p>
<p>But we also need to do more to communicate the usefulness of online
tools for scientists. The original definition of the digital divide has
a negative meaning and everybody probably agrees that we should at least
try to overcome this divide. Although there certainly is also a digital
divide among scientists, the general perception is probably not that
those scientists that are not Web 2.0-savvy are at a disadvantage. We
should have a much closer look at the tools that are currently
available, define the scenarios where they can be useful, and focus on
that. We talk too much about the details, technical or otherwise. One
example: most scientists probably want to have an idea of when an online
reference manager can be helpful rather than the tools they currently
use, rather than discuss the subtle differences between the very similar
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151001173737/http://www.citeulike.org/">CiteULike</ext-link>,
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151001173737/http://www.connotea.org/">Connotea</ext-link>,
and
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151001173737/http://www.2collab.com/">2collab</ext-link>.
Part of the problem is that people want to make money with their Web 2.0
tools for scientists, but forget that collaboration is more important
than competition when the market still has to grow and is currently
probably too small for viable business opportunities.</p>
<p>This makes closing the digital divide among scientists very much a
science education exercise, and I think that science librarians should
play a central role in this. Not surprisingly, a seminar last week by
our local science librarian in our department and
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151001173737/http://scienceblogs.com/confessions/2009/06/cool_conferences_mental_overlo.php">a
blog post</ext-link> by science librarian John Dupuis (and the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151001173737/http://friendfeed.com/johndupuis/8c6723b0/cool-conferences-mental-overload">FriendFeed</ext-link>
discussion around his blog post) were the inspiration for this post
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151001173737/http://friendfeed.com/coturnix/562bc610/wow-sunday-afternoon-and-i-don-t-even-know-on-what">another
FriendFeed discussion</ext-link> started by Bora Zivkovic made be write
the post today instead of going to bed early).</p>
<p><italic><italic>Update 06/15/09:</italic></italic>
One good strategy to overcome the digital divide among scientists would
be a <italic><italic>Science 2.0 Cookbook</italic></italic>. Similar in
format to the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151001173737/http://oreilly.com/store/series/cookbooks.csp">O'Reilly
Cookbook series</ext-link> for programming problems, the Science 2.0
cookbook would use the format problem/solution/discussion to provide a
solution for problems like <italic><italic>How do I share references
with my coworkers in the lab?</italic></italic> This could be started as
a Wiki project.</p>
<fig>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151001173737im_/http://www.linkwithin.com/pixel.png" xlink:title="" />
</fig>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
