<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Human-readable and machine-readable Persistent
Identifiers</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2015-05-27">
<day>27</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2015</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Yesterday Julie McMurry and co-authors published a preprint
<bold><bold>10 Simple rules for design, provision, and reuse of
persistent identifiers for life science data</bold></bold> (McMurry et
al., 2015). This is an important paper trying to address a fundamental
problem: how can we make persistent identifiers both human-readable and
machine-readable?</p>
<p>Don’t be fooled by the title (used frequently by
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ploscollections.org/article/browse/issue/info%3Adoi%2F10.1371%2Fissue.pcol.v03.i01">PLOS
Computational Biology</ext-link>) - the paper doesn’t describe simple
rules that help the average life sciences researcher. Rather, the paper
deals with rather complex issues, and has 36 authors.</p>
<p>There is general agreement that we need persistent identifiers for
scholarly communication, and that also includes life sciences datasets,
the focus of the paper. What is less clear is how to express these
persistent identifiers. An identifier such as
<bold><bold>AB020317</bold></bold> - for the mouse p53 gene - is
ambiguous. It is not clear without additional information that this is
an identifier for the GenBank nucleotide database, rather than
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/alexcycu/8936663973/">something
completely different</ext-link>. One common approach to make this
identifier unambiguous is to use URIs (Uniform Resource Identifiers),
e.g.
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/AB020317">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/AB020317</ext-link>
in this case.</p>
<p>The paper doesn’t like this approach, and even states that “URIs are
still among the most commonly used and most problematic identifiers in
the bio-data ecosystem”. The text also states that “their length makes
them unwieldy for humans working with the data or for referencing in
publications or other text”, but doesn’t go into any detail why URIs are
“problematic identifiers”, or why length is an issue in an online
environment.</p>
<p>This is an important weakness of the paper, because the authors
propose an alternative: CURIEs or <bold><bold>compact
URIs</bold></bold>. CURIEs were
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.w3.org/TR/curie/">proposed</ext-link>
by the W3C a few years ago, as a way to make URIs
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://crosstech.crossref.org/2008/12/curies_a_cure_for_uris.html">more
human-readable</ext-link>. The idea is simple, we use a namespace in
addition to the local identifier, separated by a colon, e.g.
<bold><bold><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/ena/data/view/AB020317">Genbank:AB020317</ext-link></bold></bold>.</p>
<p>This approach has of course been common practice in the life sciences
before CURIEs or even the WWW existed, and is still the most common
approach how identifiers for life sciences data are referenced in the
scholarly literature. Unfortunately there are important problems with
CURIEs, most of them mentioned in the paper:</p>
<list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
    <p>Persistent identifiers need to be resolvable, without additional
    information we don’t know what to do with
    <bold><bold><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/ena/data/view/AB020317">Genbank:AB020317</ext-link></bold></bold>.
    Most life sciences researchers understand this CURIE, but that might
    not necessarily be true for less commonly used namespaces</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>Namespaces are not necessarily unique, the paper uses
    <bold><bold>GEO</bold></bold> (which could mean Gene Expression
    Omnibus or GeoNames Ontology) as an example</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>Rule 3 in the paper goes into great detail what characters and
    patterns should be avoided in local identifiers that are part of a
    CURIE. It is not clear whether these recommendations will always be
    followed or how to check them</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>CURIEs should follow a pattern (regular expression) so that they
    can be extracted from a text. We know (Kafkas, Kim, &amp; McEntyre,
    2013) that extracting identifiers from journal articles is possible,
    but difficult</p>
  </list-item>
</list>
<p>URIs don’t have the problems listed above: they resolve, are unique,
and there is good understanding (and available tools) of how a valid URI
should look like and how to extract URIs from text documents. That is
why URIs are good representations of persistent identifiers.</p>
<p>Another problem I have with CURIEs: the idea doesn’t seem to have
caught on from the initial work more than five years ago (background
reading
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://manu.sporny.org/2011/case-for-curies/">here</ext-link>).
I’m not even sure what percentage of persistent identifier experts know
about CURIEs.</p>
<p>My recommendation for life sciences data: express persistent
identifiers as URIs. Now that can go into 10 simple rules for the
average life sciences researcher.</p>
<p><italic>P.S. This blog uses a tool
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://blog.martinfenner.org/2013/07/02/auto-generating-links-to-data-and-resources/">I
wrote two years ago</ext-link> that automatically turns CURIEs in the
text into links.</italic></p>
<sec id="references">
  <title>References</title>
  <p>Kafkas, Ş., Kim, J.-H., &amp; McEntyre, J. R. (2013). Database
  Citation in Full Text Biomedical Articles. <italic>PLoS ONE</italic>.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0063184">doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0063184</ext-link></p>
  <p>McMurry, J., Blomberg, N., Burdett, T., Conte, N., Dumontier, M.,
  Fellows, D. K., … Parkinson, H. (2015). 10 Simple rules for design,
  provision, and reuse of persistent identifiers for life science data.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.18003">doi:10.5281/zenodo.18003</ext-link></p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
