<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>I like poster sessions</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2008-06-04">
<day>4</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2008</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>As I
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611092256/http://network.nature.com/blogs/user/mfenner/2008/03/01/are-posters-worth-the-effort">said
before</ext-link> on this blog, I do like poster sessions. The poster
sessions at the just finished
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611092256/http://www.asco.org/">American
Society of Clinical Oncology</ext-link> meeting didn't offer food and
drink, but were otherwise very enjoyable. The meeting is probably
special because a lot of high quality research will be presented as
poster, as there is just not enough time for enough oral sessions. Many
of the poster presenters were senior faculty. I also like the printouts
that were available from most posters – but there still was a lot of
picture taking with digital cameras. A very good feature was the oral
summary of some of the poster sessions: 15 minute presentations of 5-10
posters, summarized and commented on by an expert in the field.</p>
<p>I had some very informative discussions with a number of poster
presenters. When you are familiar with the research topic it is often
possible to go straight to the interesting issues, the nonlinear and
interactive format of a poster is then often better than an oral
presentation. The downside of a poster presentation is obviously that
the format is good for presenting to a small audience only. But the
poster presenter will usually get much more feedback than from an oral
presentation.</p>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
