<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>In which I suggest a preprint archive for clinical
trials</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2010-10-16">
<day>16</day>
<month>10</month>
<year>2010</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>The
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20101105203901/http://arxiv.org/">ArXiv</ext-link>
preprint archive for research articles in physics, mathematics, computer
science and related disciplines
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20101105203901/http://people.ccmr.cornell.edu/~ginsparg/blurb/pg02pr.html">was
initiated</ext-link> by Paul Ginsparg in 1991. ArXiv enables the rapid
dissemination of research articles prior to peer review, and it quickly
became very successful in this. ArXiv has not made the peer-reviewed
journal obsolete, but rather provides a service that traditional
journals – and that also includes Open Access journals – can’t provide.
By 1998, more than 90% of all peer-reviewed papers published in
high-energy physics
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20101105203901/http://arxiv.org/abs/0906.5418">first
appeared on ArXiv</ext-link>.
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20101105203901/http://precedings.nature.com/">Nature
Precedings</ext-link> was started in 2007 to provide similar services
for research in biology, medicine (except clinical trials), chemistry
and earth sciences. In addition, many preprints are also hosted in
institutional repositories.</p>
<p>The research that I am doing is clinical research, trying to improve
the treatment of patients with cancer. Most clinical trials are drug
trials, but there are also surgical interventions, trials with medical
devices, etc. Clinical trials are a special kind of research, and I have
talked about some aspects
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20101105203901/http://blogs.nature.com/mfenner/2010/03/15/chances-and-problems-of-doing-science-online">in
a previous post</ext-link>. Registration of clinical trials before the
first patient is treated – providing
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20101105203901/http://www.who.int/ictrp/network/trds/en/index.html">key
information</ext-link> from the trial protocol – is now required in many
countries, including the United States and the European Union. The U.S.
database of registered clinical trials
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20101105203901/http://clinicaltrials.gov/">Clinicaltrials.gov</ext-link>)
is publicly available, and the EU is working on doing the same with
their
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20101105203901/https://eudract.ema.europa.eu/">EudraCT</ext-link>
database. The International Committee of Medical Journal Editors
(ICMJE), and in consequence many medical journals, also
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20101105203901/http://www.icmje.org/publishing_10register.html">requires
clinical trial registration</ext-link>. Since September 2008 the U.S.
Food and Drug Administration (FDA) also
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20101105203901/http://blogs.nature.com/mfenner/2008/08/02/fdaaa-push-to-open-data-in-clinical-medicine">requires</ext-link>
all clinical trials registered at Clinicaltrials.gov to provide key
results within 12 months after the last patient has finished
treatment.</p>
<fig>
  <caption><p><italic><italic>Flickr image by
  myelinrepairfoundation.</italic></italic></p></caption>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20101105203901im_/http://farm5.static.flickr.com/4095/4861245046_54d92ddfa9.jpg" xlink:title="" />
</fig>
<p>The results of clinical trials are rarely first reported in a
peer-reviewed journal, but rather are usually first presented at a
conference – in the case of important practice-changing clinical trials
often before an audience of thousands of people. The conference
abstracts are also an important source of information, even though they
don’t provide the space for more detailed information, including tables
and figures. Many societies publish conference abstract in their society
journals, but bibliographic databases such as PubMed probably don’t
cover all conference abstracts reporting clinical trial results.</p>
<p>The peer-reviewed paper is usually published months or even years
after the conference presentation. This not only allows for more mature
data – e.g. survival information – but also critical review and
discussion of the data. The publication of the peer-reviewed paper is
<bold><bold>not</bold></bold> the first time the medical community
learns about the results of a clinical trial, or draws conclusions for
their own research or clinical practice. To take a recent example from a
clinical trial in cancer: the results of the TROPIC trial of cabazitaxel
chemotherapy in hormone-refractory metastatic prostate cancer
(Clinicaltrials.gov
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20101105203901/http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT00417079">NCT00417079</ext-link>)
were
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20101105203901/http://www.asco.org/ASCOv2/Meetings/Abstracts?&amp;vmview=abst_detail_view&amp;confID=73&amp;abstractID=30560">first
reported</ext-link> at the ASCO Genitourinary Cancers Symposium March 5
(and there was a
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20101105203901/http://en.sanofi-aventis.com/binaries/20100304_Asco_GU_en_tcm28-27547.pdf">press
release</ext-link> a day earlier). Capazitaxel
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20101105203901/http://www.fda.gov/AboutFDA/CentersOffices/CDER/ucm216214.htm">was
approved</ext-link> by the FDA on June 17, and I treated the first
patient with the drug in September. The peer-reviewed paper
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20101105203901/http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0140-6736(10)61389-X">was
published</ext-link> in <italic><italic>The Lancet</italic></italic>
October 2.</p>
<p>I would like to suggest that we need a preprint archive for clinical
trial research papers. The preprints should be uploaded at the time of
journal submission, or shortly after the conference presentation. The
preprint server should add some structure to the preprints, e.g. linking
to both the clinical trials registry (Clinicaltrials.gov, EudraCT, and
others) and the published paper. The preprint should fulfill the
requirement for reporting results set by the FDA. Articles in the
preprint archive should be freely available, and should ideally provide
the main results as downloadable datasets. The preprint server will only
work if medical journals – and ideally the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20101105203901/http://www.icmje.org/">ICMJE</ext-link>
– have a clear policy allowing prior publication as preprint.</p>
<p><italic><italic>This post was inspired by discussions with Salvatore
Mele and Ivan Oransky. And it is my first contribution to
the</italic></italic>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20101105203901/http://www.openaccessweek.org/"><italic><italic>Open
Access Week</italic></italic></ext-link> <italic><italic>that starts on
Monday.</italic></italic></p>
<fig>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20101105203901im_/http://www.linkwithin.com/pixel.png" xlink:title="" />
</fig>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
