<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>In which I became a conference blogger</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2008-07-13">
<day>13</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2008</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>The 20th
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611091433/http://www.geneticsberlin2008.com/">International
Congress of Genetics</ext-link> started in Berlin yesterday. This is the
first time that I attend a meeting as a science blogger. An interesting
experience since you look at the talks from a different perspective and
you have to try to cover topics that are of general interest but often
not really your area of expertise.</p>
<p>The conference started yesterday afternoon with a press conference
with Rudi Balling, Alfred Nordheim, Mario Capecchi, Christiane
Nüsslein-Volhard, Oliver Smithies and Ernst-Ludwig Winnacker. The
International Congress of Genetics takes place every 5 years, but wasn't
held in Germany since 1927. The main reason for this is the horrible
crimes that were done between 1933 and 1945 in the name of “Eugenics”
[1]. This dark history of Genetics in Germany was also discussed at the
press conference. On July 14 there will be a special announcement by the
German Society for Human Genetics
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611091433/http://www.gfhev.de/en/index.htm">GfH</ext-link>),
as this is the 75th anniversary of a German law that allowed the
sterilization of people with “genetic” diseases against their will. The
GfH will say that they deeply regret the behavior of German geneticists
during that time. This is a topic that has special meaning to me, since
one of the leading German geneticists involved was
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611091433/http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Otmar_Freiherr_von_Verschuer">Ottmar
von Verschuer</ext-link> who is a cousin of my great-grandmother. The
German Research Foundation (DFG) did
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611091433/http://www.mpiwg-berlin.mpg.de/KWG/guests_e.htm">extensive
research</ext-link> on the involvement of the Kaiser-Wilhelm Society
(which became the DFG after 1945) in the crimes committed between 1933
and 1945 in the beginning of this century (see this
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611091433/http://www.nature.com/nature/journal/v425/n6959/full/425650b.html">Nature
News</ext-link> article).</p>
<p>Another topic debated in the press conference was the use of genetics
to treat patients, more specifically gene therapy and stem cells. Mario
Capecchi and others stressed that ethical decisions on these issues
should be done by society and that the scientists would only provide the
tools. Oliver Smithies pointed out that we should make the clear
distinction between somatic gene therapy and gene therapy targeting the
germline, and that the latter approach would be not only risky but in
most cases uneccessary.</p>
<p>The expectations for the conference were nicely summarized by Oliver
Smithies, who said that science happens in unexpected jumps, and that
these jumps are often produced by people from whom you don't expect
it.</p>
<p>fn1. I previously blogged about how the journal Nature
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611091433/http://network.nature.com/blogs/user/mfenner/2007/10/23/nature-in-nazi-germany-70-years-ago-no-open-access">was
banned</ext-link> in Germany 70 years ago.</p>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
