<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Increased cancer risk following computed tomography
scans</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2009-12-20">
<day>20</day>
<month>12</month>
<year>2009</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<fig>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150922174153im_/http://www.researchblogging.org/public/citation_icons/rb2_large_gray.png" xlink:title="" />
</fig>
<p>Two papers
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150922174153/http://dx.doi.org/10.1001/archinternmed.2009.427">this</ext-link>
and
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150922174153/http://http//dx.doi.org/10.1001/archinternmed.2009.440">this</ext-link>)
and an
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150922174153/http://dx.doi.org/10.1001/archinternmed.2009.453">editorial</ext-link>
in the latest issue of <italic><italic>Archives of Internal
Medicine</italic></italic> examine the cancer risks associated with the
use of computed tomography (CT)
examinations.<sup><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150922174153/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2009/12/20/increased_cancer_risk_following_computed_tomography_scans/#fn1">1</ext-link></sup></p>
<p>Ionizing radiation increases the risk for developing cancer. There is
direct evidence from atomic bomb survivors in Japan in 1945 and from
nuclear accidents such as the one in Chernobyl in 1986. There are no
studies directly demonstrating an increased cancer risk from the
diagnostic use of X-rays (either conventional radiographs or computed
tomography), as this would require long-term follow-up of a very large
number of people. This risk can only be estimated, based on the
assumption that there is no lower radiation threshold dose for cancer
risk and that a linear correlation exists between dose and cancer risk.
Similarly, we know very little about the actual radiation doses that
patients receive during a diagnostic CT scan.</p>
<p>The paper by <bold><bold>Rebecca Smith-Bindman</bold></bold> and her
coworkers looked at the radiation doses associated with the 11 most
common computed tomography examinations in four hospitals in the San
Francisco Bay Area. Radiation doses to individual patients were not
measured directly, but were estimated using the commonly used “effective
dose”. Median effective doses for routine computed tomography of the
head, chest and abdomen-pelvis were 2, 8 and 16 mSv. The highest median
effective doses (31 mSv) were used for multiphase CTs of the
abdomen-pelvis (range 6-90 mSv). The 8 mSv dose for a routine chest CT
is equivalent to 119 conventional chest X-rays. Interestingly, there was
wide variation of effective doses used both between hospitals and within
the same institution (with a mean 13-fold variation between highest and
lowest dose for each CT study type).</p>
<p>Based on these doses, the authors then estimated the increased risk
for radiation-induced cancer following a CT examination. This risk is
higher in younger people and in women. Women have a higher risk to
develop lung cancer following radiation exposure and they have the added
risk of developing breast cancer. The authors estimated that it would
for example require approximately 620 CT scans for ruling out pulmonary
embolism in 40-year-old women to induce one cancer.</p>
<p>The second paper by <bold><bold>Amy Berrington de
Gonzalez</bold></bold> and coworkers tried to calculate the total number
of CT scans performed in the US in 2007, and estimated the increased
risk for cancer related to these CT scans based on examination type, age
and sex. They used a similar model to calculate the cancer risk as the
first paper. Overall, about 72 million CT scans were performed in the US
in 2007. The authors estimated that approximately 29.000 additional
cancers will eventually develop, equivalent to approximately 2% of all
cancers diagnosed annually in the US.</p>
<p>CT scans have dramatically improved patient care, and the conclusions
of these two papers should not preclude their use in patients where the
potential benefits clearly outweigh the risks mentioned above. But in
order to reduce the cancer risk associated with CT scans, the authors of
the two papers and the editorial suggest to optimize and standardize the
CT scan procedure (remember the 13-fold difference in dose for the same
procedure) and to decrease the number of unnecessary examinations. The
latter is most relevant when CT scans are performed as screening
procedures.</p>
<p>More blog posts discussing these papers can be found on
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150922174153/http://blogs.nature.com/stories/2049">Nature
Blogs</ext-link> and
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150922174153/http://www.cancer.org/aspx/Blog/Comments.aspx?id=336">Dr.
Len's Cancer Blog</ext-link>.</p>
<p><sup>1</sup> All three papers are available as full-text without a
subscription. And none of the papers displays it's DOI, which makes
linking to them unneccessarily difficult.</p>
<sec id="references">
  <title>References</title>
  <p>Smith-Bindman, R., Lipson, J., Marcus, R., Kim, K., Mahesh, M.,
  Gould, R., Berrington de Gonzalez, A., &amp; Miglioretti, D. (2009).
  Radiation Dose Associated With Common Computed Tomography Examinations
  and the Associated Lifetime Attributable Risk of Cancer
  <italic>Archives of Internal Medicine, 169</italic> (22), 2078-2086
  https://doi.org/<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1001/archinternmed.2009.427">10.1001/archinternmed.2009.427</ext-link></p>
  <p>Berrington de Gonzalez, A., Mahesh, M., Kim, K., Bhargavan, M.,
  Lewis, R., Mettler, F., &amp; Land, C. (2009). Projected Cancer Risks
  From Computed Tomographic Scans Performed in the United States in 2007
  <italic>Archives of Internal Medicine, 169</italic> (22), 2071-2077
  https://doi.org/<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1001/archinternmed.2009.440">10.1001/archinternmed.2009.440</ext-link></p>
  <p>Redberg, R. (2009). Cancer Risks and Radiation Exposure From
  Computed Tomographic Scans: How Can We Be Sure That the Benefits
  Outweigh the Risks? <italic>Archives of Internal Medicine,
  169</italic> (22), 2049-2050
  https://doi.org/<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150922174153/http://dx.doi.org/10.1001/archinternmed.2009.453">10.1001/archinternmed.2009.453</ext-link></p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
