<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Interview with Moshe Pritsker</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2009-01-24">
<day>24</day>
<month>1</month>
<year>2009</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>The
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053056/http://scienceonline09.com/">ScienceOnline09</ext-link>
meeting last weekend not only had a number of interesting presentations
and discussions, but even more importantly, was a great opportunity to
personally interact with a great number of people that share your ideas
and interests. It was the first time I personally met
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053056/http://network.nature.com/people/U06343707/profile">Moshe
Pritsker</ext-link>, the CEO, Editor-in-Chief and co-founder of the
Journal of Visualized Experiments
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053056/http://www.jove.com/">JoVE</ext-link>),
<italic><italic>a peer-reviewed, free access, online journal devoted to
the publication of biological research in a video
format</italic></italic> (taken from
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053056/http://www.jove.com/index.stt">About
JoVE</ext-link>). As I like to write about new technologies that help
scientists publish their research, I asked Moshe a few questions after
the meeting.</p>
<sec id="1-can-you-describe-what-jove-is-and-does">
  <title>1. Can you describe what JoVE is and does?</title>
  <p><italic><italic>JoVE</italic></italic> is the first video journal
  for biological and biomedical research. We publish articles that
  include step-by-step video demonstrations of experimental techniques
  and procedures. For example,
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053056/http://www.jove.com/index/details.stp?ID=923">A
  Behavioral Assay to Measure Responsiveness of Zebrafish to Changes in
  Light Intensities</ext-link> by the group of John Dowling at Harvard
  or
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053056/http://www.jove.com/index/details.stp?ID=1067">Calcium
  Imaging of Cortical Neurons using Fura-2 AM</ext-link> by the group of
  Ricardo Dolmetsch at Stanford. We call these articles video-articles
  or video-protocols. They also include a text part which is similar to
  traditional scientific articles (abstract, introduction, experiment,
  materials and references).</p>
  <p>This novel video-based approach to scientific publishing is applied
  to increase reproducibility and transparency of experimental studies,
  which is the <italic><italic>bottleneck</italic></italic> problem in
  the life sciences today. As every bench scientist knows, it is very
  difficult to repeat biological experiments based on their text
  description in traditional scientific journals. This is because the
  text format presents a requirement for scientists to understand the
  complex reality and numerous <italic><italic>small</italic></italic>
  details of the experiment from reading. It is very difficult.
  Visualization through video provides a solution to this problem by
  clear unambiguous demonstration of experimental techniques and
  procedures. Using this new approach will enable increase efficiency
  and productivity across all the areas of biological research and drug
  discovery.</p>
  <p>Being a scientific journal, <italic><italic>JoVE</italic></italic>
  is indexed in PubMed and MEDLINE, and has an editorial board of 22
  distinguished professors from Harvard, Princeton, NIH and other
  leading institutions in US, Europe and Japan. After two years, since
  its foundation in October 2006, <italic><italic>JoVE</italic></italic>
  has published nearly 300 articles across all the areas of experimental
  biology including neuroscience, cell biology, developmental biology,
  stem cell research, immunology, bioengineering and plant biology. Most
  of the articles are produced at the laboratories in the leading
  academic research institutions including Harvard, MIT, Berkeley,
  Stanford, UCSF, Yale and others.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="2-what-kind-of-research-is-well-suited-to-be-published-in-jove-and-what-kind-of-research-doesn-t-work-well">
  <title>2. What kind of research is well-suited to be published in
  JOVE? And what kind of research doesn't work well?</title>
  <p>The <italic><italic>JoVE</italic></italic> video-based format of
  publication is very effective for description of experimental
  techniques in all the areas of biological and clinical research. We
  have accumulated a lot of experience in production and publication of
  video-articles in these areas. This format can be also applied for
  experiments in chemistry and physics. For example, we have recently
  published a video-article on a
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053056/http://www.jove.com/index/details.stp?ID=942">creation
  of chemical libraries using Ugi reaction</ext-link> by
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053056/http://network.nature.com/people/jcbradley/profile&amp;#39;s">Jean-Claude
  Bradley</ext-link> group at Drexel University.</p>
  <p>We have less experience with video-publication on theoretical and
  computational research, e.g. bioinformatics. We currently explore
  developing different formats for these non-experimental areas of
  science.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="3-how-do-you-help-authors-with-video-production">
  <title>3. How do you help authors with video production?</title>
  <p>We know that most scientists do not have experience in
  video-production, and therefore cannot make good quality videos on
  their own experiments. Therefore, we take complete responsibility for
  this part. Specifically, we send video-professionals to film at the
  laboratories that want to publish their experiments in
  <italic><italic>JoVE</italic></italic>.</p>
  <p>The entire <italic><italic>JoVE</italic></italic> publication
  process works as following:</p>
  <list list-type="bullet">
    <list-item>
      <p>authors submits a text description (protocol) of their
      experiment to <italic><italic>JoVE</italic></italic></p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p><italic><italic>JoVE</italic></italic> sends one of its
      video-professionals to film the experiment in the authors’
      laboratory</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p><italic><italic>JoVE</italic></italic> editors edit the
      video</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>the video is submitted to the approval by authors and
      reviewers</p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
  <p>To facilitate integration of video into scientific publishing,
  <italic><italic>JoVE</italic></italic> has developed a network of
  video-professionals to conduct production of scientific videos in
  research labs across 30 cities in USA, Canada, UK, Germany and Japan
  including such centers of academic research as Boston, San Diego, San
  Francisco, New York, Chicago, Seattle, Toronto, Vancouver, London,
  Berlin and others. These video-professionals are selected, interviewed
  and trained by <italic><italic>JoVE</italic></italic> before they are
  sent to film in the laboratories. This infrastructure enables
  production and publication of video-articles from university
  laboratories around the world.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="4-can-you-talk-a-little-bit-about-the-peer-review-process">
  <title>4. Can you talk a little bit about the peer review
  process?</title>
  <p>The video-articles are sent to reviewers in a regular fashion: 2-3
  anonymous reviewers at different universities. The reviewers provide
  their comments according to the timeline in videos, e.g.
  &quot;introduce changes at 2 minutes 35 seconds&quot;. They also
  provide comments on the text part, e.g. &quot;introduce changes in
  paragraph 4&quot;.</p>
  <p>We are more interested in the applicability and technical clarity
  rather than novelty of the methods published. To achieve our goal, to
  increase transparency and efficiency in biological research, we need
  to visualize all the experimental techniques applied today. It is less
  important whether they are <italic><italic>old</italic></italic> or
  <italic><italic>new</italic></italic>. For example, purification and
  transplantation of hematopoetic stem cells are used for more than 40
  years. Yet, it is very difficult, even impossible, to learn these
  techniques based on text descriptions. So, it should be published on
  video.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="5-what-are-your-responsibilities-within-jove">
  <title>5. What are your responsibilities within JoVE?</title>
  <p>As every CEO of a start-up, I wear multiple hats. I oversee and
  coordinate the work of different parts of
  <italic><italic>JoVE</italic></italic> including editorial,
  publishing, IT, video-production, business development, marketing and
  sales. My personal responsibilities as Editor-in-Chief include
  management of the editorial and publishing processes, marketing in
  academia and publishing industry, and PR.</p>
  <p>I consider myself <italic><italic>EXTREMELY</italic></italic> lucky
  to meet very smart and hard-working people working with me on
  <italic><italic>JoVE</italic></italic>, including my two partners and
  <italic><italic>JoVE</italic></italic> co-founders, Nikita Bernstein
  and Klaus Korak (M.D.). Among others are Aaron Kolski-Andreaco
  (Ph.D.), Nandita Singh (Ph.D.), Mark Shalinsky (Ph.D.), Alvin Liang
  and Lori Chesla. A large fraction of doctorate-holders in the team
  enables us to adapt our innovative product to the high demands of the
  scientific community.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="6-what-did-you-do-before-starting-to-work-for-jove">
  <title>6. What did you do before starting to work for JoVE?</title>
  <p>I was doing my Ph.D. in Molecular Biology at Princeton, working on
  embryonic stem cells and bioinformatics. This is where the
  <italic><italic>JoVE</italic></italic> idea was born since I, like any
  other scientists around, was suffering from low reproducibility of
  experiments. Then I was working as a post-doc at Harvard Medical
  School, Massachusetts General Hospital, for one year. Then I met my
  partners, Nikita Bernstein and Klaus Korak, and
  <italic><italic>JoVE</italic></italic> was started.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="7-do-you-want-to-talk-about-future-plans-for-jove">
  <title>7. Do you want to talk about future plans for JoVE?</title>
  <p>My dream is to build a large comprehensive online video-library
  that will include a video-protocol for every possible experimental
  technique in biological and medical research. This will tremendously
  increase productivity of research in academia and biotech industry,
  accelerating development of new technologies and drug discovery. This
  will also have a strong impact on scientific education and science
  policy at all levels.</p>
  <p>Being initially focused on basic biological research, we received
  numerous requests to expand our approach into clinical medicine,
  psychology and other fields. We are doing our first
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053056/http://www.jove.com/index/details.stp?ID=992">steps</ext-link>
  in these directions too.</p>
  <p><italic><italic>Further Reading</italic></italic></p>
  <list list-type="bullet">
    <list-item>
      <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053056/http://jove-blog.blogspot.com/">Official
      JoVE blog</ext-link> with posts from
      <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053056/http://network.nature.com/people/U2929A0EA/profile">Anna
      Kushnir</ext-link>
      (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053056/http://network.nature.com/people/U2929A0EA/blog/2008/01/07/blogging-can-help-you-get-a-job-continued">Blogging
      Can Help You Get a Job, Continued</ext-link>) and
      <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053056/http://network.nature.com/people/steelgraham/profile">Graham
      Steel</ext-link>.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053056/http://scienceblogs.com/clock/2008/02/visualize_this_interview_with.php">Visualize
      This! Interview with Moshe Pritsker</ext-link> (A Blog around the
      Clock)</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053056/http://arstechnica.com/journals/science.ars/2009/01/20/science-online-09-moving-beyond-text">Science
      Online 09: moving beyond text</ext-link> (Nobel Intent)</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053056/http://www.boston.com/news/local/massachusetts/articles/2008/08/21/out_in_the_open_some_scientists_sharing_results/?page=2">Out
      in the open: Some scientists sharing results</ext-link> (The
      Boston Globe)</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053056/http://usefulchem.blogspot.com/2008/11/from-ons-to-peer-review-our-jove.html">From
      ONS to Peer Review: our JoVE Article is Published</ext-link>
      (Useful Chemistry)</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053056/http://network.nature.com/groups/goodpaper/forum/topics/3785">JOURNAL
      CLUB: A Behavioral Assay to Measure Responsiveness of Zebrafish to
      Changes in Light Intensities</ext-link> (Good Paper Journal
      Club)</p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
