<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Interview with Victor Henning from
Mendeley</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2008-09-05">
<day>5</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2008</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<fig>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20080920001317im_/http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3120/2827515376_ac2f0d81a1_o.jpg" xlink:title="" />
</fig>
<p>In the last few months we have seen an ever increasing number of new
social networking (Web 2.0) sites for scientists. Good Web 2.0 tools for
scientists primarily try to solve a problem. But by adding a social
aspect, they will gain useful features that would otherwise not be
possible.
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20080920001317/http://network.nature.com/profile/U27CE62BB"><bold>Eva
Amsen</bold></ext-link> has recently written a great blog post about
this<sup><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20080920001317/http://network.nature.com/people/mfenner/blog/2008/09/05/interview-with-victor-henning-from-mendeley#fn1"><bold>1</bold></ext-link></sup>.
Many of these new services have overlapping functions, e.g. almost all
of them allow the user to maintain a list of contacts. This raises two
questions:</p>
<list list-type="order">
  <list-item>
    <p>Which of these sites has (or have) the features that I’m most
    interested in?</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>Do any of these sites work with the commonly used desktop tools
    and with each other, so that I don’t have to maintain duplicate
    information, e.g. the list of my publications?</p>
  </list-item>
</list>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20080920001317/http://network.nature.com/profile/U42E63119"><bold>Cameron
Neylon</bold></ext-link> in August posted an open letter to the
developers of these
sites<sup><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20080920001317/http://network.nature.com/people/mfenner/blog/2008/09/05/interview-with-victor-henning-from-mendeley#fn2"><bold>2</bold></ext-link></sup>
and also started a comprehensive
list<sup><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20080920001317/http://network.nature.com/people/mfenner/blog/2008/09/05/interview-with-victor-henning-from-mendeley#fn3"><bold>3</bold></ext-link></sup>.
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20080920001317/http://network.nature.com/profile/http-network-nature-comprofilegerrymck"><bold>Gerry
McKiernan</bold></ext-link> <bold></bold> collects information about
social networking sites for scientists on his SciTechNet
blog<sup><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20080920001317/http://network.nature.com/people/mfenner/blog/2008/09/05/interview-with-victor-henning-from-mendeley#fn4"><bold>4</bold></ext-link></sup>.
Mendeley<sup><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20080920001317/http://network.nature.com/people/mfenner/blog/2008/09/05/interview-with-victor-henning-from-mendeley#fn5"><bold>5</bold></ext-link></sup>
is one of these new Web 2.0 sites for scientists (they launched in
August), and I spoke with
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20080920001317/http://network.nature.com/profile/U4C4A58A2%5B6"><bold>Victor
Henning</bold></ext-link>, one of the founders of Mendeley, about
it.</p>
<p><bold>1. Can you describe what Mendeley is and does?</bold>
Mendeley is actually two things: Mendeley Desktop and Mendeley Web.
Mendeley Desktop is free academic software (available for Windows, Mac
and Linux) for managing &amp; sharing research papers. Mendeley Web lets
you back up your research papers online, shows you research trends in
your academic discipline, and connects you to like-minded
researchers.</p>
<p><bold>2. What is the connection to Last.fm?</bold>
There is a conceptual as well as a personal connection. Conceptually, in
the long run Mendeley aims to do for research what Last.fm did for
music. For those of your readers who don’t know Last.fm, this is how it
works: When you install Last.fm’s desktop software on your computer, it
will monitor which music you listen to and automatically build a profile
of your musical taste on the Last.fm website. The website then
recommends you music that you might like, shows you statistics about the
most popular songs and artists in your favourite genre, and lets you
discover people with a similar taste in music. By aggregating the
listening habits and tags of its 20 million users, Last.fm has managed
to create the largest ontological classification (and the largest open
database) of music in the world – it would be great if we could achieve
the same for research papers.</p>
<p>So, if you install Mendeley Desktop on your computer, you can manage
and share research papers on your machine, but you can also upload your
papers to your private account on Mendeley Web to access them online.
Mendeley Web anonymously aggregates the metadata of these papers to
generate statistics about the most popular authors and papers in your
research discipline, and – in the future – generates recommendations for
papers which you might like. One thing that we handle very differently
from Last.fm is privacy: The Last.fm website lets everyone know which
music you listen to, whereas Mendeley Web keeps all your research data
in your private account which can’t be accessed by anyone else. The
conceptual parallels between Last.fm and Mendeley are outlined in more
detail in a talk I gave both at the EuroScience Open Forum 2008 in
Barcelona and at the Southampton Open Science
Workshop<sup><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20080920001317/http://network.nature.com/people/mfenner/blog/2008/09/05/interview-with-victor-henning-from-mendeley#fn7"><bold>7</bold></ext-link></sup>.</p>
<fig>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20080920001317im_/http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3129/2822784112_f01ed9673b_o.jpg" xlink:title="" />
</fig>
<p>Besides the conceptual similarities, the personal connection to
Last.fm is Dr. Stefan Glänzer. He was Last.fm’s first investor and
executive chairman, and now has the same role at Mendeley. My co-founder
Jan and I first met him back in 2003, when he was a guest lecturer in
Entrepreneurship at our university, the WHU
Vallendar<sup><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20080920001317/http://network.nature.com/people/mfenner/blog/2008/09/05/interview-with-victor-henning-from-mendeley#fn8"><bold>8</bold></ext-link></sup>,
and we contributed a case study to the book he published together with
our professors. So when we were looking for funding, we approached him
again in June 2007, he was fascinated by the idea of Mendeley and
luckily decided to join us. He also brought us in touch with the former
founding engineers of Skype, who became investors as well.</p>
<p><bold>3. What are your responsibilities within Mendeley?</bold>
I do most of the conceptual work behind Mendeley and write the
specifications for our developers: What is the vision of Mendeley
Desktop and Mendeley Web in the long term, which features should we
develop next to get there, how does each feature work in detail, right
down to questions like “where do we place this button and how do we
label it?”. So you can blame me for all the usability problems you might
encounter.</p>
<p>I’m also responsible for staying in touch with the academic community
and incorporating its wishes into the Mendeley development roadmap,
which has the enjoyable side effect that I get to travel to all these
wonderful academic conferences. Next week, I’ll be at the Science in the
21st Century conference at the Perimeter Institute for Theoretical
Physics,
Waterloo/Ontario<sup><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20080920001317/http://network.nature.com/people/mfenner/blog/2008/09/05/interview-with-victor-henning-from-mendeley#fn9"><bold>9</bold></ext-link></sup>.</p>
<p><bold>4. What did you do before starting to work for Mendeley?</bold>
Until a little more than a year ago, I thought I’d pursue an academic
career – I’m currently finishing my Ph.D. on decision-making and choice
at the Bauhaus-University of Weimar. I’ve been saying “currently
finishing” for almost a year now, but I’m hopeful that I’ll manage to
submit my thesis by the end of this year :-) Prior to that, I’ve worked
in film production and the music industry a lot, and I opened a
café/bar<sup><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20080920001317/http://network.nature.com/people/mfenner/blog/2008/09/05/interview-with-victor-henning-from-mendeley#fn10"><bold>10</bold></ext-link></sup>
opposite the WHU in parallel to writing my master’s thesis. I actually
left Vallendar the day after the opening night to pursue my Ph.D. in
Weimar, so I had all of the work and little of the fun of owning a
café/bar!</p>
<p><bold>5. What is your policy regarding users sharing their PDF files
of publications with others?</bold>
I think it’s important to point out that we’re not a “Napster for
research papers” – i.e. no free-for-all peer-to-peer filesharing. Quite
a lot of people are disappointed when I tell them that! Sharing is
currently limited to “Shared Document Groups” of max. 10 people (e.g. a
lab, or collaborators on a research paper), although you can create and
join as many Shared Document Groups as you like. Also, as we state in
our terms of
use<sup><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20080920001317/http://network.nature.com/people/mfenner/blog/2008/09/05/interview-with-victor-henning-from-mendeley#fn11"><bold>11</bold></ext-link></sup>,
you may only share PDFs with the permission of the copyright owner –
e.g. your own articles or working papers, articles from Open Access
databases, articles under a Creative Commons/Scientific Commons license,
or perhaps when you and the person you are sharing the PDF with both
have licensed access to the database the PDF was taken from.</p>
<p>We also encourage users to post their own papers and working papers
on their Mendeley profiles – depending on whether they have permission
to do so from their publishers. As you can imagine, we’re big fans of
Open Access!</p>
<p><bold>6. How is Mendeley different from other desktop reference
managers such as Endnote?</bold>
There are a number of things that make Mendeley Desktop unique, but I’d
probably highlight the collaboration aspect, the “automatic metadata
extraction”, the online back-up/multi-machine support, and the
cross-platform support:</p>
<list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
    <p>As far as I know, Mendeley Desktop is the only desktop reference
    management software that lets you share and collaboratively annotate
    research papers. We’re also working on a “groups” feature in
    Mendeley Web which labs can use for discussions, sharing files,
    setting up a lab blog/wiki etc. – all of this will tie into the
    reference management seamlessly.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>The “automatic metadata extraction” is quite unique as well: When
    you drop your PDFs into Mendeley Desktop, it will automatically
    extract the full-text to make it searchable, try to guess the
    correct metadata from the full-text (author, title, journal, volume,
    issue etc.) so you don’t have to type it in manually, and also parse
    each documents’ cited references, so you can add them to your
    library as well.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>Due to the integration with Mendeley Web, you can back-up your
    entire library for online access through simple drag &amp; drop in
    Mendeley Desktop. Also, this means that you can install Mendeley
    Desktop on multiple computers and easily synchronize your PDF
    library across them via the Mendeley Online Library.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>Last but not least, Mendeley Desktop is the only desktop
    reference manager that is available on all three major platforms
    (Windows, Mac, and Linux).</p>
  </list-item>
</list>
<p>Not to mention that, in comparison to solutions such as EndNote,
RefMan, RefWorks etc., which cost hundreds of Euros per license,
Mendeley Desktop is completely free.</p>
<p><bold>7. How is Mendeley different from other social networking sites
for scientists?</bold>
While social networking is an aspect of Mendeley Web, we don’t see
ourselves primarily as a social network. We don’t believe that social
networking in itself is the killer feature that researchers are looking
for – rather we’re using a social network to enable researchers to share
their data. I think that
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20080920001317/http://network.nature.com/profile/neilfws"><bold>Neil
Saunders</bold></ext-link>, who is also here on Nature Network, said it
best: “Really, it’s our data that needs to be social, not ourselves”. So
we’ve tried to develop a research tool which is useful without any
network effects, and which uses networking as a means rather than an
end.</p>
<p>To invoke the analogy to Last.fm again: Even though people have
profiles on Last.fm and can connect to each other, Last.fm is not
primarily a social network. Last.fm connects the music first, and
networks of people form around the music as a second step.</p>
<p><bold>8. Does Mendeley integrate with other social networking sites
and services for scientists, e.g. Connotea or CiteULike? Does it
integrate with desktop reference managers?</bold>
At the moment we’re focusing on increasing the speed and stability of
Mendeley, as well as introducing more features which make Mendeley
useful as a standalone software. However, compatibility with Connotea or
CiteULike is something we’ll be working on in the near future.</p>
<p>Regarding integration with other desktop reference managers: At the
Science Blogging
Conference<sup><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20080920001317/http://network.nature.com/people/mfenner/blog/2008/09/05/interview-with-victor-henning-from-mendeley#fn11"><bold>11</bold></ext-link></sup>
I briefly spoke to
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20080920001317/http://network.nature.com/profile/mekentosj"><bold>Alexander
Griekspoor</bold></ext-link>, the developer of the Mac software
Papers<sup><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20080920001317/http://network.nature.com/people/mfenner/blog/2008/09/05/interview-with-victor-henning-from-mendeley#fn12"><bold>12</bold></ext-link></sup>,
whether we couldn’t make our software compatible so that Papers users
and Mendeley Desktop users could share and synchronize their collections
online. As for EndNote: It’s already possible to import/export data
to/from Mendeley in the EndNote XML format – but, sadly, I don’t think
that EndNote’s developers would be inclined to enable online sharing
between EndNote and Mendeley.</p>
<p><bold>9. Do you want to talk about future plans for Mendeley?</bold>
Sure! Besides speed and stability, which I already mentioned, we’ll be
working on two main issues to better integrate Mendeley into the
research workflow. First, there will be a “cite-while-you-write” plugin
for Microsoft Word (or Open Office, if our users would prefer that), so
that you can generate reference lists from your Mendeley library
automatically. Similarly, we’ll improve the integration with LaTeX by
automating the BibTeX file export from Mendeley Desktop. Second, we’ll
introduce a “bookmarklet” like the ones CiteULike or Connotea have,
which lets you import metadata/papers from websites into your Mendeley
Online Library with a single click. This metadata will then be
automatically synchronized with the Mendeley Desktop library on your
computer.</p>
<p>The Microsoft Word/LaTeX integration and the online bookmarklet will
be available very soon. Over the coming months, we’ll also introduce OCR
to Mendeley Desktop, so that you can extract metadata, full-text and
references from older scanned-image documents; we’ll integrate Mendeley
Desktop with external databases such as PubMed, Scopus, and Web of
Science; we’ll implement the groups/lab management feature on Mendeley
Web that I already mentioned; there will be much more detailed research
trend statistics on Mendeley Web; we’ll introduce the recommendation
engine for academic papers, and many more little goodies. For example, a
frequent user request has been automatic PDF file renaming based on the
metadata – so that’s going to be in one of the next versions.</p>
<p><bold>10. If a user is interested to learn more about Mendeley or
give feedback, who should he contact?</bold>
You can always contact me directly at
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20080920001317/mailto:victor.henning@mendeley.com"><bold>victor.henning@mendeley.com</bold></ext-link>.
There is also a Mendeley team blog on which there is plenty of
behind-the-scenes
information<sup><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20080920001317/http://network.nature.com/people/mfenner/blog/2008/09/05/interview-with-victor-henning-from-mendeley#fn13"><bold>13</bold></ext-link></sup>.
You can also submit feature requests or bug reports on our homepage (the
buttons on the top left).</p>
<p>Victor, thank you very much for giving me this interview.</p>
<fig>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20080920001317im_/http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3212/2822759480_c330822084_o.jpg" xlink:title="" />
</fig>
<p><italic>The Mendeley founders Stefan Glänzer, Victor Henning, Paul
Föckler and Jan Reichelt</italic></p>
<p><sup>1</sup>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20080920001317/http://network.nature.com/blogs/user/U27CE62BB/2008/08/19/how-to-get-scientists-to-adopt-web-2-0-technologies"><bold>How
to get scientists to adopt web 2.0 technologies</bold></ext-link></p>
<p><sup>2</sup>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20080920001317/http://blog.openwetware.org/scienceintheopen/2008/08/06/an-open-letter-to-the-developers-of-social-network-and-%E2%80%98web-20%E2%80%99-tools-for-scientists"><bold>An
open letter to the developers of social network and web 2.0 tools for
scientists</bold></ext-link></p>
<p><sup>3</sup>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20080920001317/http://docs.google.com/View?docid=dhs5x5kr_572hccgvcct"><bold>A
critical analysis Google Docs</bold></ext-link></p>
<p><sup>4</sup>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20080920001317/http://scitechnet.blogspot.com/"><bold>SciTechNet</bold></ext-link></p>
<p><sup>5</sup>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20080920001317/http://www.mendeley.com/"><bold>Mendeley</bold></ext-link></p>
<p><sup>6</sup>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20080920001317/http://www.mendeley.com/profiles/victor-henning"><bold>Victor
Henning’s profile on Mendeley</bold></ext-link></p>
<p><sup>7</sup>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20080920001317/http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UzJbrA9EY7A"><bold>A
Last.fm for Research</bold></ext-link></p>
<p><sup>8</sup>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20080920001317/http://www.whu.edu/cms/index.php?id=1959&amp;amp;L=1&amp;amp;1354"><bold>WHU
Otto Beisheim School of Management</bold></ext-link></p>
<p><sup>9</sup>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20080920001317/http://www.science21stcentury.org/"><bold>Science
in the 21st Century</bold></ext-link></p>
<p><sup>10</sup>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20080920001317/http://www.korova-bar.de/korova/"><bold>Korova
Bar</bold></ext-link></p>
<p><sup>11</sup>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20080920001317/http://www.mendeley.com/terms/"><bold>Mendeley
terms of use</bold></ext-link></p>
<p><sup>12</sup>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20080920001317/http://www.nature.com/natureconferences/sciblog2008/index.html"><bold>Science
Blogging 2008: London</bold></ext-link></p>
<p><sup>13</sup>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20080920001317/http://mekentosj.com/papers/"><bold>Papers</bold></ext-link></p>
<p><sup>14</sup>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20080920001317/http://www.mendeley.com/blog"><bold>Mendeley
blog</bold></ext-link></p>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
