<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Interview with Kevin Emamy</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2009-01-30">
<day>30</day>
<month>1</month>
<year>2009</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>One interesting session at
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150922174120/http://scienceonline09.com/">ScienceOnline09</ext-link>
was
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150922174120/http://www.scienceonline09.com/index.php/wiki/Social_networking_for_scientists/">Social
networking for scientists</ext-link>, moderated by Cameron Neylon and
Deepak Singh. We now have so many of these social networking sites, that
it becomes difficult to differentiate between them and to see how they
can interact with each other. One important category is social
bookmarking sites for scientists. I spoke with Kevin Emamy from
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150922174120/http://www.citeulike.org/">CiteULike</ext-link>
to find out more.</p>
<p><italic><italic>Most of the CiteULike team. Kevin is the second
person from the right.</italic></italic></p>
<sec id="1-can-you-describe-what-citeulike-is-and-does">
  <title>1. Can you describe what CiteULike is and does?</title>
  <p>CiteULike is social bookmarking for research papers. It enables you
  to easily store references online, share them in groups and discover
  new ones.</p>
  <p>It's run as a web service, so everything is always stored online.
  You can access it from any computer (most of us use more than one
  these days) and if you're lazy and stupid like me you're much less
  likely to lose anything. Sharing and discovery obviously work better
  this way too.</p>
  <p>The social side of it is simply that by default everyones posts are
  public and you can see who has bookmarked the same papers as you, what
  tags they are giving them and from there you can go on to browse what
  else they are bookmarking.</p>
  <p>And then we have groups which are shared libraries of posts,
  newsfeeds for every user action, RSS feeds, watchlists,
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150922174120/http://www.citeulike.org/citegeist">CiteGeist</ext-link>
  (which is a hotlist of posts) and obviously search as ways to
  encourage this social discovery.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="2-do-your-users-basically-just-store-their-own-bookmarks-or-do-you-also-see-a-lot-of-use-of-the-social-networking-features">
  <title>2. Do your users basically just store their own bookmarks or do
  you also see a lot of use of the social networking features?</title>
  <p>In the 30 days up to the Christmas Holidays 08, CiteULike received
  116,477 posts and 6,189 of those were copies made directly from other
  user's librarys, which is the successful end result of the social
  stuff. That doesn't count people who find an article, go to the
  original source to read it, and then post it.</p>
  <p>The other social stuff is hard to quantify without diving into the
  weblogs. Also, once you get into the realms of counting pageviews and
  linkouts etc. it becomes easy to mislead yourself about what is really
  going on, which is why we use “posts” as a genuine metric (assuming
  you are on top of the spam).</p>
  <p>But the social discovery stuff is certainly used. Groups for
  example; well over 50% are active, by which I mean people have posted
  to them in the last 90 days. Watchlists (following another user's
  posts) and RSS are very active. Many people search the site, either
  directly or through RSS feeds.</p>
  <p>One thing that is definitely true is that many more people browse
  the site than actually register and post, by a factor of say 5:1, and
  I'm discounting the random Google traffic that just bounces on and
  off.</p>
  <p>Of course, the service would never have got off the ground if it
  didn't provide individual value to a user without any social features,
  so yes, many people use it just like that and always will.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="3-how-is-citeulike-different-from-other-social-bookmarking-tools-e-g-connotea-2collab-or-delicious">
  <title>3. How is CiteULike different from other social bookmarking
  tools, e.g. Connotea, 2collab or delicious?</title>
  <p>It differs from
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150922174120/http://delicious.com/">delicious</ext-link>
  because we extract and bookmark citation metadata along with the URL,
  so it's aimed at professional researchers and scientists. We have over
  50 sites where we do this, covering most of the online sources of
  journal papers. Because of this specialization our userbase is very
  different and therefore much more relevant when you look at the
  community features. The tags, as one example, are very
  specialized.</p>
  <p>There are lots of differences in detail with the other two
  'scholarly' services but it seems that the users have voted with their
  feet (or should I say mice); CiteULike is far and away the most
  popular service. If you count the number of papers posted we estimate
  that CiteULike is currently 3-5 times the size of
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150922174120/http://www.connotea.org/">Connotea</ext-link>
  both in total posts and posts on a daily basis (2 million+ posts and
  very little spam for CiteULike vs. 650k posts including a significant
  proportion of spam for connotea, 3k-5k daily posts for CiteULike vs.
  1k to 1.5k claimed for Connotea).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="4-does-citeulike-integrate-with-other-social-networking-sites-and-services-for-scientists-e-g-connotea-mendeley-or-friendfeed-does-it-integrate-with-desktop-reference-managers">
  <title>4. Does CiteULike integrate with other social networking sites
  and services for scientists, e.g. Connotea, Mendeley or FriendFeed?
  Does it integrate with desktop reference managers?</title>
  <p>You can export and import files to and from pretty much all these
  services.</p>
  <p>In the case of
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150922174120/http://friendfeed.com/">FriendFeed</ext-link>
  I have seen many people using RSS feeds to display their CiteULike
  posts there, which is great, it's a really good service.</p>
  <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150922174120/http://www.mendeley.com/">Mendeley</ext-link>
  are based in London like us and we have begun to discuss ways where we
  can integrate more tightly, the point being to make the workflow
  better for users of both services.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="5-what-is-your-policy-regarding-personal-pdf-files-uploaded-to-citeulike">
  <title>5. What is your policy regarding personal PDF files uploaded to
  CiteULike?</title>
  <p>Only the person who uploaded a PDF can download it, so CiteULike is
  acting as an online storage drive.</p>
  <p>We have also allowed uploads to “private groups” which are invite
  only and otherwise invisible. In this case the user will commit that
  they have a right to distribute the document to the people in the
  group,
  who they already know.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="6-what-are-your-responsibilities-within-citeulike">
  <title>6. What are your responsibilities within CiteULike?</title>
  <p>There are only five of us, so we don't really have roles. Unlike
  the rest of the team, I can't write code or design applications, so I
  have to leave that to my esteemed colleagues.</p>
  <p>One of the things I try and do is to promote CiteULike and increase
  our userbase and traffic, which is a bit of a capricious art, but one
  way that has worked for us is to try to engage with, dare I say it,
  the publishers.</p>
  <p>Springer, who we
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150922174120/http://www.springer.com/company/citeulike?SGWID=0-164102-0-0-0">recently
  agreed a sponsorship with</ext-link>, have been invaluable to us in
  this regard. They are one of the few major publishers who are really
  progressive and actually understand this stuff.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="7-what-did-you-do-before-starting-to-work-for-citeulike">
  <title>7. What did you do before starting to work for
  CiteULike?</title>
  <p>We all worked in the software industry, sometimes together. Richard
  wrote CiteULike as a tool for his own use when he was back doing
  research at university.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="8-do-you-want-to-talk-about-future-plans-for-citeulike">
  <title>8. Do you want to talk about future plans for
  CiteULike?</title>
  <p>Well the team are continuously improving the service, making it
  perform better, fixing things that break etc. I wish I could count the
  number of improvements that have been made over the last 18 months.
  That is part of the secret to it's growth, the users can tell when the
  developers are making an effort. We have a very active newsgroup where
  users make feature and functionality requests or report problems. I
  have regularly seen my colleagues put stuff live in a matter of hours
  following a user request, which is one of the advantages of a service
  that is run by it's developers.</p>
  <p>We have wanted to do some kind of recommendation system for a long
  time; automated collaborative filtering or whatever. We certainly have
  the data to do it. But it is, I'm told, a hard problem if you want to
  get useful results. It's possible we'll work with someone else on
  this.</p>
  <p>It was really interesting to see
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150922174120/http://www.plos.org/">PLoS</ext-link>
  announcing the variety of impact metrics they want to publish about
  their articles, a small part of which is going to be social
  bookmarking posts. We are currently giving them this data on request,
  it would be nice to allow anyone to get this sort of data out of
  CiteULike themselves (we do already make the whole CiteULike dataset
  freely available for download).</p>
  <p>Another example of that is that a lot of other sites want to
  display CiteULike tag data along with the relevant articles; there are
  6.7 million user created tags on CiteULike now (that's total not
  distinct)
  and those tags have been given by people who know the subjects. I
  suppose I am talking about some kind of API, which would also allow
  reference managers etc. to integrate with CiteULike more easily, as
  you asked about above.</p>
  <p>Having said that, there is a great temptation to continually add
  more features or try to make it into something different to what it
  really is and I'm not sure if that is the right approach (though we
  have been guilty of it).</p>
  <p>For example, one of the biggest issues we have is that CiteULike is
  good at matching articles that have been posted by hand but not
  articles imported by file upload. By “match” I mean identify that two
  articles from different sources are in fact the same, which is the
  basis of the social stuff; seeing who is reading what you're reading
  etc. Seeing as 40% or so of our posts come via file upload, it would
  be great to fix. Matching is done by DOI and PMID; however we ran some
  tests that showed only 5% of file uploaded articles contain these, so
  maybe we'll try a different approach.</p>
  <p>So what we try to focus on is to make it better and more efficient
  at what it does well: social bookmarking for research papers. There is
  plenty of work to do in that regard.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
