<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Interview with Alexander Griekspoor</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2008-10-03">
<day>3</day>
<month>10</month>
<year>2008</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Good software solves a problem. When one journal after another
switched to PDF as electronic document format, and journals started to
appear only in electronic form, storing papers as printouts in folders
became impractical. But the PDF files will soon start to clutter the
hard drive, despite efforts to organize them by topic, year or author.
At least for Macintosh users,
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053037/http://mekentosj.com/papers/">Papers</ext-link>
is one practical and elegant solution to this problem. I talked with
Papers author
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053037/http://network.nature.com/people/mekentosj/profile">Alexander
Griekspoor</ext-link> not only about Papers, but also about his career
switch from cell biologist to software developer.</p>
<sec id="1-can-you-describe-what-papers-is-and-does">
  <title>1. Can you describe what Papers is and does?</title>
  <p>The tag-line we coined for Papers is “your personal library of
  science”, a play-of-words on the well-known PLoS acronym. And this
  program for the Mac provides exactly that, it helps you manage and
  organize your personal scientific literature library. It provides a
  complete workflow for finding new articles using built-in search
  engines, browsing the publisher’s website using the built-in Safari
  web browser, downloading, archiving and renaming the PDF files, and
  organizing and indexing these articles. Finally, it allows you to
  easily read the papers and share them with colleagues.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="2-how-is-papers-different-from-other-macintosh-bibliography-tools">
  <title>2. How is Papers different from other Macintosh bibliography
  tools?</title>
  <p>Papers distinguishes itself from other bibliography tools in that
  it is not a typical reference manager to begin with. The Mac has had
  several good reference management applications for a long time
  already, but when I created Papers I wanted to make a different
  application, one that didn’t exist yet and one there was clearly a
  need for, one to manage all those PDF files that people were
  downloading. In the years before, the publishing industry had
  introduced PDFs as a replacement for sending articles by regular mail
  and it was a great success in that it made access to the literature
  much easier.</p>
  <p>Still, their support of the researcher ended the moment you pressed
  the download button. Your web browser would save some cryptically
  named PDF file on your hard disk, which soon quickly filled up with
  dozens of these files. So whereas PDFs were introduced to save us from
  the messy file cabinets with hundreds of paper copies of your
  articles, we were now facing the digital equivalent of that on our
  desktop.</p>
  <p>That was when it struck me that Apple had already solved this issue
  for MP3 files a few years earlier, iTunes had allowed us to stop
  bothering about managing MP3s and instead allowed us to focus on the
  songs. Papers was designed to do exactly the same when it comes to
  managing PDFs and instead lets us focus on the articles. Obviously,
  now the have seen how things can be different you notice that most
  reference managers on the Mac have started to play catch up, and are
  introducing PDF management features as well. Still, for us this has
  always been the key element and is just the start of many exciting
  things to come.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="3-what-recommendations-do-you-give-windows-and-linux-users">
  <title>3. What recommendations do you give Windows and Linux
  users?</title>
  <p>The most obvious answer is to buy a Mac of course 😉 But more
  seriously, at the moment I’m not aware of a program on Windows or
  Linux that offers the same feature set and user experience that Papers
  offers. But like the other reference management tools on the Mac
  there’s a similar trend of adopting
  these kind of features in bibliography tools on Linux and Windows as
  well.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="4-what-did-you-do-before-working-on-papers">
  <title>4. What did you do before working on Papers?</title>
  <p>Perhaps surprisingly I’m a cell biologist of training and not a
  computer scientists or IT person. I studied medical biology at the
  Free University in Amsterdam and ended up doing my PhD at the
  Netherlands Cancer Institute in Amsterdam as well, where I studied the
  immune system using
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053037/http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.mib.2005.04.007">live-cell
  fluorescence microscopy</ext-link>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="5-how-did-you-get-involved-in-writing-macintosh-software">
  <title>5. How did you get involved in writing Macintosh
  software?</title>
  <p>It all started out as a hobby driven by a long-time interest for
  both design and technology. I was introduced to the Mac when my dad
  brought home one of these “portable” classic Macs when I was about 14
  years old, and almost immediately I started experimenting with
  Photoshop et al. During university I earned some money in my spare
  time by designing and building websites, but it wasn’t until about the
  time I started by PhD that Apple introduced Mac OS X and with it came
  the free set of developer tools that finally made it easy enough for
  someone without the classical IT background to start building his/her
  own Mac applications. Together with my best friend and fellow PhD
  student Tom Groothuis we started building a number of tools for
  molecular biologists
  (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053037/http://mekentosj.com/enzymex/">EnzymeX</ext-link>),
  which we distributed for free under our “mek en tosj” monicker. It
  didn’t take long before the hobby started to get out of hand as the
  popularity of our programs started to soar.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="6-you-talked-about-your-postdoc-choice-in-a-2007-nature-jobs-article-what-made-you-decide-to-move-from-postdoc-to-company-founder">
  <title>6. You talked about your postdoc choice in a 2007
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053037/http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nj7130-948b">Nature
  Jobs article</ext-link>. What made you decide to move from postdoc to
  company founder?</title>
  <p>When the time came to pick a postdoc I knew one thing for sure, the
  programming was something I was so passionate about that it should be
  part of the postdoc rather than a spare time project. That’s why I
  picked the text mining group at the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053037/http://www.ebi.ac.uk/">European
  Bioinformatics Institute</ext-link> in Cambridge UK, also driven by an
  interest in the changes that were/are ongoing in the scientific
  publishing industry. I applied for a two year EU Marie Curie
  fellowship which I was fortunate to get, however it would take a few
  months between the end of my PhD and all the bureaucracy before I
  could get started in Cambridge. This was when I decided to build
  Papers. I got the idea for this “iTunes for PDF files” already two
  years earlier, but never had the time to do it. I did tell everybody I
  knew about it, but no one had done it and now finally I had some spare
  time on my hands.</p>
  <p>The first beta of the program was released right at the time I
  started my postdoc and it was a success right from the start. In fact
  it was so successful and offered so many opportunities that it was
  soon difficult to focus on my actual postdoc and after a year I
  realized that this was the thing I was really passionate about and was
  what I wanted to concentrate fully on. That was when I decided to quit
  my job and become the company founder of Mekentosj Inc. 😉</p>
</sec>
<sec id="7-do-you-want-to-talk-about-future-plans-for-papers">
  <title>7. Do you want to talk about future plans for Papers?</title>
  <p>It’s still to early to talk in many details but like I said, for us
  the current version of Papers has always been the foundation on which
  we can build many exciting things we envision. We’re working hard on
  the next major release of Papers which will definitely be a big step
  up. And obviously the introduction of the iPhone is something that
  also brings very exciting possibilities, so many things to look
  forward to!</p>
  <p><italic><italic>Alex, thanks a lot for this interview. For more
  information, you can read an
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053037/http://www.macresearch.org/interview_with_alexander_griekspoor_from_mekentosj">interview</ext-link>
  from two years ago, or visit the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053037/http://network.nature.com/groups/papers/forum/topics">Mekentosj
  Papers Nature Network Forum</ext-link>. And please tell me how you
  manage all these PDF files and how you use these references when
  writing a paper yourself.</italic></italic></p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
