<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Interview with Pablo Fernicola</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2008-11-07">
<day>7</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2008</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>The Article Authoring Tag Set of the National Library of Medicine
(NLM DTD for short) <italic><italic>creates a standardized format for
new journal articles that can be used by authors to submit publications
to journals and to archives such as PubMed Central.</italic></italic>[1]
The Microsoft Word Article Authoring Add-in that was released earlier
this year reads and writes this format.
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053041/http://network.nature.com/people/pablofe/profile">Pablo
Fernicola</ext-link> from Microsoft first explains the Add-in in a video
and then answers a few questions.</p>
<sec id="1-can-you-describe-what-the-microsoft-word-article-authoring-add-in-is-and-does">
  <title>1. Can you describe what the Microsoft Word Article Authoring
  Add-in is and does?</title>
  <p>There is an already ongoing transition to digital workflows for
  journals, as well as a nascent transition to digital distribution and
  consumption. Generating content that is best suited for digital
  distribution, as well as for archival, search, and semantic analysis
  in the future, is going to be essential. As a community, today we are
  not taking full advantage of the potential that the tools and formats
  currently in use present to us, and trying to bolt these capabilities
  to existing print centric processes is costly, inefficient, and does
  not allow for exercising the benefits afforded by the digital medium.
  Authoring for print delivery still dominates many of the processes,
  and constrains the final outcome, even if print distribution is
  discontinued.</p>
  <p>It is important to realize that the content we generate today is
  what we will be accessing, and relying on as reference material, in
  the future. It is imperative that we generate content that is best
  suited for the way it will be consumed. Also, it would be ideal if
  this transition could be done in a non intrusive and low cost approach
  as possible.</p>
  <p>The Article Authoring Add-in for Word
  2007<sup><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053041/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2008/11/07/interview_with_pablo_fernicola/#fn2">2</ext-link></sup>
  is a free download, which provides new capabilities to the Word
  application, focused on Scholarly Publishing. The overall goal for the
  Authoring Add-in project is to help improve the scholarly publishing
  process for workflows that rely on Microsoft Word or Word generated
  content, covering the authoring experience, editorial workflow, and
  archiving of STM articles, with an eye towards generating content that
  is best suited for preservation, digital consumption, and search. A
  core capability provided by the add-in is the ability to open and save
  files in the NLM XML format.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="2-how-is-the-authoring-add-in-different-from-commercial-tools-such-asextyles-from-inera">
  <title>2. How is the Authoring Add-in different from commercial tools
  such as
  eXtyles from Inera?</title>
  <p>The add-in differs in at least the following ways:</p>
  <list list-type="bullet">
    <list-item>
      <p>It is targeted at both authors and editorial staff
      audiences</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>It focuses on enhancing the experience within Word, both for
      authors and editorial staff, and not just for content but also for
      metadata</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Enables providing a consistent experience for authors, in
      relation to templates and the entering of metadata, across
      journals</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Enables two way interaction with the NLM formats (article and
      book formats), saving and opening NLM files within Word</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Provides a platform for software vendors to build on top of</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Builds on the transition to XML as the underlying native format
      in Word 2007</p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
</sec>
<sec id="3-what-advantages-do-you-see-for-authors-that-submit-their-manuscripts-in-the-nlm-journal-publishing-xml-format">
  <title>3. What advantages do you see for authors that submit their
  manuscripts in the NLM Journal Publishing XML format?</title>
  <p>The add-in doesn't force authors to submit their articles in the
  NLM format, but makes the conversion to that format a lot easier as
  part of the workflow. The add-in provides a way for authors to enter
  information in their articles so that this content (semantics and
  metadata) is preserved through the publishing workflow, in a way that
  is ready to save as a valid NLM document, while still using the Word
  user interface. I would expect that the more common scenario will be
  that of journals providing templates and authors submitting docx
  files, augmented with NLM data through the add-in, and that the
  journals or repository staff will be the ones doing the conversion to
  the NLM format.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="4-how-do-you-think-the-author-submission-process-will-change-in-relation-to-formats">
  <title>4. How do you think the author submission process will change
  in relation to formats?</title>
  <p>Many journals already use the NLM format as part of their
  publishing workflow, as well as for their archival format. Some
  publishers are moving to the format now. And, certainly for NIH funded
  research, all articles eventually end up in the NLM format as part of
  the submission to PubMed Central. But I don't know of any journals
  that take in the NLM format directly from authors.</p>
  <p>We have tried to take a very end user centric approach in the
  project. We would like for authors not to have to be aware of the
  underlying format. We don't want authors to think of XML, for example,
  as formats should be something that happens in the background, which
  the authoring tools handle for the authors, and just make the authors'
  work easier, and their content more easily searchable and
  relevant.</p>
  <p>In our work with the journals, publishers, and repositories we
  focus a lot on interoperability based on formats and protocols
  commonly used in the community, not only in the form of the NLM format
  itself, but also by incorporating technologies such as
  SWORD<sup><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053041/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2008/11/07/interview_with_pablo_fernicola/#fn4">4</ext-link></sup>
  and
  OAI-ORE<sup><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053041/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2008/11/07/interview_with_pablo_fernicola/#fn5">5</ext-link></sup>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="5-what-is-your-job-at-microsoft-what-did-you-do-before-working-on-the-authoring-add-in">
  <title>5. What is your job at Microsoft? What did you do before
  working on the Authoring Add-in?</title>
  <p>I have always been involved in software development, working and
  managing both small and large teams. Currently I am a group manager at
  Microsoft, in charge of running this overall project, which also
  includes an online service focused on the peer review process. I drive
  the development, the technology direction and architecture, and
  community engagement as it relates to scholarly
  publishing<sup><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053041/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2008/11/07/interview_with_pablo_fernicola/#fn6">6</ext-link></sup>.
  Before starting this effort, I worked for many years on developer
  platform technologies related to text, reading, graphics, and
  multimedia, both at Microsoft and at Apple, as well as being the
  Program Manager in charge of the web developer platform in Internet
  Explorer for a couple of versions of the browser.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="6-do-you-plan-to-also-release-an-add-in-for-microsoft-word-2008-for-macintosh">
  <title>6. Do you plan to also release an Add-in for Microsoft Word
  2008 for Macintosh?</title>
  <p>We are investigating how we can best bring the authoring focused
  features to Word 2008 users. On Windows, Word 2007 is now in many ways
  a developer platform in its own right, there are even software
  development kits for it, and Word 2007 provides a lot of extensibility
  and programmability to developers. The equivalent developer support is
  not provided in Word 2008, with the Macintosh offering's strength
  being on providing a great end user experience to its end user
  audience.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="7-do-you-want-to-talk-about-future-plans-for-the-authoring-add-in">
  <title>7. Do you want to talk about future plans for the Authoring
  Add-in?</title>
  <p>We got a lot of feedback on our version 1 of the add-in, which we
  made available this past July, from folks involved in the back-end of
  the publishing workflow, such as folks at journals, publishers, and
  repositories, as well as from companies that provide the software
  tools and services in support of this work (of note is the integration
  work we did with Design Science for their MathType
  package<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053041/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2008/11/07/interview_with_pablo_fernicola/#fn7">7</ext-link>).</p>
  <p>Development work on version 2 is currently underway and we expect
  to make available a Technology Preview soon, with the final release of
  version 2 in 2009. In version 1 we focused quite a bit on the
  architecture and getting the basic infrastructure in place to provide
  support for the NLM format. In version 2 there is a greater focus on
  the author experience, as well as on continuing to improve the support
  for the format.</p>
  <p>Some of the driving questions that we would like to address
  are:</p>
  <list list-type="bullet">
    <list-item>
      <p>in which ways can we make the submission/upload process easier
      for authors</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Can we make the author and article metadata more reliable and
      consistent, thereby reducing the roundtrips between authors and
      the journals, as well as reducing the cost for cleaning up the
      data?</p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
  <p>And overall, the philosophy is to simplify, simplify, simplify.
  Especially for authors, help them get the content into the article,
  and keep the technology in the background. For the staff at journals
  and repositories, provide them with access to all the richness of the
  NLM format, and the flexibility that they will need to build their own
  solutions.</p>
  <p>fn1.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053041/http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/articleauthoring/">Article
  Authoring Tag Set</ext-link></p>
  <p>fn2.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053041/http://www.microsoft.com/downloads/details.aspx?familyid=09c55527-0759-4d6d-ae02-51e90131997e&amp;displaylang=en">Article
  Authoring Add-in for Microsoft Office Word 2007</ext-link></p>
  <p>fn3.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053041/http://www.inera.com/extylesinfo.shtml">eXtyles
  Product Information</ext-link></p>
  <p>fn4.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053041/http://www.jisc.ac.uk/whatwedo/programmes/reppres/tools/sword">SWORD</ext-link></p>
  <p>fn5.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053041/http://www.openarchives.org/ore/">Open
  Archives Initiative Object Reuse and Exchange</ext-link></p>
  <p>fn6.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053041/http://blogs.msdn.com/exscientia/">ex
  Scientia</ext-link></p>
  <p>fn7.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053041/http://www.dessci.com/en/products/mathtype/">MathType</ext-link></p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
