<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Interview with Geoffrey Bilder</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2009-02-17">
<day>17</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2009</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Almost exactly two years ago,
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090221213233/http://www.crossref.org/"><bold>CrossRef</bold></ext-link>
invited a number of people to discuss unique identifiers for researchers
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090221213233/http://www.crossref.org/CrossTech/2007/02/crossref_author_id_meeting.html"><bold>CrossRef
Author ID meeting</bold></ext-link>). One year ago Thomson Reuters
launched <bold>ResearcherID</bold>
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090221213233/http://network.nature.com/people/mfenner/blog/2008/01/21/thomson-scientific-launches-researcherid-to-uniquely-identify-authors"><bold>Thomson
Scientific launches ResearcherID to uniquely identify
authors</bold></ext-link>). And two months ago Phil Bourne and Lynn Fink
wrote about this topic in a  <bold>PLoS Computational Biology</bold>
paper
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090221213233/http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000247"><bold>I
Am Not a Scientist, I Am a Number</bold></ext-link>).</p>
<p>So it comes as no surprise that we also talked about author
identifiers at the recent
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090221213233/http://www.scienceonline09.com/index.php/wiki/"><bold>ScienceOnline09</bold></ext-link>
meeting in North Carolina (both in the session
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090221213233/http://www.scienceonline09.com/index.php/wiki/Reputation_authority_and_incentives/"><bold>Impact
Factors and researcher incentives</bold></ext-link> and over drinks
afterwards).
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090221213233/http://network.nature.com/people/U42E63119/profile"><bold>Cameron
Neylon</bold></ext-link> wrote down his thoughts after the meeting in a
blog post
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090221213233/http://blog.openwetware.org/scienceintheopen/2009/01/20/a-specialist-openid-service-to-provide-unique-researcher-ids/"><bold>A
specialist OpenID service to provide unique researcher
IDs?</bold></ext-link>), and this resulted in
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090221213233/http://friendfeed.com/e/c1fd00ec-15f9-d894-4ea9-4ffeaac5ae28/A-specialist-OpenID-service-to-provide-unique"><bold>a
very interesting</bold></ext-link> discussion on
<bold>FriendFeed</bold>. And at about the same time both
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090221213233/http://network.nature.com/people/jandot/profile"><bold>Jan
Aerts</bold></ext-link>
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090221213233/http://saaientist.blogspot.com/2009/01/who-o-o-are-you-who-who-who-who.html"><bold>Who-o-o
are you? Who who? Who who?</bold></ext-link>) and Christopher Leonard
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090221213233/http://blogs.openaccesscentral.com/blogs/pmcblog/entry/some_thoughts_on_unique_author"><bold>Some
thoughts on unique author IDs</bold></ext-link>) independently wrote
blog posts about the same topic. This week
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090221213233/http://network.nature.com/people/U42E63119/profile"><bold>Cameron
Neylon</bold></ext-link> summarized the discussion in another blog post
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090221213233/http://blog.openwetware.org/scienceintheopen/2009/02/15/contributor-ids-an-attempt-to-aggregate-and-integrate/"><bold>Contributor
IDs – an attempt to aggregate and integrate</bold></ext-link>).</p>
<p>Science bloggers have put a lot of thought into the idea of a unique
author identifier and I’ve collected more reading material about author
ID at <bold>Connotea</bold> using the tag
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090221213233/http://www.connotea.org/tag/authorid"><bold>authorid</bold></ext-link>.
But I was also very curious to learn more about the work that has
already been done. That’s why I asked
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090221213233/http://network.nature.com/people/gbilder/profile"><bold>Geoffrey
Bilder</bold></ext-link> from <bold>CrossRef</bold> a few questions. In
the end Geoffrey talked not only about author identifiers, but also
about CrossRef, DOIs and many other aspects of scholarly publishing.</p>
<sec id="1-can-you-describe-what-crossref-is-and-does">
  <title>1. Can you describe what CrossRef is and does?</title>
  <p>Let me start with what it does because this is a little less likely
  to make your eyes glaze-over.</p>
  <p>CrossRef was originally founded by scholarly publishers to fight
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090221213233/http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Link_rot"><bold>link-rot</bold></ext-link>.</p>
  <p>Web links have a half-life of about six years. That is, after six
  years a link is likely to break because the content that it pointed to
  has been moved. To a lay-audience this might be a mere annoyance, but
  to scholarly and professional publishers broken links are anathema.
  The scholarly record is built on a foundation of links in the form of
  citations. If these online citation links break, the online scholarly
  citation record breaks.
  But surely fighting link-rot should be simple, right? After all, the
  glory of the web is its decentralized architecture, one in which the
  domain name that you own can be used as a namespace for identifiers.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090221213233/http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tim_Berners-Lee"><bold>Tim
  Berners-Lee</bold></ext-link> has said that “cool URIs never die”.
  Aren’t “persistent URIs” merely a matter of being disciplined in the
  way that you mint URIs and in being conscientious about sensibly
  redirecting URIs when things change location on your web server?</p>
  <p>Well, certainly the majority of broken links on the web are the
  result of careless web administrators not taking the time to structure
  and redirect their web site’s URIs properly, but there are a
  significant percentage of links that will break despite the best
  efforts of webmasters. This is because in some cases the domain name
  in the link will change, and in these cases the whole “domain name as
  URI minting name-space” starts to crumble. When otherwise sensible
  technorati refer to “owning” a domain name, it makes me want to stick
  forks in my eyeballs. We do not “own” domain names. At best, we only
  lease them and there are manifold ways in which we could lose control
  of a domain name – through litigation, through forgetfulness, through
  poverty, through voluntary transfer, etc. Once you don’t control a
  domain name anymore, then you can’t control your domain-name-based
  persistent identifiers either.</p>
  <p>Incidentally, another technorati meme that makes me want to
  self-harm with cutlery is the notion that “persistent identifiers
  don’t matter in the age of the search engine. If a link breaks, we can
  just find the content again wherever it has moved.” This, naturally,
  is the self-serving argument often used by Google and it’s starry-eyed
  acolytes. Even just few minutes’ reflection reveals the gaping hole in
  this approach.</p>
  <p>The hole is this – how do you cite a specific copy of something if
  there are multiple <bold>almost identical</bold> copies of it located
  in different places? For instance, lets say there are 2 copies (X and
  Y) of an article which only differ in a few paragraphs, but those few
  paragraphs are crucial and likely to change the reader’s
  interpretation of the work. How, in a world where persistent linking
  is maintained by search engines, do you create a citation link to
  article X instead of article Y? To create a search-based link that is
  more likely to resolve to article X, you would essentially have to
  encode the entire article in the search URI! Even this wouldn’t
  guarantee you that the link directed a future reader to article X
  first; it is still possible that article Y might end up getting a
  higher ranking because more people have linked to it and it therefore
  has a higher page-rank (or equivalent). Believe me, even variations of
  the search engine scenario (using document hashes for citations,
  pingbacks, etc.) quickly unravel after a little reflection.</p>
  <p>This is all a long-winded and ranty way of saying that the issue of
  persistent identifiers on the web is just a wee bit more complex than
  most people think. So how does CrossRef address the persistent
  identifier issue?</p>
  <p>From our perspective, the persistent identifier problem is much
  more a social problem than a technical one.</p>
  <p>In fact, the technical part of our service is relatively
  straightforward. CrossRef provides a level of indirection (i.e. a
  pointer) between an identifier and a URL. When publishers put
  something online, they assign a CrossRef
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090221213233/http://www.doi.org/"><bold>Digital
  Object Identifier</bold></ext-link> (DOI) to it and submit a record
  for that item with CrossRef. The record includes the CrossRef DOI,
  basic bibliographic metadata for the content and a URL that points to
  the current location of the content. People citing the publisher’s
  content are encouraged to use the CrossRef DOI for the citation
  instead of the publisher’s URL. When a researcher clicks on a CrossRef
  DOI, the CrossRef service redirects the URL to whatever URL the
  publisher has currently registered for that CrossRef DOI. This means
  that the publisher can update their CrossRef DOI record to point to a
  completely new URI (including a new domain name) and any CrossRef DOI
  citations will continue to work. We provide a few other services based
  on this infrastructure too. So, for instance, we can resolve an
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090221213233/http://www.oclc.org/research/projects/openurl/default.htm"><bold>OpenURL</bold></ext-link>
  to a CrossRef DOI (by querying the publisher-submitted bibliographic
  metadata), resolve a free-text query to a CrossRef DOI and we can also
  return bibliographic metadata instead of redirecting if that is what
  the user wants.</p>
  <p>So-far, so good, but this isn’t anything that couldn’t be
  accomplished using other redirection tools such as
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090221213233/http://www.purl.org/"><bold>PURLs</bold></ext-link>,
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090221213233/http://www.handle.net/"><bold>CNRI
  Handles</bold></ext-link>,
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090221213233/http://www.oasis-open.org/committees/tc_home.php?wg_abbrev=xri"><bold>XRIs</bold></ext-link>,
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090221213233/http://numly.com/numly/default.asp"><bold>NUmly
  Numbers</bold></ext-link>, etc.? The crucial question to ask of any
  such service is, “what guarantees that the publisher will actually
  update their URL pointers?” If the publisher doesn’t update these
  pointers, then the links will break anyway. It isn’t enough that a
  publisher decides to use PURLs, if they then don’t update their PURLs-
  in perpetuity.</p>
  <p>This is where it is important to explain the organizational
  structure and the social effect that this has on the service.</p>
  <p>CrossRef was founded as a non-profit, membership organization for
  publishers. Note that we are entirely catholic in our definition of
  what a publisher is, so our membership includes commercial publishers,
  non-profit publishers, open access publishers, institutional
  repositories, NGOs and IGOs, Video publishers, Wiki-based publishers,
  etc. We are also open to publishers of all disciplines (humanities,
  social sciences, sciences, professional), geographies and content
  types (journals, books, database records, videos, etc.)</p>
  <p>In practice, what unites our membership is a concern that their
  content should be considered worthy of trust by professional
  researchers. One way in which researchers assess the trustworthiness
  of content is by determining how it sits within the scholarly record.
  Does it provide evidence for its assertions in citations? Do other
  people cite it?</p>
  <p>When a publisher joins CrossRef, they agree to a
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090221213233/http://www.crossref.org/02publishers/59pub_rules.html"><bold>set
  of enforceable terms and conditions</bold></ext-link> that govern the
  way in which they use CrossRef’s persistent citation infrastructure.
  Specifically, they agree to:</p>
  <list list-type="bullet">
    <list-item>
      <p>Register DOIs within a week of something being published
      online</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Update the URLs associated with a DOI when said URLs change</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Link citations in their content via the DOI</p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
  <p>In joining CrossRef they also agree that CrossRef can fine them or
  throw them out of the service if they do not meet the terms and
  conditions of the service. Note that the penalty of being thrown out
  can be quite severe as it effectively means that the publisher would
  become invisible in the online scholarly citation record. In short,
  the system has a built-in social feedback loop that strongly enforces
  good citizenship.</p>
  <p>As I said, the technical infrastructure of CrossRef is pretty
  mundane, and it is the social aspect of the service that does the most
  to guarantee the persistency of CrossRef citation links.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="2-what-are-your-responsibilities-within-crossref">
  <title>2. What are your responsibilities within CrossRef?</title>
  <p>Thinking of, gathering the requirements for, designing and (most
  importantly) launching new services.</p>
  <p>Last year we launched a plagiarism detection service called
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090221213233/http://www.crossref.org/crosscheck.html"><bold>CrossCheck</bold></ext-link>.
  This year I am working on Contributor ID, another project tentatively
  named CrossMark and a bunch of smaller projects designed to encourage
  the use of DOIs in citations.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="3-what-did-you-do-before-starting-to-work-for-crossref">
  <title>3. What did you do before starting to work for
  CrossRef?</title>
  <p>In the early nineties Allen Renear and I co-founded Brown
  University’s Scholarly Technology Group, where we were charged with
  providing advanced consulting and support to Brown’s research
  community. In the mid-nineties I grew tired of the politics, resource
  constraints and institutional paralysis that seems to grip so many
  universities and I decided to do something as far away from the
  academic sphere as possible. In short, I worked at a management
  consultancy doing R&amp;D for their IT group. In 2000 I was lured into
  managing the web development efforts for an Information Architecture
  firm called Dynamic Diagrams. In 2001 we were bought by
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090221213233/http://www.ingentaconnect.com/"><bold>Ingenta</bold></ext-link>
  in the UK. I became Ingenta’s CTO and I moved to Oxford in 2002. I
  left Ingenta in 2005, did a brief spell of consulting for publishers
  in 2006 and joined CrossRef in 2007.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="4-what-are-your-thoughts-on-how-an-author-identifier-should-look-like">
  <title>4. What are your thoughts on how an author identifier should
  look like?</title>
  <p>First of all, I think we need to stop talking about “author”
  identifiers. One of the first requirements we found when interviewing
  publishers, researchers and librarians is that we would ideally like
  to be able to identify any party who contributes to the scholarly
  literature in any way. That is, we would also like to be able to
  identify reviewers, editors, correspondents, bloggers, commenters,
  etc. This is why we have taken to calling our project the “CrossRef
  Contributor ID” project. This isn’t just playing with words either.
  For instance, as soon as you start thinking about things like “how do
  you accommodate reviewers” in this system you need to think of things
  like pseudo-anonymity. That is, you want somebody to be able to get
  credit for doing reviews in a way that doesn’t necessarily reveal who
  reviewed what. In turn, the pay-off for designing a system whereby
  anonymous reviewers might be credited with reviews could be profound.
  It might ultimately result in researchers having much more incentive
  to review if reviewing were something that could be counted and rated
  in the same way that authorship is.</p>
  <p>Second, I think that people conflate a lot of issues when they talk
  about “author identifiers” [sic]. Are they talking about the simple
  token used (e.g. a unique string or a number assigned to an individual
  like a social security number), are they talking about an
  authentication mechanism (e.g.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090221213233/http://openid.net/what/"><bold>OpenID</bold></ext-link>,
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090221213233/http://shibboleth.internet2.edu/"><bold>Shibboleth</bold></ext-link>)
  or are they talking about the profile information associated with an
  identifier (e.g. publications, affiliation, contact info, etc.)?
  Obviously, these all overlap in some ways, but how they relate and
  what you choose to focus on depends largely on your use cases.</p>
  <p>Third, speaking of use cases, our requirements gathering has
  identified two broad categories of use cases that, though related,
  have profoundly different implementation implications. One category of
  use cases identified revolves around “knowledge discovery” and the
  other category of cases revolves around “authentication.”</p>
  <p>The “knowledge discovery” use cases are probably the most obvious
  things that people would like to be able to do with a contributor ID
  such as:</p>
  <list list-type="bullet">
    <list-item>
      <p>Determine what IDs authored/edited/reviewed document X</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>What documents where authored/edited/reviewed by ID Y</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>What IDs are related to ID Z and what is the nature of that
      relationship (e.g. co-authored, edited, reviewed)</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>What (subject to privacy settings) is the profile information
      for ID Z (e.g. institutional affiliation, email address, etc.)</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>All the author IDs and their respective publications where the
      institutional affiliation recorded by the author is X</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Etc.</p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
  <p>At this point I feel obliged to point out that the bulk of our
  requirements gathering has been focused on trying to understand the
  needs of our member publishers. The reason I mention this here is that
  the bulk of the “authentication” use cases that we identified are all
  focused around making publisher back-office systems less cumbersome.
  So, for instance, publishers are interested in using a “contributor
  id” for:</p>
  <list list-type="bullet">
    <list-item>
      <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090221213233/http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Single_sign-on"><bold>single
      sign-on</bold></ext-link> (SSO) for manuscript tracking
      systems</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Disambiguating contact information for use by editorial
      offices, royalty payments systems, copyright clearances, etc.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Automatic updating of email addresses for table of contents
      (TOC) alerts and other automated email communications</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Automated tools for detecting potential reviewers, including
      tools for detecting potential conflicts of interest</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Synchronization with publisher web site user profiles and
      granting researchers customized, privileged access to content
      based on profiles</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Understanding all of the manifold ways in which an individual
      “contributes” to a publisher or a field (e.g. As an editor,
      reviewer, letter writer, conference chair, etc.).</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Etc.</p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
  <p>As I said, these are very publisher-focused use cases, but this is
  not to say that we are not interested in the use cases posed by
  librarians, researchers and funding agencies. We have actively been
  talking to people from each of these constituencies and we are trying
  to understand if there are ways in which we can help them. For
  instance, we have recently been speaking to a group of researchers who
  are interested in using some sort of authenticated contributor ID as a
  mechanism for controlling who gets trusted access to sensitive
  genome-wide aggregate genotype data.</p>
  <p>The interesting thing to note about these “authentication” use
  cases is that they have far more stringent requirements than the
  “knowledge discovery” use cases. In other words if you are only trying
  to address the knowledge discovery problem, it might be fine to use
  automated techniques to disambiguate authors and assign IDs to them.
  State-of-the-art mechanisms for automatic disambiguation of authors
  from a defined corpus can be 96-97% accurate, which sounds pretty
  good. At least until you realize that CrossRef has ~200K new article
  DOIs deposited each month, each of which on average has about 3
  authors. This could potentially leave you with upwards of 20K in
  mis/un-identified authors. This error rate might be an acceptable
  tradeoff for knowledge discovery type applications, but it certainly
  isn’t suitable for authentication type applications.</p>
  <p>Speaking of authentication, I think the fourth thing to note is
  that, though I think <bold>OpenID</bold> will probably play an
  important role in any service we provide, by itself it makes a pretty
  bad identity token and would provide little utility on its own. This
  all gets back to some of the issues that I raised above when
  discussing persistent identifiers: URI-based identifiers are fragile
  because they depend on the domain name. What happens if your OpenID is
  tied to a domain that you don’t control (e.g. a company, an
  institution a country)? How can you guarantee that, should you leave
  that company/institution/country that they will do the right thing and
  let you maintain or redirect that identifying credential?</p>
  <p>The traditional geeky response to this scenario is “don’t get
  yourself into that situation. Only tie your <bold>OpenID</bold> to a
  domain that you own.” (Insert forks in eyeballs). Again, you do not
  “own” a domain name. You lease it. What happens if you lose control of
  it due to litigation, forgetfulness, poverty, divorce, death? Death?
  Yes, what happens when somebody dies? When I die does the not-yet-born
  Georgia Bilder get to buy “my” domain “gbilder.com” and make it the
  basis of her identity? Mmm… Gets kind of complicated doesn’t it?</p>
  <p>Of course, lots of the same issues can be raised with CrossRef,
  right? What guarantees that CrossRef won’t become evil and co-opt all
  of our identities? This, of course is the big fear underlining the
  knee-jerk reaction against “centralized systems” in favor of
  “distributed systems”. The problem with this, as I mentioned in the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090221213233/https://friendfeed.com/e/c1fd00ec-15f9-d894-4ea9-4ffeaac5ae28/A-specialist-OpenID-service-to-provide-unique/"><bold>FriendFeed
  thread</bold></ext-link> is that my personal and unfashionable
  observation is that “distributed” begets “centralized.” For every
  distributed service created, we’ve then had to create a centralized
  service to make it useable again (ICANN, Google, Pirate Bay, CrossRef,
  DOAJ, ticTocs, WorldCat, etc.). This gets us back to square one and
  makes me think the real issue is- how do you make the centralized
  system that eventually emerges accountable? This is, of course, a
  social issue more than a technical issue and involves making sure that
  whatever entity emerges has clearly defined data portability policies
  and a “living will” that attempts to guarantee that the service can be
  run in perpetuity- even if by another organization. For the record, I
  don’t think adopting the slogan “don’t be evil” is enough ;).</p>
  <p>Anyway- I could go on talking about what the contributor ID “should
  look like” for a very, very long time, but I think that the above
  probably addresses some of the major points that are raised when the
  topic is discussed.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="5-what-are-the-benefits-and-maybe-disadvantages-if-crossref-manages-the-author-identifier">
  <title>5. What are the benefits (and maybe disadvantages) if CrossRef
  manages the author identifier?</title>
  <p>I think the biggest potential disadvantage that CrossRef has is
  that it is a consensus-based organization that is governed by
  sometimes fierce competitors. This aspect of the organization can
  sometimes slow things down. On the other hand, this can also be a huge
  strength for us. Once a consensus is agreed, we can move very quickly
  and push uptake across the industry.</p>
  <p>Research increasingly transcends institutional, geographic and
  discipline boundaries, so I think another advantage that we have is
  that we are well positioned to provide a service that is similarly
  unconstrained.</p>
  <p>Finally, I think that we have a very interesting advantage by
  virtue of the fact that our infrastructure is already integrated
  upstream in the publication process. There is a useful property of the
  system that we are designing in that, as researchers used the CrossRef
  identifier in their interactions with publishers and this data is fed
  back into our system via DOI deposits, you could start to develop a
  trust-metric based on the types of claims attached to an author’s
  profile. For instance, an author profile that consisted of nothing but
  self-claims (e.g. I claim I wrote paper X) might not be very worthy of
  trust whereas an author profile that consisted of publications that
  had been verified by the publisher (by virtue of those publications
  having been processed along with the CrossRef contributor ID) would
  have far more credibility. You can start to see an interesting
  hierarchy of publication claims emerging such as:</p>
  <list list-type="bullet">
    <list-item>
      <p>Proxy claims (Leigh claims Geoffrey wrote article X)</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Self Claims (Geoffrey claims Geoffrey wrote article X)</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Verified claims (Geoffrey claims Geoffrey wrote article X
      <bold>and</bold> the “Journal of Psychoceramics” confirms this
      claim)</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Verified Proxy Claims (Geoffrey (who has already been verified
      as an author of article X) claims that Kirsty was also an author
      of article X)</p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
</sec>
<sec id="6-how-does-your-author-identifier-relate-to-other-identifiers-e-g-researcherid-scopus-author-idor-openid">
  <title>6. How does your author identifier relate to other identifiers,
  e.g.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090221213233/http://www.researcherid.com/">ResearcherID</ext-link>,
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090221213233/http://help.scopus.com/robo/projects/schelp/h_autsrch_intro.htm">Scopus
  Author ID</ext-link>or
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090221213233/http://openid.net/what/">OpenID</ext-link>?</title>
  <p>OpenID is a different kettle of fish, and I discussed it already
  above. As for the others (I’d add
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090221213233/http://www.authorresolver.com/"><bold>Author
  Resolver</bold></ext-link>,
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090221213233/http://repec.org/"><bold>RePEC</bold></ext-link>,
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090221213233/http://www.scilink.com/start.action"><bold>SciLink</bold></ext-link>,
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090221213233/http://bibserver.berkeley.edu/cgi-bin/mathweb/index.py"><bold>MathPeople</bold></ext-link>,
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090221213233/http://network.nature.com/"><bold>Nature
  Network</bold></ext-link>, etc.), we’ve actually been talking to some
  of these parties in order to understand how they might relate to a
  CrossRef Contributor ID. One obvious difference is in the use-cases
  being addressed. All of the above are focused on “knowledge discovery”
  use-cases. None of them pretends to provide any sort of authentication
  services. It is also interesting to note that in a lot of the above
  cases, the parties see their author identification functionality as a
  means to an end. For instance, their primary application is “creating
  better metrics” or “running a social network” or “expert
  identification” for recruiting purposes. In these cases they don’t
  necessarily see a CrossRef system as being competitive and, in fact,
  they think that such a service might even improve their primary
  application.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="7-can-you-talk-about-the-current-status-and-next-planned-steps-of-the-contributorid-project">
  <title>7. Can you talk about the current status and next planned steps
  of the ContributorID project?</title>
  <p>We just ended lengthy period of investigation and requirements
  gathering. In the process we went down a few blind alleys. Now we are
  working on a prototype that we will test with a few publishers. It is
  hard to say how long this will take as we are just in the process of
  planning this phase.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="8-satisfying-many-different-interests-is-one-of-the-biggest-challenges-in-creating-an-author-identifier-what-are-the-lessons-learned-from-implementing-the-digital-object-identifier-doi-">
  <title>8. Satisfying many different interests is one of the biggest
  challenges in creating an author identifier. What are the lessons
  learned from implementing the digital object identifier
  (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090221213233/http://www.doi.org/">DOI</ext-link>)?</title>
  <p>I’ll give you one tactical lesson and one strategic lesson.</p>
  <p>The tactical lesson is foremost in my mind because I have recently
  been trying to build tools to encourage researchers to use DOIs in
  their citations. The problem arrises when a researcher occasionally
  encounters a DOI that is 80 characters long. There is just no way that
  a researcher is going to insert <bold>that</bold> in a citation. The
  tactical lesson here is that it is sometimes better to make an
  identifier opaque and short. This is also a tremendously unfashionable
  position to take, but I think that one of Clay Shirky’s observations
  about hierarchical categorization systems also applies to identifiers.
  If you make the identifier human-interpretable and add semantics, then
  people will be extremely tempted to start hard-coding ontologies into
  their identifiers. This makes said identifiers both long and
  inherently brittle. The ontologies will inevitably evolve, and then
  people will want to change the identifiers- at which point they will
  either break or you have a giant identifier mapping subsystem to
  create.</p>
  <p>We see a manifestation of this syndrome already with the DOI. Each
  DOI has a four-digit “prefix” which is effectively a namespace for the
  assigning publisher. Note that I said the “assigning” publisher- this
  is not necessarily the publisher who currently “owns” the DOI with
  that prefix. What this often means is that, when publisher A acquires
  publisher B, publisher A will ask CrossRef if we can create new DOIs
  for all of publisher B’s backfiles so that they all have the same
  prefix! The answer to their request is “no”, but you wouldn’t believe
  how stroppy publishers can get about this. They somehow imbue this
  ridiculous four-digit prefix with branding significance. This, of
  course, is absolutely mental, but it is a predictable form of mental.
  The French went mad when they had to replace their region-encoded
  license plates with opaque EU ones. People in the US go mad when they
  are given new area codes. In short, when people associate semantic
  significance in identifiers, you will face problems.</p>
  <p>The strategic lesson is basically a recapitulation of the
  &quot;technical vs “social” theme I’ve been banging on about. I think
  that, at first, even our membership thought of the CrossRef DOI as
  being a technical solution to a problem, not a social one. It has
  become much clearer to us over the years that CrossRef DOIs are only
  as persistent as CrossRef staff. That is, we sometimes have to bang on
  lots of heads and threaten members with fines and worse in order to
  make sure that they are meeting their terms &amp; conditions. The good
  news is that CrossRef has become essential infrastructure for a wide
  variety of publishers who are often at each other’s throats in any
  other circumstances. In many ways these “different interests” are our
  strength. Everybody wants it to work better, nobody wants to see it
  die and nobody wants it to be co-opted. We are working hard to put the
  social structures into place that will guarantee its longevity. Part
  of this is making sure that we are fiscally sound (which we are) and
  part of this is making sure that, even if we do disappear, other
  stakeholders can run the system if need be.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="9-what-can-researchers-interested-in-author-identifiers-do-to-help">
  <title>9. What can researchers interested in author identifiers do to
  help?</title>
  <list list-type="bullet">
    <list-item>
      <p>Feed CrossRef more use cases.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Let CrossRef know what you think will/won’t work.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Make sure you let your publishers know if you think this is a
      good idea. Naturally, I expect you will also let them know if you
      think it is a bad idea ;-)</p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
  <p>I can be reached at <bold>gbilder at crossref dot org</bold>.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
