<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Is Schema.org about a technical standard or about
something else?</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2011-06-19">
<day>19</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2011</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>At the beginning of the month Google, Bing and Yahoo
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525041721/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2011/06/07/schema-org-for-scholarly-html/">announced</ext-link>
schema.org, a new initiative for structured markup on the web. Richard
MacManus responded with a critical piece at ReadWriteWeb
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525041721/http://www.readwriteweb.com/archives/is_schemaorg_really_a_google_land_grab.php">Is
Schema.org really a Google Land Grab?</ext-link>), mainly criticizing
that the initiative didn’t use RDFa and didn’t seem to have consulted
with the web standards body W3C. The best discussion about schema.org
that I found so far (via Eric Hellman’s
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525041721/http://go-to-hellman.blogspot.com/2011/06/our-metadata-overlords-and-that.html">post</ext-link>)
is by Henri Sivonen
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525041721/http://hsivonen.iki.fi/schema-org-and-communities/">Schema.org
and Pre-Existing Communities</ext-link>). He explains why he thinks it
makes sense that schema.org picked microdata over RDFa or microformats
as markup standard. And he discusses how the web community has developed
standards in the past and what characterizes the successful efforts. I
personally believe that schema.org will bring us closer to the semantic
web, and the discussion reminds me a little bit of the discussion around
HTML 5 vs. XHTML 2 (where the pragmatic solution supported by the major
browser vendors won over the ideal but dogmatic solution discussed for
many years in standards bodies). Schema.org is will certainly be
discussed at the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525041721/http://scienceonlinelondon.wikidot.com/start">Science
Online London Conference</ext-link> in September.</p>
<p>Whether schema.org becomes a success depends in large part on the
adoption by the community. Schema.org is backed by the three largest
search engines (Google, Bing, Yahoo), so everybody who wants to be found
by them will take a close look at the standard. Scholarly content is for
the most part collected and curated in specialized databases. This makes
it not only a technical decision whether or not to adopt schema.org for
markup (we need more and better defined scholarly data types in the
standard), but also a business decision. If scholarly publishers start
marking up their journal articles, they will be easier to find via
Google, Bing, etc. But will this mean that institutions would start
re-evaluating their subscriptions to commercial services like Scopus or
Web of Science? And will schema.org help or hinder the very large market
of discovery tools for scholarly content?</p>
<p>At this point this is very much a theoretical discussion. We first
need better scholarly data types in the schema.org standard. The
Association of Educational Publishers and Creative Commons
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525041721/http://www.aepweb.org/mediacenter/AEP-CC-Schema_6-7-11.htm">has
announced</ext-link> an initiative to create a metadata framework for
educational resources based on schema.org. And we hopefully see a
similar initiative from scholarly publishers. I hope that the group
behind schema.org is open to this input.</p>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
