<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Just Science starts tomorrow</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2008-02-03">
<day>3</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2008</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611110608/http://www.justscience.net/2008/?page_id=1368">Just
Science</ext-link> is an effort to collect blog posts about science that
are written within one week. Just Science 2008 will start
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611110608/http://scienceblogs.com/gnxp/2008/01/just_science_announcement.php">tomorrow</ext-link>
and ends February 8. Science bloggers that agree to participate should
write one daily blog entry for these five days. The blog entries should
talk about science, and not about topic related to science (e.g. open
access). Interested readers can subscribe to the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611110608/http://www.justscience.net/2008/?feed=rss2">RSS
Feed</ext-link> and will automatically receive all blog posts.</p>
<p>The recently launched
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611110608/http://www.researchblogging.org/">Research
Blogging</ext-link> is a related effort to aggregate blog posts about
science.</p>
<p>Like many other science bloggers, I do not write directly about
science, but rather about issues that are important for scientists. I
have so far been reluctant to blog about science. Why is that? Jon Udell
two weeks ago wrote a
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611110608/http://blog.jonudell.net/2008/01/22/bloggers-talk-to-bloggers-scientists-talk-to-scientists/">blog
post</ext-link> where he observes that bloggers talk to bloggers and
scientists talk to scientists. I agree with him that we need better
tools to integrate scientific publishing and the blogosphere.</p>
<p>But more importantly, many Scientists (including myself) are still
reluctant to talk about their science in the blogosphere. This is
understandable if you have unpublished results, half-baked ideas, etc
that are not yet ready to be shared with the scientific community. But
non-scientists usually don't read the scientific literature, as most
papers are difficult to impossible to understand – and access to
scientific literature can be expensive. We shouldn't forget to
communicate our research to the community. If we don't do that, we
shouldn't be surprised if the traditional media either don't report our
research at all, or give a distorted view that we are not happy
with.</p>
<p>Having said that, I don't have have any immediate plans to blog about
science. My area of expertise is cancer research, and talking about
cancer research is even more complicated because of often unrealistic
expectations that these findings quickly translate into new treatment
options for patients.</p>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
