<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Lemon8-XML: Interview with MJ Suhonos</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2009-02-27">
<day>27</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2009</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Finishing an exciting research project and writing it up in a paper
are the first two steps in getting your work published. The next two
steps – submitting your paper to a journal and getting it through the
review process – have changed dramatically in the last 10-15 years. No
longer do we have to print out our manuscript using one of the few
available laser printers in the department, paste our gel pictures on
cardboard and number the figures with Letraset. And then send it off
with the mail. And then repeat the process for every revision of the
manuscript.</p>
<fig>
  <caption><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003091211/http://www.flickr.com/photos/synaptichappenings/2276034665/">Flickr
  Photo</ext-link> by synaptic.happenings.</p></caption>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="https://martinfenner.ghost.io/content/images/2021/02/2276034665_456342fb50_n.jpg" xlink:title="" />
</fig>
<p>Now of course we submit our manuscripts online using a manuscript
submission system such as
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003091211/http://www.editorialmanager.com/homepage/home.htm">Editorial
Manager</ext-link> or
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003091211/http://www.ejpress.com/index.shtml">eJournalPress</ext-link>.
Which is not to say that the process is necessarily easy or fun. Many of
us can tell stories of spending hours or whole days until the manuscript
is finally submitted. We struggle with the conversion of the different
parts of the manuscript into a single PDF file, have problems with
fonts, have to deal with different graphics formats (e.g. PDF, JPEG,
EPS, TIFF), don’t use the correct style for our references, etc.</p>
<p>The flip side of this is the time and money spent at the journal to
format your accepted manuscript into something that can be turned into a
journal article published online or in print.</p>
<p>Some of these problems wouldn’t exist if we used a common document
format for manuscript writing, manuscript revisions and manuscript
printing and online viewing. That common document format does exist and
is called
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003091211/http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/">NLM
Journal Publishing DTD</ext-link> (and no, it’s not LaTex). This
document format is used in the workflow of many journals, but until now
has rarely been used by authors. Last November
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003091211/http://network.nature.com/people/mfenner/blog/2008/11/07/interview-with-pablo-fernicola">I
talked with Pablo Fermicola</ext-link> about a free tool that allows
Microsoft Word to save manuscripts in that format
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003091211/http://www.microsoft.com/DOWNLOADS/details.aspx?FamilyID=09c55527-0759-4d6d-ae02-51e90131997e&amp;displaylang=en">Microsoft
Word Authoring Add-In</ext-link>).
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003091211/http://www.inera.com/extylesinfo.shtml#NLM">eXtyles
NLM</ext-link> is another tool for Microsoft Word with similar
functionality.</p>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003091211/http://pkp.sfu.ca/lemon8">Lemon8-XML</ext-link>
takes a different approach in helping academic authors convert their
manuscripts into the NLM DTD format. Version 1.0 of the software
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003091211/http://pkp.sfu.ca/node/1891">was
released today</ext-link>, so this was a great opportunity to talk with
the lead developer <italic><italic>MJ Suhonos</italic></italic> about
Lemon8-XML.</p>
<sec id="1-can-you-describe-what-lemon8-xml-is-and-does">
  <title>1. Can you describe what Lemon8-XML is and does?</title>
  <p>Lemon8-XML is a freely-available, open source web application that
  aims to help academic authors and editors convert scholarly articles
  from layout formats like Microsoft Word to structured XML formats
  without requiring a great deal of knowledge of XML or the schema that
  they’re working with. It’s based on the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003091211/http://opendocument.xml.org/overview">OpenDocument</ext-link>
  format internally, and the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003091211/http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/">NLM
  Journal Publishing DTD</ext-link> as the default export format.</p>
  <p>Originally, Lemon8-XML came from a bunch of scripts that performed
  a series of tasks:</p>
  <list list-type="bullet">
    <list-item>
      <p>convert an author’s article from a myriad of document formats
      to OpenDocument,</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>parse the article and try to extract metadata, determine
      section structure based on layout information, and parse citations
      into their disparate elements,</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>export this semantic data as XML.</p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
  <p>The work to date on Lemon8-XML has been building these functions
  into an easy-to-use web UI that also provides some editing facilities;
  for example, to fix problems from incomplete or incorrect parsing. One
  of the most promising features of Lemon8-XML is its ability to parse
  citations in a wide range of formats, and automatically try to correct
  or enhance them by searching for their complete records in, eg.
  PubMed, CrossRef, and WorldCat.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="2-what-are-the-advantages-of-using-lemon8-xml-over-traditional-word-processors-such-as-microsoft-word">
  <title>2. What are the advantages of using Lemon8-XML over traditional
  word processors such as Microsoft Word?</title>
  <p>I should start by clarifying that Lemon8-XML wasn’t really intended
  to be used as a word processor, but rather a conversion tool to be
  used after the writing was done. This was to fit in with existing
  practices, where authors upload papers to a journal and the editing is
  done afterwards. Of course, the advent of online word processors
  challenges this notion, and has caused us to think differently about
  the editing aspects of Lemon8-XML. Cross-platform deployment and
  online collaboration are things that obviously the web is great for.
  An author could, for example, upload a paper to Lemon8-XML, and work
  together with an editor on that same copy, regardless of what desktop
  tools they have. One advantage of this idea is that the burden of work
  is shared between more people, whether that’s an author and a
  copyeditor, or multiple editors. This is a big deal for small journals
  who don’t have funds for dedicated staff.</p>
  <p>Within PKP in general, we also try to keep the requirements for our
  software as low as possible, both technically and financially. So, for
  journals like
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003091211/http://www.openmedicine.ca/">Open
  Medicine</ext-link>, who are entirely volunteer-run, paying $230 per
  copy for Microsoft Word on each computer actually represents a
  significant cost. Using OpenOffice on the desktop and a single copy of
  Lemon8-XML on a server — both of which are free — lets them spend this
  out-of-pocket expense on other things to keep their journal alive and
  growing. Microsoft Word also has an unfortunate history of being
  variable and inconsistent across platforms and versions. We wanted to
  help people escape that, which is one of the reasons for converting
  everything to OpenDocument as early as possible. In addition,
  stewarding documents through an online workflow can be a laborious and
  frustrating process, so the possibility for journals to make the
  editing process more centralized and interactive by integrating
  Lemon8-XML is a compelling one.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="3-how-does-lemon8-xml-compare-to-the-microsoft-word-article-authoring-add-in-that-also-produces-nlm-journal-publishing-dtd-output">
  <title>3. How does Lemon8-XML compare to the Microsoft Word Article
  Authoring Add-In, that also produces NLM Journal Publishing DTD
  output?</title>
  <p>In many ways, we’re working in parallel with Pablo Fermicola’s
  group at Microsoft —
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003091211/http://perspectives.on10.net/blogs/jonudell/Word-for-scientific-publishing/">they’re
  basically building an editor</ext-link> for placing a structured NLM
  schema on top of the Microsoft WordML (DOCX) XML format, while
  Lemon8-XML places the NLM schema on top of the OpenDocument (ODT) XML
  format. Of course, there’s nothing saying that Lemon8-XML couldn’t be
  modified to read DOCX files generated with the Article Authoring
  Add-In or vice-versa. This difference is really a reflection of the
  two competing standards, and the tools they use, with the same
  ultimate goal: to allow users to generate semantically-structured
  documents from layout-based ones. In addition, the Article Authoring
  Add-In is built on Microsoft Word 2007 as a platform, which I think
  has some limitations; for example, most of the PKP team don’t use
  Windows, so the Article Authoring Add-In is basically inaccessible to
  us. But overall, our goals appear to be very similar.</p>
  <p>To my mind, the main difference between the projects is in how they
  approach the user: the Article Authoring Add-In presents new tools for
  adding semantic mark-up in a (somewhat) familiar interface; many
  authors are already familiar with Microsoft Word and are comfortable
  working in that environment. My concern with this approach is that it
  still has strong ties to the layout paradigm, so, for example, marking
  text as “article title” may not be sufficiently different in authors’
  minds from marking text as “16 point bold”. I also think the idea of
  presenting an entire document in a single free-form editor reinforces
  the layout paradigm, as opposed to identifying the distinct elements
  which comprise a scholarly article. Lemon8-XML, on the other hand,
  builds from these individual elements, and assembles them within the
  user interface based on their structural relations. You can see this
  reflected in the tabs in the current interface: “Metadata, Sections,
  Citations” — these are the front, body, back matter of an article.</p>
  <p>This places restrictions on how a user can edit their article,
  which is sometimes frustrating, but it forces them to think about what
  they’re doing and the meaning of their content: why do I have to place
  it here, what content is valid in this element, etc. In a future
  version, this will all be on the same web page, similar to how it
  would appear in Microsoft Word, but again with the semantic structure
  visually enforced instead of being totally free-form.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="4-what-is-the-difference-between-lemon8-xml-and-online-word-processors-such-as-google-docs">
  <title>4. What is the difference between Lemon8-XML and online word
  processors such as Google Docs?</title>
  <p>Unlike most word processor software, Lemon8-XML is built around the
  semantic notion of a document, not its appearance. We wanted to help
  people begin to think about the meaning and structure of their
  articles, not just whether they look good on the screen or as a PDF.
  It turns out this is a tough challenge, though — people have a hard
  time with WYSIWYM (What You See Is What You Mean) editors, and there’s
  often a lot of complex structure to present visually for editing. One
  thing people seem to be comfortable with, or at least used to, is
  entering metadata and information in web forms, so much of the
  Lemon8-XML user interface is built that way.</p>
  <p>Lemon8-XML is also specifically aimed at modeling and editing
  scholarly articles, which have a long history of practice and some
  very rigid conventions that aren’t applicable more broadly. This means
  it’s not a general-purpose editor like most word processors, but that
  also means we can focus on the specific things it should do, and
  refine them rather than trying to please everyone and falling victim
  to feature-creep.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="5-why-did-you-pick-the-nlm-journal-publishing-dtd-as-document-format">
  <title>5. Why did you pick the NLM Journal Publishing DTD as document
  format?</title>
  <p>I did a survey in 2003 of available DTDs to represent scholarly
  journal articles, looking for something I could use as a common source
  for generating HTML and PDF. I selected the NLM DTD above the others
  (eg. BioMed Central,
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003091211/http://www.docbook.org/whatis">DocBook</ext-link>,
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003091211/http://www.erudit.org/apropos/info.html">Erudit</ext-link>,
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003091211/http://www.tei-c.org/index.xml">Text
  Encoding Initiative</ext-link>) since it seemed to strike a good
  balance between comprehensiveness and granularity; it can be as simple
  or as complex as you need it to be. It also had a very thorough
  citation model and a modular design, so extensibility wasn’t a concern
  — I liked the “journal articles plus” concept that it was built with.
  And, of course, being stewarded by the National Library of Medicine
  meant it would likely be well-maintained and remain open. The fact
  that it became
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003091211/http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/about/faq.html#q21">the
  central XML standard for PubMed Central as an archival
  format</ext-link> was just icing on the cake.</p>
  <p>Another reason is that, among the STM journals at least, a lot of
  established practice has developed around generating HTML and PDF from
  NLM XML specifically, and we want to support that. Actually, we want
  to expand adoption of the NLM DTD by making it accessible to
  humanities and social science journals, as well. The information
  contained in the XML is essentially identical regardless of subject,
  which means we just need to develop discipline-specific rendering; for
  example, for different citation styles. I think there’s an incredible
  amount of room for growth and improvement in this area in
  particular.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="6-does-lemon8-xml-integrate-with-manuscript-submission-systems-such-as-open-journal-systems">
  <title>6. Does Lemon8-XML integrate with manuscript submission systems
  such as Open Journal Systems?</title>
  <p>Not yet, but that’s the next major area of development immediately
  following the 1.0 release.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003091211/http://pkp.sfu.ca/?q=ojs">OJS</ext-link>
  has been so successful, one of our biggest challenges has been keeping
  it flexible enough to support a wide range of workflows, and we want
  to continue with that by taking as much of the technology from
  Lemon8-XML as possible and folding it into OJS. I don’t know if we’ll
  see a side-by-side kind of integration immediately, but rather
  strategic enhancements of certain aspects of OJS: automatic document
  conversion, annotation directly within articles, extraction and
  stripping of metadata to improve blindedness, automatically parsing
  and linking citations, etc. By going this way, we give users the
  ability to choose specific features that are useful for them, and at
  the same time build upon the huge community that already exists for
  OJS in terms of development, testing, and feedback.</p>
  <p>There’s definitely still value in a stand-alone Lemon8-XML for
  cases where people don’t want journal workflow, or where they’re
  integrating with a different kind of system. So, we will be working on
  a Lemon8-XML 2.0 that’s built on the same modular, reliable framework
  as the rest of the PKP suite, and back-porting code from OJS.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="7-what-is-the-public-knowledge-project">
  <title>7. What is the Public Knowledge Project?</title>
  <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003091211/http://pkp.sfu.ca/node/1410">PKP</ext-link>
  is a small research group distributed between Simon Fraser University,
  University of British Columbia, Stanford University and Arizona State
  University that has been quietly
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003091211/http://www.openmedicine.ca/article/view/276">developing
  open source software for online publishing and knowledge
  sharing</ext-link> for the past 10 years, under the direction of Dr.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003091211/http://ed.stanford.edu/suse/faculty/displayRecord.php?suid=willinsk">John
  Willinsky</ext-link> at Stanford. Our major aim is to provide tools
  for improving access to academic research, as well as helping improve
  the quality and efficiency of its production. Our philosophy is also
  to create partnerships between researchers, librarians, publishers, to
  help them build sustainable and globally accessible scholarly
  infrastructure. In my mind, it’s also about giving people options and
  choices aside from what’s being offered commercially, especially to
  those who can’t afford them, like a lot of developing-world
  journals.</p>
  <p>We have four applications in addition to Lemon8-XML:
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003091211/http://pkp.sfu.ca/?q=ojs">Open
  Journal Systems</ext-link>, our most popular, is being used by over
  2500 journals in over 50 countries. We also produce a conference
  management system
  (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003091211/http://pkp.sfu.ca/?q=ocs">Open
  Conference Systems</ext-link>), an OAI metadata indexing system
  (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003091211/http://pkp.sfu.ca/?q=harvester">Open
  Archives Harvester</ext-link>), and a monograph publishing system
  (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003091211/http://pkp.sfu.ca/omp">Open
  Monograph Press</ext-link>), currently under development. All of our
  software is freely available under the GPL open source license, and we
  have an active community of over 1500 users. We’ve worked with small,
  volunteer-run humanities journals, to major international society
  conferences, to high-profile, ISI-ranked medical journals.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="8-what-are-your-responsibilities-within-the-lemon8-xml-project">
  <title>8. What are your responsibilities within the Lemon8-XML
  project?</title>
  <p>Because our group’s so small, we all share responsibilities — there
  are only a handful of people to do almost all of the development, and
  that’s in addition to handling the support, correspondence, and
  software maintenance of the rest of the PKP suite, not to mention
  providing various international workshops. So, we often divvy roles
  based on expertise or interest. Since bringing Lemon8-XML to PKP, I do
  the vast majority of Lemon8-XML development, but I also manage
  collaborations with our development and research partners, and write
  white papers on the software design we use to share our ideas, on top
  of contributing to the daily stuff above.</p>
  <p>Probably the biggest struggle in developing Lemon8-XML has been
  that it’s one person, about half-time, doing all of the coding,
  testing, etc. We already have a number of very exciting partnerships
  with groups who will be testing and providing feedback, and have
  contributed a talented developer who’s recently started half-time as
  well. Of course, we can always use more help with the coding side of
  things. Our team is quite spread-out geographically, so we have a lot
  of experience with working across time zones and with distributed
  development practices. I’m hoping that after the 1.0 release, more
  people will become interested and will want to help get involved.
  Whether contributing plugins for citation processing, or helping us
  improve the UI — really, anything that helps the software grow will
  benefit more authors and editors, which is the main goal.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="9-what-did-you-do-before-starting-to-work-on-lemon8-xml">
  <title>9. What did you do before starting to work on
  Lemon8-XML?</title>
  <p>I worked for a two-person medical informatics journal that was
  publishing around 50 articles a year using Microsoft FrontPage and
  managed entirely via email. My job was to transition it to an online
  manuscript management system (naturally, I chose OJS), convert around
  300 back articles from FrontPage HTML into valid NLM XML, develop a
  custom rendering system that would create HTML and PDF galleys from
  that XML, get the journal accepted into PubMed Central, and establish
  an impact factor from ISI (which is now 3.0) — oh, and continue
  publishing 50 articles a year. The journal also ran an international
  medical conference during that time (using OCS). Three years later, I
  left to do my Masters degree in Library/Information Studies, during
  which time I joined PKP and started working on Lemon8-XML, based on a
  lot of the things I’d learned from my time at the journal.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="10-do-you-want-to-talk-about-future-plans-for-lemon8-xml">
  <title>10. Do you want to talk about future plans for
  Lemon8-XML?</title>
  <p>The most common question I’m asked is, “when will it be ready?”,
  which for many people really means, “when will it be a one-click magic
  bullet for getting my journal into PubMed Central?”. I’m proud of the
  Lemon8-XML 1.0 release, and I feel that it represents a significant
  milestone given how far we’ve come — but there’s still a long way to
  go before we get to that point. I hope people will view the 1.0
  version as a stable tool that’s already being used in production by at
  least one journal, and a strong indicator of PKP‘s commitment to
  developing research and software in this area.</p>
  <p>I mentioned the Open Journal Systems integration, which is both a
  strategic and pragmatic move; this will be our main focus, as well as
  integration with OMP from its earliest inception. We also want to
  improve the editing aspect of Lemon8-XML — there is some great work
  being done in the area of using style templates for providing
  structural mark-up in traditional word processors; we will be working
  more closely with Peter Sefton’s group on the ICE project, who have a
  lot of experience. I’d also like to re-visit the idea of using
  web-based WYSIWYM editors like
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003091211/http://www.wymeditor.org/">WYMeditor</ext-link>
  or an enhanced
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003091211/http://tinymce.moxiecode.com/">TinyMCE</ext-link>
  as part of a user interface overhaul, and possibly integrating more
  closely with Google Docs if that’s an option. Certainly, there’s room
  for adding more citation lookup plugins:
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003091211/http://www.oaister.org/about.html">OAIster</ext-link>,
  Amazon.com,
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003091211/http://citeseer.ist.psu.edu/citeseer.html">CiteSeer</ext-link>,
  etc. as well as improving the existing ones. Finally, we want to try
  applying the approach we’ve used with citation parsing and lookup with
  other scholarly article elements; for example, checking quotations for
  correctness and plagiarism, extracting and linking author/contributor
  identifiers, and so on. We also have some ideas around
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003091211/http://www.dlib.org/dlib/may06/apps/05apps.html">OpenURL</ext-link>
  that may or may not come into Lemon8-XML development.</p>
  <p>We’re also starting a major side-project based entirely around the
  NLM DTD in two parts: 1) building mappings from various other XML
  schemas to NLM; and 2) building a standard set of rendering tools for
  generating HTML and PDF from NLM XML, in a way that can be easily
  customized for an individual journal. There are already a lot of
  groups out there using NLM but currently the practice is quite
  fragmented — we’d like to see these journals and publishers become
  more connected and share their work as a community. As I say, we want
  to help increase adoption as a way to raise the bar on journal quality
  and improve options for publishing and archiving.</p>
  <p>One of the most important things we’ve learned during the
  development of Lemon8-XML has been the value of user feedback early
  and often, and remaining aware of related work that’s going on, so we
  can remain efficient by building partnerships instead of working in
  parallel. We’ll continue pursuing this approach, and I’d encourage
  anyone who is interested in any of these areas or has ideas of their
  own to contribute to
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003091211/http://pkp.sfu.ca/contact">get
  in touch with us</ext-link>.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
