<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Let’s make science metrics more
scientific</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2010-03-29">
<day>29</day>
<month>3</month>
<year>2010</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<fig>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611101936im_/http://www.researchblogging.org/public/citation_icons/rb2_large_gray.png" xlink:title="" />
</fig>
<p>In the March 25 edition of <italic><italic>Nature</italic></italic>,
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611101936/http://client.norc.org/jole/SOLEweb/JLHome.html">Julia
Lane</ext-link>, Program Director of the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611101936/http://www.nsf.gov/funding/pgm_summ.jsp?pims_id=501084&amp;org=NSF&amp;from_org=NSF">Science
of Science and Innovation Policy Program</ext-link> at the National
Science Foundation, wrote an interesting opinion piece about the
assessment of scientific performance. She argues that the current
systems of measurement are inadequate, as they have several inherent
problems and do not capture the full spectrum of scientific activities.
Good scientific metrics are difficult, but without them we risk making
the wrong decisions about funding and academic positions.</p>
<p>Julia Lane suggests that we develop and use standard identifiers both
for researchers and their scientific output (examples given include the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611101936/http://www.doi.org/">DOI</ext-link>
for publications and
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611101936/http://www.orcid.org/">ORCID</ext-link>
as unique author identifier), that we develop standards for reporting
scientific achievements (e.g. using the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611101936/http://www.nsf.gov/bfa/dias/policy/rppr/">Research
Performance Progress Report</ext-link> format), and that we open up and
connect the various tools and databases that collect scientific output.
She cites the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611101936/http://lattes.cnpq.br/english/index.htm">Lattes</ext-link>
database for Brasilian researchers as a successful example for
systematically collecting scientific output. Another example given is
the ongoing
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611101936/http://nrc59.nas.edu/star_info2.cfm">STAR
METRICS</ext-link> project which measures the impact of federally funded
research on economic, scientific and social outcomes.</p>
<p>The article emphasizes that is not enough to think about how to best
collect and report scientific output, but that it is equally important
to understand what these data mean and how to use them, and this may
differ from field to field. Knowledge creation is complex and measuring
this can not be reduced to counting scientific papers and the number of
times they are cited. Social scientists and economists should be
involved in this step. Julia Lane suggests an international platform
supported by funding agencies in which ideas and potential solutions for
science metrics can be discussed.</p>
<fig>
  <caption><p>Flickr photo by jepoirrier.</p></caption>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611101936im_/http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3406/3592693331_ae8822f91d_d.jpg" xlink:title="" />
</fig>
<p>The article contains a lot of food for thought and has already
collected some insightful
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611101936/http://www.nature.com/nature/journal/v464/n7288/full/464488a.html#comments">comments</ext-link>.
In perfect timing, <italic><italic>Nature</italic></italic> this week
not only made
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611101936/http://www.nature.com/press_releases/naturenews.html">Nature
News available without a subscription</ext-link>, but also
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611101936/http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/464466a">added
commenting to all their articles</ext-link>. I would like to add some
thoughts on topics that were not covered because of space constraints
and different perspective.</p>
<sec id="what-are-the-standard-identifiers-for-research-output">
  <title><bold><bold>What are the standard identifiers for research
  output?</bold></bold></title>
  <p>Using standard identifiers for research output is an essential
  first step, and the standard identifier for scientific papers is the
  DOI. So why is it that PubMed (the most important database for
  biomedical articles, published by the U.S. National Institutes of
  Health) still uses their own PMID and doesn't display the DOI in their
  abstract and summary views? And where is the DOI in abstracts,
  full-text HTML or PDF of articles published in the New England Journal
  of Medicine, to take just one popular medical journal as an example?
  Both PubMed and the NEJM obviously use the DOI, but why do they make
  it so difficult for others?</p>
  <p>The unique author identifier
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611101936/http://www.orcid.org/">ORCID</ext-link>
  was mentioned in the article (disclaimer: I am a member of the ORCID
  technical working group). There are many other initiatives for
  uniquely identifying researchers, most of them older than
  <bold><bold>ORCID</bold></bold> which was started in November 2009.
  But is very important that we can agree on a single author identifier
  that is supported by researchers, institutions, journals and funding
  organizations. <bold><bold>ORCID</bold></bold> already has support
  from a growing list of
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611101936/http://www.orcid.org/gallery.php">ORCID
  members</ext-link> and is our best chance for a widely supported and
  open unique author identifier. But this list of
  <bold><bold>ORCID</bold></bold> members is very short on funding
  organizations (with notable exceptions such as the
  <bold><bold>Wellcome Trust</bold></bold> and
  <bold><bold>EMBO</bold></bold>). What is holding them back, and that
  includes the <bold><bold>National Science Foundation</bold></bold>
  (where Julia Lane works) and the U.S. <bold><bold>National Institutes
  of Health (NIH)</bold></bold>?</p>
  <p>Persistent identifiers are essential to attribute, cite and share
  primary research data sets. We have a long tradition for this with
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611101936/http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Genbank/">sequence
  data</ext-link>, and there is growing demand in other research areas,
  especially when huge amounts of data are collected (one example is
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611101936/http://www.pangaea.de/about/">PANGEA</ext-link>
  for earth system research).
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611101936/http://www.datacite.org/">DataCite</ext-link>
  is a new initiative that aims to improve the scholarly infrastructure
  around datasets, and to <italic><italic>increase acceptance of
  research data as legitimate, citable contributions to the scientific
  record</italic></italic>.</p>
  <p>With the focus on research papers, we forget that we do not have
  standard identifiers for many aspects of scientific activity,
  including</p>
  <list list-type="bullet">
    <list-item>
      <p>research grants</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>principal investigator in clinical trials</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>scientific prizes and awards</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>invited lectures</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>curation of scientific databases</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>mentoring of students</p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
</sec>
<sec id="how-do-we-measure-scientific-output">
  <title>How do we measure scientific output?</title>
  <p>Citations are the traditional way to measure the impact of a
  scientific paper. Some of the problems with this approach are
  well-known and were for example highlighted in a 2007 editorial in the
  <italic><italic>Journal of Cell Biology</italic></italic>
  (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611101936/http://dx.doi.org/10.1083/jcb.200711140">Show
  me the data</ext-link>). We need a metric that is open and not
  proprietary, and that measures the citations of an individual paper
  and not the journal as a whole. We should also not forget that the
  number of citations can't be compared between different fields.</p>
  <p>A 2009 analysis by the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611101936/http://www.mesur.org/">MESUR</ext-link>
  project indicates that scientific impact of a paper can not be
  measured by any single indicator
  (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611101936/http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0006022">A
  Principal Component Analysis of 39 Scientific Impact
  Measures</ext-link>). Alternatives to citations are usage statistics
  such as HTML page views and PDF downloads, popularity in social
  bookmarking sites, coverage in blog posts, and comments to articles.
  The <italic><italic>PLoS</italic></italic>
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611101936/http://article-level-metrics.plos.org/">article
  level metrics</ext-link> introduced in September 2009 combine these
  different metrics, and make the data openly available.</p>
  <p>How best to measure the other aspects of scientific output is
  largely unknown. It is possible to count the number of research grants
  or the total amount of money awarded, but should we simply count the
  number of submitted research datasets, invited lectures, science blog
  posts, etc., or do we need some quality indicator similar to
  citations?</p>
</sec>
<sec id="why-do-we-need-all-this">
  <title><bold><bold>Why do we need all this?</bold></bold></title>
  <p>Julia Lane emphasizes that we need science metrics to make the
  right decisions about funding and academic positions. And I fully
  agree with her that we need more research by social scientists and
  economists to better understand what these data mean and how best to
  use them. There is a lot of anecdotal evidence that suggests that
  science metrics alone may be poor indicators of future scientific
  achievements, simply because there are too many confounding factors.
  Maybe we also need to find a better term, as metric implies that
  scientific output can be reduced to
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611101936/http://friendfeed.com/jcbradley/18e76233/binfield-article-level-metrics-should-be">one
  or more numbers</ext-link>.</p>
  <p>Another important motivation for improving science metrics, and not
  mentioned in the article, is to reduce the burden on researchers and
  administrators in evaluating research. The proportion of time spent
  doing research vs. time spent applying for funding, submitting
  manuscripts, filling out evaluation forms, doing peer review, etc. has
  become ridiculous for many active scientists. Initiatives such as the
  standardized <bold><bold>Research Performance Progress
  Report</bold></bold> format mentioned in the paper or automated tools
  to created a publication list or CV can reduce this burden. Funding
  organizations are also trying to reduce the burden of evaluating
  research , e.g. by increasing the time of funding from 3 to 5 years,
  reducing the number of papers that can be listed in grant applications
  (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611101936/http://blogs.nature.com/mfenner/2010/03/01/german-research-foundation-says-that-numbers-arent-everything">German
  Research Foundation says that numbers aren't everything</ext-link>),
  or funding
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611101936/http://www.wellcome.ac.uk/Funding/investigator-awards/Implementation/index.htm">investigators
  and not projects</ext-link>.</p>
  <p>Science metrics are not only important for evaluating scientific
  output, they are also great discovery tools, and this may indeed be
  their more important use. Traditional ways of discovering science
  (e.g. keyword searches in bibliographic databases) are increasingly
  superseded by
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611101936/http://blogs.nature.com/mfenner/2010/02/22/there-is-still-so-much-to-learn-in-reference-management">non-traditional
  approaches</ext-link> that use social networking tools for awareness,
  evaluations and popularity measurements of research findings.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="references">
  <title>References</title>
  <p>Lane, J. (2010). Let's make science metrics more scientific
  <italic>Nature, 464</italic> (7288), 488-489
  https://doi.org/<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611101936/http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/464488a">10.1038/464488a</ext-link></p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
