<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Mutation, selection and metastasis</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2009-02-14">
<day>14</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2009</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<fig>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003091150im_/http://citizenship.typepad.com/blogfordarwin/DarwinBadge.gif" xlink:title="" />
</fig>
<p>Mutation and selection are important concepts in cancer biology. One
well-known example is hereditary colon cancer. Patients with mutations
in the DNA mismatch repair genes <italic><italic>MLH1</italic></italic>
or <italic><italic>MSH2</italic></italic> develop colon cancer because
of an increased rate of mutations. And tumors in patients with familial
polyposis coli have a growth advantage because of a mutation in the
tumor suppressor gene APC. Mutations and selection also help to explain
the process of metastasis, the formation of secondary tumor foci at
distant sites in the body. Understanding metastasis is important,
because it is often this spread of the tumor that makes a previously
localized cancer an incurable disease.</p>
<p>In 1977 a landmark paper in <italic><italic>Science</italic></italic>
by Isaiah Fidler and Margaret Kripke (Fidler 1977) described a mouse
model of lung metastasis using the syngeneic B16 mouse melanoma cell
line. This melanoma cell line originated spontaneously in a C57BL/6
mouse in 1954 and is known to metastasize to the lung. They produced
several clones of the B16 cells, each clone originating from a single
cell and therefore genetically identical. Cells from these clones were
then injected into the tail vein of C57BL/6 mice. The number of lung
metastases in these mice varied dramatically between clones and was also
different from the parental cell line. Fidler and Kripke concluded that
a subpopulation of highly metastatic cells preexists in the parent
population and is selected during the metastatic process.</p>
<p>In 1994 I started to work on a research project that tried to
identify molecules responsible for the selection process in this B16
lung metastasis model. This was before microarrays and the sequencing of
the mouse genome, and we used a technique called differential display to
identify differentially expressed genes in two variant B16 cell lines
that created low and high numbers of lung metastases. We identified a
novel gene that turned out to be a transcriptional regulator (Shioda
1996) but probably is not that critical for the metastatic process.</p>
<p>In 2009 we have learned a lot more about the metastatic process, but
we still know much more about genes involved in tumor cell
proliferation, apoptosis, etc. than the genes critical for the
metastatic process. And we still have not come up with a clever way to
specifically treat that malignant subpopulation of tumor cells that will
later produce metastatic disease.</p>
<sec id="references">
  <title>References</title>
  <p>Fidler, I., &amp; Kripke, M. (1977). Metastasis results from
  preexisting variant cells within a malignant tumor. Science,
  197(4306), 893–895.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1126/science.887927">https://doi.org/10.1126/science.887927</ext-link></p>
  <p>Shioda, T., Fenner, M. H., &amp; Isselbacher, K. J. (1996). msg1, a
  novel melanocyte-specific gene, encodes a nuclear protein and is
  associated with pigmentation. Proceedings of the National Academy of
  Sciences, 93(22), 12298–12303.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.93.22.12298">https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.93.22.12298</ext-link></p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
