<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Nature Communications: Interview with Lesley
Anson</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2009-11-26">
<day>26</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2009</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170507030644/http://www.nature.com/ncomms/about_journal.html">Nature
Communications</ext-link> is a new journal that will launch in Spring
2010. The journal will publish papers in all areas of the physical,
chemical and biological sciences and is open for submissions.</p>
<p>The Nature Publishing Group publishes one fully open access journal
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170507030644/http://www.nature.com/msb/index.html">Molecular
Systems Biology</ext-link>) and
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170507030644/http://www.nature.com/press_releases/greengold.html">more
than ten journals</ext-link> that offer an open access option for
authors (including
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170507030644/http://www.nature.com/emboj/index.html">EMBO
Journal</ext-link>). <italic>Nature Communications</italic> will be the
first Nature journal with an open access option for authors.
<italic>Nature Communications</italic> papers where the author has not
opted for open access will be available through an institutional
subscription, or by purchasing an individual article.</p>
<p>There are many good arguments for open access, but from a journal
perspective the publishing model must make business sense. Most open
access journals use the author-pays model, and
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170507030644/http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nmat2497">an
editorial in the August 2009 issue</ext-link> of Nature Materials talked
about some of the difficulties of this publishing model for the Nature
journals – the costs that are currently spread among many subscribers
would be prohibitely high for an author-pays option. Some high-profile
open access journals have article publication charges that are probably
not covering all costs (e.g.
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170507030644/http://www.plosbiology.org/home.action">PLoS
Biology</ext-link>) or use a different business model that doesn't
require article publication charges
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170507030644/http://www.bmj.com/">BMJ</ext-link>).
<italic>Nature Communications</italic> will have an
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170507030644/http://www.nature.com/ncomms/open_access/index.html">article
publication charge of $5000</ext-link>, which is higher than what most
journals charge. I interviewed Lesley Anson, the Chief Editor of
<italic>Nature Communications</italic>, to learn more about the
journal.</p>
<sec id="1-can-you-describe-nature-communications-for-me">
  <title>1. Can you describe Nature Communications for me?</title>
  <p><italic>Nature Communications</italic> is the latest journal in
  NPG's portfolio. It is an online-only multidisciplinary journal
  publishing original research papers in all areas of the biological,
  chemical and physical sciences. The published research will be of the
  quality associated with Nature-branded journals, but won't necessarily
  have the high impact or broad appeal of papers published in Nature and
  the Nature research journals. In other words, we expect that papers
  published in <italic>Nature Communications</italic> will be of
  interest and importance to specialists within each field.</p>
  <p>All research papers will be in Article format, regardless of their
  length, and will undergo rigorous, yet efficient, peer review and be
  published rapidly online. Authors of primary research papers can
  choose to make their published article available via subscribed
  access, or open access through the payment of a publication fee.
  <italic>Nature Communications</italic> will also publish occasional
  Reviews and Editorials.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="2-what-will-you-be-doing-differently-from-other-nature-journals">
  <title>2. What will you be doing differently from other Nature
  journals?</title>
  <p>There are a number of differences between <italic>Nature
  Communications</italic> and other Nature-branded journals. For
  example, all other Nature titles publish print issues with regular
  news and comment sections and are available only by subscribed
  access.</p>
  <p>Like other Nature-branded journals, <italic>Nature
  Communications</italic> has an independent team of editors who are
  responsible for maintaining the quality of the published research
  through rigorous peer review. However, <italic>Nature
  Communications</italic> has streamlined the editorial process – by
  limiting presubmission enquiries, appeals and the number of rounds of
  review – in order to secure rapid decisions for authors. The journal
  has also undertaken to publish research papers within 28 days of
  acceptance.</p>
  <p>Another distinctive feature of <italic>Nature
  Communications</italic> is its Editorial Advisory Panel – to be
  announced shortly – which will consist of recognized experts from all
  areas of science. Their collective expertise will support the
  editorial team in ensuring that every field is represented in the
  journal.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="3-is-nature-communications-still-a-journal-in-the-traditional-sense-the-journal-is-online-only-has-no-news-and-views-and-the-articles-will-be-so-specialized-that-most-people-will-probably-find-papers-by-a-database-search-rather-than-by-looking-at-the-table-of-contents-">
  <title>3. Is Nature Communications still a journal in the traditional
  sense? The journal is online only, has no news and views, and the
  articles will be so specialized that most people will probably find
  papers by a database search rather than by looking at the table of
  contents.</title>
  <p>I suppose it depends on your definition of a traditional journal.
  One could argue that we are going back to the roots of learned
  journals by focussing predominantly on primary research. In addition,
  like the traditional Nature-branded journals, <italic>Nature
  Communications</italic> has a defined scope and publishes only
  high-quality research.</p>
  <p>We appreciate, though, that readers are accustomed to browsing
  journals by issue, therefore we are implementing technology to make
  the online browsing experience both intuitive and effective. There
  will be a number of ways for authors to find papers of interest to
  them, including personalization options and an extensive browse by
  subject category.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="4-why-did-you-decide-to-have-a-hybrid-model-of-both-open-access-and-subscribed-access">
  <title>4. Why did you decide to have a hybrid model of both open
  access and subscribed access?</title>
  <p>We consider ourselves fortunate in being able to offer authors the
  choice of publishing with open access as well as subscribed access.
  Increasing support by funders for open access publication has made
  hybrid business models more viable for publishers. Furthermore,
  <italic>Nature Communications</italic> focus on primary research is
  particularly suited to a hybrid model because the cost of
  commissioning, editing and producing secondary content is minimized.
  These factors, and the high rejection rates on Nature and the Nature
  research journals, make open access charges for any other
  Nature-branded journal prohibitively high in the current market.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="5-with-this-hybrid-model-in-place-it-will-be-interesting-to-closely-watch-how-open-access-and-subscribed-access-articles-are-accessed-over-time-">
  <title>5. With this hybrid model in place, it will be interesting to
  closely watch how open access and subscribed access articles are
  accessed over time.</title>
  <p>Yes, it will be interesting to monitor the average view rates for
  open-access versus subscribed access papers and we will be doing this
  following launch.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="6-does-an-author-decide-about-open-vs-subscribed-access-before-or-after-a-paper-is-accepted-for-publication">
  <title>6. Does an author decide about open vs. subscribed access
  before or after a paper is accepted for publication?</title>
  <p>Authors won't have to make a final decision about access to their
  paper until the point at which their paper is accepted. Where authors
  do indicate a preference one way or the other during the editorial
  process, the reviewers will be blind to that choice.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="7-what-percentage-of-articles-do-you-expect-to-be-open-access">
  <title>7. What percentage of articles do you expect to be open
  access?</title>
  <p>We can't predict what the open-access take-up will be like, and we
  are therefore prepared for open access uptake varying from as little
  as 0% to as much as 100%. <italic>Nature Communications</italic>
  business model works at both extremes and all values in between.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="8-how-does-the-transfer-of-a-manuscript-rejected-at-another-nature-journal-work">
  <title>8. How does the transfer of a manuscript rejected at another
  Nature Journal work?</title>
  <p>The process of transferring a manuscript to <italic>Nature
  Communications</italic> is exactly the same as the transfer mechanism
  between the existing Nature-branded journals. Control rests entirely
  with the author, so transfers are only made at the authors request and
  with the understanding that the reviewers' reports from the previous
  journal will be transferred to <italic>Nature
  Communications</italic>.</p>
  <p>Importantly, because all Nature journals are editorially
  independent, authors rejected from another Nature journal can choose
  to submit their paper to <italic>Nature Communications</italic> as a
  new submission. In that case, any submission or peer review details
  will remain confidential to the journal from which the manuscript was
  rejected.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="9-what-are-your-responsibilities-at-nature-communications">
  <title>9. What are your responsibilities at Nature
  Communications?</title>
  <p>I am the Chief Editor of <italic>Nature Communications</italic> ,
  which means I am responsible for the editorial content of the journal.
  I have a team of talented editors to help in the task of selecting
  suitable manuscripts for publication: a biologist, a physicist and a
  chemist. Their profiles are
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170507030644/http://www.nature.com/ncomms/authors/about_eds/index.html">available
  on our website</ext-link>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="10-what-did-you-do-before-starting-to-work-at-nature-communications">
  <title>10. What did you do before starting to work at Nature
  Communications?</title>
  <p>Before taking on the task of launching Nature Communications, I
  spent more than ten years as a manuscript editor at Nature. During
  that time, I handled a number of different areas in the cellular and
  molecular sciences, and was also responsible for the editorial content
  of Nature's
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170507030644/http://www.nature.com/nature/supplements/insights/index.html">Insight
  Programme</ext-link>. Before joining Nature I trained as a
  biophysicist at the University of Bristol and University College
  London.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="11-what-are-the-best-places-to-find-out-more-about-nature-communications">
  <title>11. What are the best places to find out more about Nature
  Communications?</title>
  <p>For more information about <italic>Nature Communications</italic>,
  including the journal's Aims and Scope, biographies of the editors and
  how to submit, please visit
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170507030644/http://www.nature.com/naturecommunications">our
  website</ext-link>. Any questions can be directed to our
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170507030644/http://network.nature.com/groups/naturecommunications/forum/topics">dedicated
  forum</ext-link> on Nature Network, or sent directly to the editorial
  team by e-mailing
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170507030644/mailto:natcomms%40nature.com">natcomms@nature.com</ext-link>.
  We look forward to hearing from you!</p>
  <p><italic>For further information, please also read the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170507030644/http://blogs.nature.com/nautilus/2009/10/nature">announcement</ext-link></italic>
  on the <italic>Nautilus</italic> blog and the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170507030644/http://blog.openwetware.org/scienceintheopen/2009/11/16/nature-communications-qa/">Nature
  Communications Q&amp;A</ext-link> with Grace Baynes on the
  <italic>Science in the open</italic> blog._</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
