<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>New in PLoS ONE: Citation rates of self-selected vs.
mandated Open Access</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2010-10-18">
<day>18</day>
<month>10</month>
<year>2010</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p><italic><italic>PLoS ONE</italic></italic> today published a paper
very relevant to
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20101114042817/http://www.openaccessweek.org/">Open
Access Week</ext-link> (which started today):</p>
<p><bold><bold>Gargouri Y, Hajjem C, Larivière V, Gingras Y, Carr L,
Brody T, Harnad S</bold></bold>. Self-Selected or Mandated, Open Access
Increases Citation Impact for Higher Quality Research.
<italic><italic>PLoS ONE</italic></italic>. 2010;5(10):e13636+.
doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20101114042817/http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0013636">10.1371/journal.pone.0013636</ext-link>.</p>
<p>The paper studied the citation rates of papers from four institutions
with the longest-standing self-archiving mandate:
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20101114042817/http://www.soton.ac.uk/">Southampton
University</ext-link>,
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20101114042817/http://public.web.cern.ch/public/">CERN</ext-link>,
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20101114042817/http://www.qut.edu.au/">Queensland
University of Technology</ext-link> and
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20101114042817/http://www.uminho.pt/Default.aspx?lang=en-US">Minho
University</ext-link>. The mandates (instituted between 2002 and 2004)
increased the rate of self-archiving in the respective institutional
repositories from around 15% to 60%:</p>
<fig>
  <caption><p><italic><italic>Fig 1. Open Access Self-archiving
  percentages for institutions with self-archiving mandates compared to
  non-mandated, self-selected controls.
  doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20101114042817/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2010/10/18/new-in-plos-one-citation-rates-of-self-selected-vs-mandated-open-access/10.1371/journal.pone.00136363.g001">10.1371/journal.pone.00136363.g001</ext-link></italic></italic></p></caption>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20101114042817im_/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/files/2010/10/journal.pone_.0013636.g001.png" xlink:title="journal.pone.0013636.g001" />
</fig>
<p>The authors then compared the citation rates of self-archived papers
from the four institutions published in non-Open Access (OA) journals
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20101114042817/http://www.sherpa.ac.uk/romeoinfo.html">mandated
OA</ext-link>) to matched papers from the same non-OA journal, volume
and year (non-OA). 15% of the latter papers were also available from
repositories (self-selected OA). Overall the study examined the
citations of 27,197 papers from 1,984 non-OA journals. The study also
looked at the influence of other factors that affect citation rates,
e.g. article age, journal impact factor or number of references.</p>
<p>The main results of the study are that OA articles are cited more
frequently than non-OA articles and that there is no difference in
citation rates between mandated and self-archived articles. The authors
conclude that OA articles are cited more often not because of
self-selection (articles with higher impact more likely become OA), but
because of readers cite OA articles more often.</p>
<p>The study is an effort to better understand if and why OA papers are
cited more often, the so-called OA Advantage. Unfortunately I feel that
the paper comes a little short. Yes, they did a very detailed analysis
of the citation behavior, and take into account important cofactors. But
the reader is left with the impression that mandatory self-archiving of
post-prints in institutional repositories is the only reasonable Open
Access strategy, and the introduction and discussion accordingly leave
out some important arguments.</p>
<p>The authors fail to mention that not all studies show a citation
advantage for OA articles (e.g. the randomized controlled trial by
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20101114042817/http://dx.doi.org/10.1136/bmj.a568">Davis
PM et al. 2008</ext-link>), and they only look at self-archiving in
institutional repositories (green OA). Not only are there important
disclipline-specific repositories such as PubMed Central and ArXiv, but
of course also OA journals such as <italic><italic>PLoS
ONE</italic></italic> that published the study (gold OA). And the study
only discussed archiving of articles after peer review, even though
archiving of preprints is a popular strategy in high-energy physics and
related disciplines (and here the self-archiving rate is close to 100%).
I also don’t see a discussion of why the self-archiving rate of
post-prints in institutions with a mandate is 60% and not close to 100%.
And what is wrong if archiving rates are only around 15% if it is left
to the researchers to decide? Finally, there are many reasons other than
citation rates that make OA worthwhile, including access to the
literature for those not working in academic institutions (and maybe
never citing a paper), and work that uses the OA literature in new and
exciting ways that go beyond citations. For me personally, the OA
advantage is much more in these two aspects than in the citation rates
of papers.</p>
<p>For me Open Access week is an opportunity to celebrate what has been
achieved over the years. But it is equally important to look at the road
ahead. There is no “one size fits all” solution for Open Access, and we
shouldn’t look away from the things that aren’t working, and the
solutions that haven’t been found yet.</p>
<sec id="references">
  <title>References</title>
  <p>Gargouri, Y., Hajjem, C., Larivière, V., Gingras, Y., Carr, L.,
  Brody, T., &amp; Harnad, S. (2010). Self-Selected or Mandated, Open
  Access Increases Citation Impact for Higher Quality Research
  <italic>PLoS ONE, 5</italic> (10)
  https://doi.org/<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20101114042817/http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0013636">10.1371/journal.pone.0013636</ext-link></p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
