<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Nobel blogging?</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2008-07-12">
<day>12</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2008</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Last night we had the first in a series of
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611091423/http://network.nature.com/group/berlin">Nature
Network Berlin</ext-link> dinners scheduled around the International
Congress of Genetics. It was a very entertaining evening, not least
because of our special guests
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611091423/http://www.pathology.unc.edu/common/smithies.htm">Oliver
Smithies</ext-link>,
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611091423/http://capecchi.genetics.utah.edu/">Mario
Capecchi</ext-link> (both 2007 Nobel laureates) and Matt Brown
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611091423/http://network.nature.com/london/news/blog/matt/2008/07/10/medley-of-medals-for-london-scientists">Nature
Network London Editor of the Year</ext-link>). Just one of the many
stories was by Oliver Smithies, who told us how he constructed a PCR
machine after listening to a talk by G. Mullis – way before commercial
Taq polymerase and PCR machines. And that machine is still running.</p>
<p>You could argue that surprisingly few people showed up for this
event, including only four PhD students. But I don't worry too much
about this, because increasing the awareness for these events takes
time. But I wonder whether we could do better to disseminate the
knowledge and life experience of these accomplished scientists. Time and
travel costs allow only relatively few people to listen to keynote
lectures or take part in a networking dinner.</p>
<p>The solution is obvious: we have to convince our Nobel laureates to
become science bloggers. In many ways they are the perfect bloggers.
Most of them probably don't know yet about science blogging, and some of
them will need help with the technology. And perhaps only a few will be
interested. But with a little help this could turn out very well. And we
would have good company for
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611091423/http://network.nature.com/profile/charlesdarwin">Charles
Darwin</ext-link>.</p>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
