<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>OAI-PMH: Interview with Tony Hammond</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2009-05-25">
<day>25</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2009</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Most of us find, store and sometimes read scientific papers
electronically. Although abstracts and full-text papers are usually
available as web pages in HTML format, PDF is clearly the preferred
format for storing and printing papers.</p>
<p>But publishing scientific papers in electronic form obviously
requires more than providing the content in HTML or PDF format. We want
to find the papers we are interested in on the journal homepage or in a
digital library (e.g.
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003101404/http://www.pubmed.gov/">PubMed</ext-link>),
and for this we need metadata about the paper. The metadata could simply
be an digital object identifier
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003101404/http://www.doi.org/">DOI</ext-link>),
but the metadata could also contain important information required to
find a paper in a search strategy (e.g. authors, title, publication date
or keywords).</p>
<p>As
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003101404/http://network.nature.com/people/duncan/profile">Duncan
Hull</ext-link> <italic><italic>et al.</italic></italic> noted in a
<italic><italic>PLoS Computational Biology</italic></italic> paper last
year
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003101404/http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000204">Defrosting
the digital library: bibliographic tools for the next generation
web</ext-link>), metadata are often disconnected from the data, and
there are no universally agreed standards to represent these
metadata.</p>
<p>But why should we as scientists care about the technologies used to
publish and distribute a paper? We shouldn't forget that these
technologies could allow new and innovative ways to find and read
scientific papers. One simple example: storing the metadata in the PDF
file (using
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003101404/http://blogs.nature.com/wp/nascent/2008/12/xmp_labelling_for_nature.html">XMP</ext-link>)
could make it much easier to import a large collection of PDF files into
a reference manager.</p>
<p>One such initiative to provide the metadata of a scientific paper is
OAI-PMH. I asked Tony Hammond from Nature.com a few questions about this
newly supported protocol, as well as some more general questions about
metadata provided by the Nature Publishing Group journals.</p>
<sec id="1-can-you-describe-what-oai-pmh-is-and-does">
  <title>1. Can you describe what OAI-PMH is and does?</title>
  <p>Well, we'll first need to unpack that double acronym. OAI-PMH is
  the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003101404/http://www.openarchives.org/pmh/">Protocol
  for Metadata Harvesting</ext-link> which comes from the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003101404/http://www.openarchives.org/">Open
  Archives Initiative</ext-link>. It's traditionally been known simply
  as OAI, although these days it's more properly referred to in full as
  OAI-PMH in view of the arrival of a new sibling protocol: OAI-ORE,
  which stands for
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003101404/http://www.openarchives.org/ore/">Object
  Reuse and Exchange</ext-link>. The two protocols are complementary:
  OAI-PMH deals with metadata harvesting, while OAI-ORE is concerned
  with content aggregation and compound digital objects.</p>
  <p>In brief, OAI-PMH provides an interoperability framework for
  networked repositories to exchange metadata records on their holdings.
  Such metadata typically includes bibliographic-type descriptions of
  repository items, such as title, authors and other identifying
  information. At a technical level OAI-PMH provides a very simple
  Web-based API for querying a repository by item, by set of items or by
  date range with data records being returned in an XML format which can
  be validated by a W3C XML Schema. A basic metadata format using
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003101404/http://dublincore.org/">Dublin
  Core</ext-link> is available from all OAI-PMH implementations, while
  other richer community-specific metadata formats are encouraged for a
  fuller semantic exchange.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="2-what-is-prism-aggregator-message-pam-">
  <title>2. What is PRISM Aggregator Message (PAM)?</title>
  <p>I posted an entry
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003101404/http://www.crossref.org/CrossTech/2009/05/post_2.html">PRISM
  Aggregator Message</ext-link> on CrossTech recently which delved into
  the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003101404/http://www.idealliance.org/industry_resources/intelligent_content_informed_workflow/about_the_prism_aggregator_message">PRISM
  Aggregator Message</ext-link> (PAM) format and provided some specific
  details and also reasons why we chose to use it. Basically our choice
  of PAM stems from our earlier work with RSS and
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003101404/http://prismstandard.org/">PRISM</ext-link>.</p>
  <p>Our first foray into semantic descriptions was with RSS feeds.
  While still at Elsevier I had collaborated with Timo Hannay and Ben
  Lund at Nature Publishing Group and wrote up a piece for
  <italic><italic>XML.com</italic></italic> entitled
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003101404/http://www.xml.com/lpt/a/1252">Why
  Choose RSS 1.0?</ext-link> which described how journal RSS feeds could
  be enhanced with PRISM metadata. Specifically that piece reviewed the
  different RSS strains and came out strongly in favour of RSS 1.0 which
  being an RDF application was truly extensible and could accommodate
  new vocabularies. The identification of PRISM as a useful vocabulary
  was largely based on noting the adjacency of two RDF use cases in an
  early edition of the W3C RDF Primer: RSS and PRISM. I had been reading
  up on RSS and RDF and I suddenly thought “Bingo!”, we can add in PRISM
  terms to the RSS feeds since PRISM is a very handy supplement to
  Dublin Core and provides support for enumerated fields such as volume,
  issue, and page number. Another advantage for publishers was that
  PRISM is a simple term set and did not require any specialist library
  knowledge. A later paper by the same authors
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003101404/http://www.dlib.org/dlib/december04/hammond/12hammond.html">The
  Role of RSS in Science Publishing</ext-link> published with
  <italic><italic>D-Lib Magazine</italic></italic> made a more in-depth
  review of RSS in scholarly publishing and concluded again that RSS 1.0
  with its transparent support for new vocabularies such as PRISM was
  the right way to go.</p>
  <p>We wanted to provide this standard article description that we were
  shipping with RSS also with OAI-PMH records. Unfortunately we could
  not simply move over the RDF properties into an OAI-PMH delivered
  RDF/XML payload. The problem with OAI-PMH is that it requires a record
  to be constrained by a W3C XML Schema. This is where
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003101404/http://www.idealliance.org/industry_resources/intelligent_content_informed_workflow/about_the_prism_aggregator_message">PRISM
  Aggregator Message</ext-link> (PAM) comes in.</p>
  <p>PAM is an application of PRISM and defines a W3C XML Schema for XML
  content aggregators to use. The message is simply structured as a
  sequence of one or more articles each with a body section for XHTML
  content and a head section with PRISM metadata. The body sections are
  optional so PAM can be used exclusively as a simple metadata packaging
  format as we have chosen to implement for OAI-PMH.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="3-how-does-pam-relate-to-the-nlm-dtd">
  <title>3. How does PAM relate to the NLM DTD?</title>
  <p>Well, both are schemas for content. This was my blind spot with
  regard to PAM for many years. Our focus was on metadata exchange.
  PRISM was a vocabulary for metadata, or rather a set of closely
  related vocabularies. No problem. And yet there was this thing called
  PAM which was busying itself with content. And we had no interest in
  that as we had our own Nature-specific DTD. But the PRISM folks were
  very enthusiastic – so clearly there was a need.</p>
  <p>It only dawned on me relatively slowly that the PAM DTD (also
  available in W3C XML Schema form since PRISM 2.0) was the
  correspondent of the NLM DTD in the scholarly world. It provides an
  interchange format for content elements. So the real impetus behind
  the development of the PRISM metadata vocabularies was as a direct
  support to XML content exchange although content is not actually
  required to be present and the metadata alone can be used in different
  applications.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="4-what-are-typical-use-cases-for-oai-pmh">
  <title>4. What are typical use cases for OAI-PMH?</title>
  <p>The main use of OAI-PMH is to sync, or perhaps a better term would
  be align, the holdings descriptions of digital repository collections,
  where the word “repository” should be understood in its broadest
  context. The protocol exposes a machine interface for the robot
  harvesting of records from a data provider which a service provider
  will build upon to provide value add services. But this machine
  interface can sometimes also be accessed through a user interface
  (such as that provided by the Nature OAI-PMH service) which adds a
  browser onto the repository records.</p>
  <p>For additional uses of OAI-PMH a good start point is the paper by
  Herbert Van de Sompel, Jeff Young and Thom Hickey in
  <italic><italic>D-Lib Magazine</italic></italic> on
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003101404/http://www.dlib.org/dlib/july03/young/07young.html">Using
  the OAI-PMH … Differently</ext-link>. This paper notes that the
  metadata formats used by OAI-PMH are any that can validated by a W3C
  XML Schema and that therefore OAI-PMH is nothing less than “a medium
  for incremental, date-sensitive exchange of any form of
  semi-structured data”. OAI-PMH clearly has legs.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="5-why-should-researchers-care-about-oai-pmh">
  <title>5. Why should researchers care about OAI-PMH?</title>
  <p>I'm not sure that researchers should want to have any specific
  knowledge of OAI-PMH. Bear in mind that at heart this is an
  infrastructural technology which exists down in the data pipes and
  service conduits and is analogous to the fibre or radio channels that
  deliver broadband services to users.</p>
  <p>Applications that make use of the syndicated metadata records that
  OAI-PMH provides for, however, are another matter. Those are very
  definitely things that researchers will care much about. It is
  difficult to distil those consumer applications into any specific
  categories as the services platform that OAI-PMH supports is very
  broad, ranging from general to domain-specific descriptions to full
  text records, and beyond.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="6-what-are-the-different-data-formats-that-descriptions-of-nature-com-articles-are-provided-how-do-they-differ">
  <title>6. What are the different data formats that descriptions of
  Nature.com articles are provided? How do they differ?</title>
  <p>At Nature Publishing Group we are working towards a common delivery
  architecture for our metadata. We are defining a core set of
  properties and making descriptions built from that property set
  available across multiple channels. Currently we are focussing on the
  basic bibliographic record which supports reference linking so that
  links can be made back to the platform. But once the channels are
  established they can be readily amplified to carry additional
  properties using the various channels' native packaging mechanisms.
  Metadata channels include both standalone services (e.g. RSS, OAI-PMH,
  etc.) as well as content objects themselves (HTML, PDF, etc.).</p>
  <p>On the services side we began almost six years ago with RSS feeds,
  which being RSS 1.0 are full RDF/XML documents. The open data model
  implicit in RDF means that we can readily add new properties into our
  feeds. A case in point is the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003101404/http://www.iupac.org/inchi/">InChI</ext-link>
  identifier for chemical substances which we are currently working
  towards adding into our RSS feeds for <italic><italic>Nature
  Chemistry</italic></italic>, similarly to what the Royal Society of
  Chemistry has done earlier with their
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003101404/http://www.rsc.org/Publishing/Journals/ProjectProspect/index.asp">Project
  Prospect</ext-link>.</p>
  <p>We have just released our OAI-PMH service which provides the same
  basic property set as RSS but in PAM format – see the post
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003101404/http://blogs.nature.com/wp/nascent/2009/05/a_catalog_for_naturecom.html">A
  Catalog for Nature.com</ext-link>. As alluded to above OAI-PMH comes
  from an earlier generation of protocols that put more rather emphasis
  on validation (or packaging the elements) than on data modelling (or
  relating the elements). That is, while the records served by the
  OAI-PMH server are validatable using W3C XML Schema the properties
  they contain are not directly reusable within an open,
  cross-application context such as is provided for by RDF. We do though
  have a simple stylesheet that can generate RDF/XML from these OAI-PMH
  records.</p>
  <p>On the content side we added in the same properties to our HTML
  using META tags a year ago now – see the post
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003101404/http://blogs.nature.com/wp/nascent/2008/05/naturecom_adds_metadata.html">Nature.com
  adds metadata</ext-link>. These properties are easily extractable by
  tools as simple key/value pairs. While this metadata is not directly
  representable as RDF it can be readily generated. We are anyway moving
  to make this property set more accessible by adding in
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003101404/http://googlewebmastercentral.blogspot.com/2009/05/introducing-rich-snippets.html">RDFa</ext-link>
  which has now gone mainstream following Google's recent
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003101404/http://googlewebmastercentral.blogspot.com/2009/05/introducing-rich-snippets.html">announcement
  of rich snippets</ext-link> and their
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003101404/http://google.com/support/webmasters/bin/answer.py?hl=en&amp;answer=146898">support
  for RDFa</ext-link>.</p>
  <p>We also began at the end of that year a programme to embed
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003101404/http://www.adobe.com/products/xmp/">XMP</ext-link>
  packets into all of our newly published PDF files, again using the
  same basic property set – see the post
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003101404/http://blogs.nature.com/wp/nascent/2008/12/xmp_labelling_for_nature.html">XMP
  Labelling for Nature</ext-link>. The XMP packets are essentially
  simple RDF/XML documents.</p>
  <p>You can begin to see where all this is going. We are aiming to make
  all our descriptions conformant to a common data model, i.e. to RDF.
  That way, regardless of the distribution channel used the data
  delivered down that pipe can be merged into the common semantic
  graph.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="7-what-tools-can-researchers-use-to-retrieve-these-descriptions">
  <title>7. What tools can researchers use to retrieve these
  descriptions?</title>
  <p>Many of these channels are amenable to repurposing. The metadata
  they carry can be consumed within application-specific contexts, or it
  can be extracted from the channel medium for use in a wider generic
  context. Consider, for example, an RSS feed which can be used directly
  by a desktop or Web-based RSS reader. But it can also be mined for its
  metadata content, trivially in this case since the medium is already
  RDF/XML. Or consider again the metadata within an XMP packet in a PDF
  document which can be read by a viewer application (e.g. Adobe
  Acrobat) and presented to the user in a “Document Properties” display.
  But it can also be extracted simply by locating the XMP packet and
  reading the single XML child element which is itself a full RDF/XML
  document.</p>
  <p>So one could say there are two classes of tools, those that operate
  at an application or specific layer and those that operate at a more
  generic layer, albeit with some preprocessing steps to unpack the
  metadata.</p>
  <p>I should really expand here on OAI-PMH specifically since this is
  new for us. The primary means of interacting with an OAI-PMH server is
  via its service endpoint. Obviously to manage pagination seamlessly
  (the resumption token provides a cursor into the result record set) a
  library or tool is of enormous assistance. The OAI website provides a
  reasonably full
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003101404/http://www.openarchives.org/pmh/tools/tools.php">listing
  of PMH tools</ext-link> available.</p>
  <p>Our OAI-PMH server implements Jeff Young's
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003101404/http://www.oclc.org/research/software/oai/cat.htm">OAICat</ext-link>
  which is a Java servlet webapp providing a repository framework which
  also comes with a
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003101404/http://www.nature.com/oai/">forms
  interface</ext-link> for testing. This interface is especially useful
  for occasional use, e.g. a single
  “<italic><italic>GetRecord</italic></italic>“:http://www.nature.com/oai/html/getRecord.html
  or call to
  “<italic><italic>ListRecords</italic></italic>“:http://www.nature.com/oai/html/listRecords.html
  (or
  “<italic><italic>ListIdentifiers</italic></italic>“:http://www.nature.com/oai/html/listIdentifiers.html),
  although repetitive calls to
  <italic><italic>ListRecords</italic></italic> (or
  <italic><italic>ListIdentifiers</italic></italic>) would quickly
  become tedious.</p>
  <p>For harvesting we have used for testing purposes the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003101404/http://oai.rubyforge.org/">ruby-oai</ext-link>
  gem for Ruby by Ed Summers and Will Groppe which includes a library
  and simple client which can also be run interactively as a shell. Note
  that this gem is not listed on the OAI-PMH tools page.</p>
  <p>We have also made use of the open-source Java client
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003101404/http://www.oclc.org/research/software/oai/harvester2.htm">OAIHarvester2</ext-link>,
  again by Jeff Young of OCLC. We used this for test harvesting of our
  full record collection as it was a robust implementation and we had
  earlier run into some problems with the Ruby app as it is not as
  finished as it might be, although it remains very configurable and
  easy to use. Our intention is to proceed with the Ruby app for
  incremental harvesting. We're aiming to become consumers of our own
  services for quality control purposes.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="8-what-are-your-responsibilities-at-nature-com">
  <title>8. What are your responsibilities at Nature.com?</title>
  <p>I work within the Platform Technologies group on infrastructural
  projects supporting discovery and access across the nature.com
  platform, especially those that are built upon open technologies. My
  job handle is <italic><italic>Application Architect</italic></italic>
  although we're working on deconstructing that. I don't have line
  responsibilities but do supervise the development of our new
  interfaces.</p>
  <p>We are corralling these various standards – some come from the
  wider Web world, some from the digital library community, some come
  from industry, and some are closer to home – under the general moniker
  of
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003101404/http://www.nature.com/libraries/public_interfaces/index.html">Public
  Interfaces</ext-link>. We also have a new documentation centre for
  this which is located on our
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003101404/http://www.nature.com/libraries/index.html">Librarian
  Gateway</ext-link>.</p>
  <p>I do maintain an active presence with various external bodies, not
  unsurprisingly given that the focus of my work is on defining and
  building interfaces. I have been from the beginning very involved in
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003101404/http://www.crossref.org/">CrossRef</ext-link>
  and the development of
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003101404/http://www.doi.org/">DOI</ext-link>
  and related technologies. Most recently I have worked with a CrossRef
  WG to draw up a best practices document for scholarly publishers and
  RSS, and we are now starting work on a companion document for
  embedding metadata. I am also on the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003101404/http://www.idealliance.org/industry_resources/intelligent_content_informed_workflow/prism/membership">PRISM
  WG</ext-link> and a regular contributor.</p>
  <p>Other activities I'm involved with include being a member of the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003101404/http://www.loc.gov/standards/sru/">SRU</ext-link>
  Editorial Board and of the eJournal Joint Technical Panel on
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003101404/http://www.bl.uk/aboutus/stratpolprog/legaldep/">Legal
  Deposit</ext-link> here in the UK. I have previously been a member of
  the OpenURL Standard Committe that developed
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003101404/http://www.niso.org/standards/z39-88-2004/">ANSI/NISO
  Z39.88</ext-link>, and worked as a member of the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003101404/http://www.openarchives.org/ore/">OAI-ORE</ext-link>
  TC and the JISC
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003101404/http://www.jisc.ac.uk/aboutus/committees/workinggroups/palsmetadatagroup.aspx">PALS
  Metadata and Interoperability WG</ext-link>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="9-what-did-you-do-before-starting-to-work-for-nature-com">
  <title>9. What did you do before starting to work for
  Nature.com?</title>
  <p>Before working with Nature I was with Elsevier (2001-2004) as part
  of their Advanced Technology Group, and prior to that I worked with
  Academic Press (1997-2001) as Head of the Online Resource Activity.
  With Academic Press I was part of Electronic Publishing team that
  managed IDEAL – one of the first successful large journals platforms
  that applied consortial site licenses.</p>
  <p>My previous experiences included a long-ish stint (1986-1995) with
  NATO SACLANTCEN in La Spezia, Italy, as Scientific Editor and
  subsequently as Head of the Information Branch. The facility was named
  SACLANT ASW Research Centre when I joined and had been transmuted into
  NATO Undersea Research Centre by the time I left (the anti-submarine
  warfare aspect deftly tidied away). Same mission though, to work on
  basic research (from oceanography to operational research) that would
  aid the NATO nations in their submarine detection programmes. (It now
  seems to be commuted to NURC alone.)</p>
  <p>Prior to that I worked (1982-1985) as Assistant to the Editors for
  the North-Holland Publishing Company journal <italic><italic>Nuclear
  Physics A</italic></italic> based in Copenhagen, Denmark, and previous
  to that as a Research Associate in the Space Physics Laboratory at the
  University of Kent at Canterbury, UK where I collaborated in building
  a micrometeoroid sensor experiment which was deployed by the Space
  Shuttle.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="10-do-you-want-to-talk-about-future-plans-for-metadata-at-nature-com">
  <title>10. Do you want to talk about future plans for metadata at
  Nature.com?</title>
  <p>Sure. I guess I should separate out metadata management per se from
  metadata delivery and discovery. As a company we have an active
  programme underway to review wholesale our various ontologies and
  vocabularies in order to coordinate and streamline them. We also have
  ongoing initiatives to add in text mining to our production workflow
  and to address the entity extraction problem. Having better and richer
  vocabularies and new terms is one step. The next step is how to
  communicate that value in an open and structured manner to consumer
  applications.</p>
  <p>My particular focus is on delivery channels. As I mentioned earlier
  we are working towards providing a notion of public interfaces: a set
  of open interfaces for delivering standard object descriptions.
  Complementing the OAI-PMH service which provides a catalog for
  nature.com we are also currently working on an SRU
  (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003101404/http://www.loc.gov/standards/sru/">Search
  and Retrieve by URL</ext-link>) service to support structured
  searching. And that would also be accessible through simple
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003101404/http://www.opensearch.org/">OpenSearch</ext-link>
  conventions.</p>
  <p>We will be extending our page markup to include
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003101404/http://www.w3.org/TR/rdfa-syntax/">RDFa</ext-link>
  which will not only provide metadata in RDF format but will also
  localize those descriptions to the content fragment so that
  cut-and-paste operations will scoop up any descriptive markup along
  with the actual content.</p>
  <p>We are now close to completing our support across our full title
  range for
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003101404/http://www.adobe.com/products/xmp/">XMP</ext-link>
  in PDFs. A related development will be to embed XMP into our images
  (JPEGs and GIFs) so that all of our main resources then become
  self-describing. It is a wonder that we have gotten thus far in online
  publishing sending out content entities which are not unambiguously
  labelled.</p>
  <p>And beyond this all lie the promises and challenges of the Semantic
  Web.</p>
  <fig>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003101404im_/http://www.linkwithin.com/pixel.png" xlink:title="" />
  </fig>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
