<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>On Guest authors and Ghostwriters</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2008-04-19">
<day>19</day>
<month>4</month>
<year>2008</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>The legal disputes following the withdrawal from the market of two
drugs for the treatment of pain (the COX-2 inhibitors rofecoxib and
valdecoxib) have led to another critical examination of the paper
publishing process. I have
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611111125/http://network.nature.com/blogs/user/mfenner/2008/02/23/should-peer-review-be-confidential">written</ext-link>
in February about the drug company Pfizer trying to obtain confidential
peer review documents from the journals
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611111125/http://jama.ama-assn.org/">JAMA</ext-link>
and
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611111125/http://www.nejm.org/">NEJM</ext-link>.
Courts in Chicago and Boston have
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611111125/http://sciencenow.sciencemag.org/cgi/content/full/2008/401/1">denied</ext-link>
such requests.</p>
<p>An
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611111125/http://jama.ama-assn.org/cgi/content/full/299/15/1800">article</ext-link>
and accompanying
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611111125/http://jama.ama-assn.org/cgi/content/full/299/15/1833">editorial</ext-link>
in this week's JAMA look at guest authorship and ghostwriting in
publications related to rofecoxib (better known as Vioxx, produced by
Merck). Guest authorship was defined as an author that does not meet
authorship criteria. The
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611111125/http://www.icmje.org/">Uniform
Requirements for Manuscripts to Biomedical Journals</ext-link> from the
International Commitee of Medical Journal Editors (ICMJE) define
authorship as follows:</p>
<p specific-use="wrapper">
  <disp-quote>
    <p><italic><italic>Authorship credit should be based on 1)
    substantial contributions to conception and design, or acquisition
    of data, or analysis and interpretation of data; 2) drafting the
    article or revising it critically for important intellectual
    content; and 3) final approval of the version to be published.
    Authors should meet conditions 1, 2, and 3.</italic></italic></p>
  </disp-quote>
</p>
<p>Ghostwriting was defined as the failure to designate an individual
that made significant contributions to the research or writing of a
manuscript.</p>
<p>The JAMA
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611111125/http://jama.ama-assn.org/cgi/content/full/299/15/1800">article</ext-link>
did a systematic analysis of the court documents obtained during
litigation related to rofecoxib. Guest authorship was identified in 16%
of research articles and 26% of review articles; ghostwriting was
identified in 13% of research articles and 10% of review articles. The
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611111125/http://jama.ama-assn.org/cgi/content/full/299/15/1833">editorial</ext-link>
in the same issue is called <italic><italic>Impugning the Integrity of
Medical Science: The Adverse Effects of Industry
Influence</italic></italic> and dicusses this article as well an another
article called
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611111125/http://jama.ama-assn.org/cgi/content/full/299/15/1813">Reporting
Mortality Findings in Trials of Rofecoxib for Alzheimer Disease or
Cognitive Impairment</ext-link> in the same issue. The editorial
proposes that drastic action is necessary and includes a list of 11
measures.</p>
<p>Criteria for authorship and disclosure of financial interests are
clearly defined not only by the ICMJE, but also by the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611111125/http://www.blackwell-synergy.com/doi/full/10.1111/j.1525-1497.2005.41015.x">World
Association of Medical Editors</ext-link> (WAME) and by most journals.
And the European Medical Writers Association (EMWA) has published
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611111125/http://www.emwa.org/Mum/EMWAguidelines.pdf">guidelines</ext-link>
on the role of medical writers in peer-reviewed publications. As medical
writers usually don't fulfill the authorship criteria defined above
(with the possible exception of review articles), they should rather be
acknowledged. The EMWA guidelines propose the following wording:</p>
<p specific-use="wrapper">
  <disp-quote>
    <p><italic><italic>We thank Dr Jane Doe who provided medical writing
    services on behalf of XYZ Pharmaceuticals Ltd.</italic></italic></p>
  </disp-quote>
</p>
<p>The rules are clear and it is also clear that there will be
violations of these rules. Guest authorship and ghostwriting are
probably common practices, not only in publications supported by drug
companies. Typical examples would be the inclusion of the department
head that did little more than to provide financial support or the
exclusion of the technician that did critical experiments but is not
acknowledged. Cases of suspected guest authorship or ghostwriting should
be taken seriously and the papers in JAMA will ignite a renewed
discussion on these topics.</p>
<p>For different views on this topic, look at
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611111125/http://blogs.nature.com/nm/spoonful/2008/04/exit_ghost.html">Exit
ghost</ext-link> by Juan Carlos Lopez over at <italic><italic>Spoonful
of Medicine</italic></italic> and
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611111125/http://pipeline.corante.com/archives/2008/04/18/cut_it_out_cut_it_out_now.php">Cut
it out. Cut it out now.</ext-link> by Derek Lowe at <italic><italic>In
the Pipeline</italic></italic>.</p>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
