<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>On Privacy</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2010-05-24">
<day>24</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2010</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Social media and privacy have a complicated relationship, as using
social media implies giving up at least some privacy. And the value of a
social networking site is directly related not only to the number of
users, but also the extend of personal data that the site has collected.
All this is of course not unique to social networking tools for
scientists, but conducting science using online tools is different from
connecting to friends or people with similar personal interests with
these tools. One area where privacy issues are particularly prominent is
the creation of unique identifiers for scientists, and here I'm involved
in the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611031846/http://www.orcid.org/">ORCID</ext-link>
initiative. We need a discussion about required privacy standards, and
about the limitations of privacy that we accept in order to increase our
scientific productivity.</p>
<fig>
  <caption><p>Flickr image by rpongsaj.</p></caption>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611031846im_/http://farm3.static.flickr.com/2052/2404940312_e759c4030d.jpg" xlink:title="" />
</fig>
<p>I've collected a couple of thoughts below. They are of course only
starting points for a discussion, and I welcome any comments and
suggestions.</p>
<sec id="1-the-service-allows-anonymous-access">
  <title>1. The service allows anonymous access</title>
  <p>Social networking sites for scientists can be quite useful for
  anonymous users, e.g. for reading of blog or forum posts. Users should
  not be required to sign up for a service just for reading a public
  message or looking at the public part of a user profile. Many social
  networking sites unfortunately require a user account these
  activities, and they often nag users to “complete their personal
  profiles”, i.e. to provide as much personal information as
  possible.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="2-the-service-has-a-privacy-policy">
  <title>2. The service has a privacy policy</title>
  <p>I've randomly checked five social networking sites for scientists,
  and they all provide a privacy policy:</p>
  <list list-type="bullet">
    <list-item>
      <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611031846/http://www.academia.edu/privacy">Academia.edu</ext-link></p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611031846/http://www.citeulike.org/privacy">CiteULike</ext-link></p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611031846/http://www.mendeley.com/privacy/">Mendeley</ext-link></p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611031846/http://network.nature.com/site/privacy">Nature
      Network</ext-link></p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611031846/http://www.researchgate.net/application.PrivacyPolicy.html">ResearchGate</ext-link></p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
  <p>The privacy policy should make clear what user data the service is
  collecting, whether the service is providing these user data to third
  parties, and should provide an email address for further privacy
  questions.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="3-personal-data-are-owned-by-the-user">
  <title>3. Personal data are owned by the user</title>
  <p>All personal data that a user uploads should be owned by the user,
  and the privacy policy should make this clear. This implies that a
  user should be allowed to cancel an account and delete all personal
  information (surprisingly difficult with most social networking
  sites), and that the user decides which part of the personal data is
  shared with others, and with whom.</p>
  <p>To give users control over their privacy settings, these settings
  should default to not being public for everything beyond the most
  basic information, and they should not change over time
  (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611031846/http://mattmckeon.com/facebook-privacy/">The
  Evolution of privacy on Facebook</ext-link>).</p>
  <p>Obviously there is a large grey area. If I comment on a blog post
  by someone else, who owns this comment, and who should be allowed to
  delete this comment – me, the author of the blog post, and/or the
  provider of the social networking site? And who owns my usage data of
  a service, how often I logged in, my activity in the service,
  etc.?</p>
</sec>
<sec id="4-the-service-protects-the-user-data">
  <title>4. The service protects the user data</title>
  <p>The social networking site should make all efforts necessary to
  protect the personal data of a user. There are examples where this has
  gone wrong, and this includes examples involving scientists
  (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611031846/http://www.nature.com/news/2009/090423/full/news.2009.398.html">Fake
  Facebook pages spin web of deceit</ext-link>).</p>
  <p><italic><italic>Update 5/25/10: I didn't see it when I wrote the
  post, but last week the Electronic Frontier Foundation published a
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611031846/http://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2010/05/bill-privacy-rights-social-network-users">Bill
  of Privacy Rights for Social Network Users</ext-link> (thanks to Renny
  Guida for the link).</italic></italic></p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
