<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>One Ring to Rule them All</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2014-07-30">
<day>30</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2014</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p specific-use="wrapper">
  <disp-quote>
    <p>One Ring to rule them all, One Ring to find them, One Ring to
    bring them all and in the darkness bind them.</p>
  </disp-quote>
</p>
<p>Yesterday 60 years ago the first volume of the <italic>Lord of the
Rings</italic> trilogy by <italic>J.R.R. Tolkien</italic> was published.
The quote above obviously doesn’t quiet apply to scholarly publishing,
but one recurring theme that I have often heard in the last few years is
that of a need for a canonical digital document format for scholarly
content that rules all other formats.</p>
<fig>
  <caption><p>Document formats in scholarly Publishing</p></caption>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="http://blog.martinfenner.org/images/rings.png" xlink:title="" />
</fig>
<p>A few years ago almost everyone you would have said that
<monospace>xml</monospace> is that format, with the NLM Archiving and
Interchange Tag Suite - which has evolved into
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/">JATS</ext-link>
- probably the most commonly used Document Type Definition (DTD).
<monospace>xml</monospace> does many things really well, but also has
important shortcomings, most importantly that it is probably not a good
format for authors (and don’t tell me that <monospace>docx</monospace>
and <monospace>odt</monospace> are XML-based). We therefore don’t really
expect authors to submit manuscripts in JATS <monospace>xml</monospace>,
but rather convert documents into this format after a manuscript has
been accepted for publication. This conversion step is often
time-consuming and labor-intensive.</p>
<p>More recently <monospace>html</monospace> has become the most
interesting candidate for a canonical scholarly document format. The big
advantage over <monospace>xml</monospace> is that
<monospace>html</monospace> - or at least <monospace>html5</monospace>
which is most popular today - is an attractive format for online
authoring tools (that is why <monospace>html</monospace> is listed both
as input and output format) The downside of this flexibility is that it
is much harder to embed structure and metadata into
<monospace>html5</monospace> compared to <monospace>xml</monospace>.
There are initiatives such as
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://schema.org/">schema.org</ext-link>
and
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/oreillymedia/HTMLBook">HTMLBook</ext-link>
that hope to change that, but we aren’t quiet there yet.</p>
<p>Or maybe we should learn from Tolkien and give up on the idea of a
canonical document format and rather spend our energy on building tools
that make it easier to transition from one format to another.
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://johnmacfarlane.net/pandoc/">Pandoc</ext-link>
is such as tool, but can’t do all the required conversions, e.g. it
can’t yet use <monospace>docx</monospace> as input. The downside here is
that every file conversion runs the risk of loosing important
information. But the increase in flexibility hopefully outweights these
shortcomings.</p>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
