<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Online reference managers: not quite there
yet</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2008-06-23">
<day>23</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2008</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>For my
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611092952/http://network.nature.com/blogs/user/mfenner/2008/06/14/my-paper-writing-dream-machine-1-0">Paper
Writing Dream Machine</ext-link> I obviously need a reference manager.
My list of required features includes:</p>
<list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
    <p>Easy addition of references by integration with Pubmed, Google
    Scholar and other online databases. A special bookmarklet would be a
    bonus.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>Commenting on references, e.g. custom tags or free-form text</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>Creation of reference lists, e.g. by tags</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>Sharing of reference lists to user-defined groups or to
    everybody</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>Integration of the references into your word processor of choice.
    An export function into a common format such as .ris is a minimum. A
    better solution would be an open programming interface (API).</p>
  </list-item>
</list>
<p>For obvious reasons (sharing references with your coauthors) an
online reference manager is the easiest way to accomplish these feature
requests.</p>
<sec id="connotea">
  <title><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611092952/http://www.connotea.com/">Connotea</ext-link></title>
  <p>You import references into Connotea via bookmarklet or by entering
  the DOI. A direct query of Pubmed is not possible. References can be
  tagged and commented on. Unfortunately it is not possible to create a
  reference list for a particular paper that is only seen by your
  coauthors (Connotea groups are all or nothing). References can be
  exported into common formats, but no direct word processor
  integration. A Connotea Web API is
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611092952/http://www.connotea.org/wiki/WebAPI">available</ext-link>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="citeulike">
  <title><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611092952/http://www.citeulike.org/">CiteULike</ext-link></title>
  <p>CiteULike is very similar in features to Connotea. The same
  limitations (no private group for reference list, no word processor
  integration) also apply.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="2collab">
  <title><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611092952/http://www.2collab.com/">2collab</ext-link></title>
  <p>A newer service created by Elsevier. Again similar in features to
  CiteULike and Connotea. Private groups for your coauthors to share a
  reference list are supported. No direct word processor integration.
  2collab has a public API.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="refworks">
  <title><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611092952/http://www.refworks.com/">RefWorks</ext-link></title>
  <p>In contrast to Connotea and CiteULike this is a commercial product
  (our university has a subscription). Again no direct integration with
  Pubmed (only copy and paste), but a bookmarklet. And again
  difficulties to create a list of references that is visible just to
  your coauthors. Write-n-Cite is a RefWorks plugin for Microsoft Word.
  No API.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="endnote-web">
  <title><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611092952/http://www.endnoteweb.com/enwebinfo.asp">EndNote
  Web</ext-link></title>
  <p>EndNote Web is promoted as a sort of Endnote Lite, i.e. a web-based
  tool with just the basic features of the commercial desktop
  application. Again no direct Pubmed Search, but integration with
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611092952/http://isiknowledge.com/">Web
  of Science</ext-link> (just like Endnote a product from Thomson
  Scientific). Sharing of reference lists to just your coauthors is
  possible. Endnote Web comes with a Microsoft Word plugin for ease
  paper writing.</p>
  <p>With the exception of Connotea and 2collab, all the systems
  mentioned above allow you to store the full-text PDF. This is a handy
  feature, but online storing of creates copyright issues for papers
  that are not public access.</p>
  <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611092952/http://www.zotero.org/">Zotero</ext-link>,
  a Firefox extension, is not on this list, because references are
  stored locally and cannot easily be shared with others.</p>
  <p>Surprisingly, none of the tools supports all my requirements.
  Endnote Web comes closest, but is far from perfect (e.g. sometimes
  slow, also needs Web of Science). Is it so difficult to build a Pubmed
  query function and group reference list into the tools?</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
