<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>OPDS: RSS for ePub or how to distribute ePub
files</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2011-02-06">
<day>6</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2011</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>ePub is a great
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611043846/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2011/01/23/beyond-the-pdf-%E2%80%A6-is-epub/">format
for scholarly content</ext-link>, and there are a
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611043846/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2011/02/01/epub-wordpress-plugin-released-today/">number
of tools</ext-link> to create ePub files. But creating content is only
half the story, at least as important is an easy mechanism for
distribution. This is particularly true if your ePub files are not
books, but shorter pieces of content: journal articles, blog posts or
even output from your ongoing research.
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611043846/http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/RSS">RSS</ext-link>
or the related Atom protocol has of course become the standard mechanism
to publish frequently updated works.</p>
<p>Open Publication Syndication System
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611043846/http://code.google.com/p/openpub/wiki/CatalogSpecDraft#Introduction">OPDS</ext-link>)
is a syndication format for electronic publications based on Atom. OPDS
is a relatively new format, but is supported by a growing number of
(book) publishers, ePub tools and readers. If you want to try OPDS for
yourself, pick one the feeds listed
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611043846/http://code.google.com/p/openpub/wiki/AvailableFeeds">here</ext-link>
and add the feed as a Book source in the Stanza reader (in the
<bold><bold>Shared</bold></bold> section). Alternatively, install the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611043846/http://www.epubread.com/de/manual.php">EPUBReader
plugin</ext-link> for Firefox. As you can see, OPDS does more than just
list titles with a summary and image, you can also categorize the
content by author (or tag), and provide a search interface.</p>
<fig>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611043846im_/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/files/2011/02/OPDS-500x371.jpg" xlink:title="OPDS" />
</fig>
<p>I’m looking forward to the first scholarly publisher that not only
provides ePub files of his journal articles, but also makes them
available via OPDS. Although OPDS is currently used mostly for
electronic books, I think that this is a very interesting protocol for
scholarly publishers. Did I mention that OPDS also provides facilities
for buying or lending content? And that you probably shouldn’t expect
OPDS support in the Apple iBooks application for iPhone and iPad anytime
soon as they don’t seem to like distributed content delivery? I would
like to see scholarly publishers providing their journal content via
ePub and OPDS that can be consumed with one of the many available
readers, rather than everybody creating his own little app that only
works with a single publisher on a single platform.</p>
<p>OPDS is a relatively simple protocol and similar to RSS should make
it easy for everybody to provide his content in catalog form. It should
be straightforward to add OPDS support to the WordPress
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611043846/http://wordpress.org/extend/plugins/epub-export/">ePub
plugin</ext-link> that I released last week, thus making a blog (or blog
network) available directly in the ePub reader. While I expect that we
will continue to read most blogs via the Web or RSS reader, ePub might
be the better format for longer posts and the posts you want to store on
your computer.</p>
<p>ePub is a very interesting format for packaging research objects,
e.g. the description and data files from an experiment. OPDS would be
very helpful as a distribution mechanism for these ePubs, and also works
on the small scale of a research group. You can for example use the
Calibre eBook management tool – which can create not only ePub files but
also OPDS catalogs – together with Dropbox to
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611043846/http://dearauthor.com/wordpress/2010/02/14/create-your-own-cloud-of-ebooks-with-calibre-calibre-opds-dropbox/">share
your content</ext-link>. The
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611043846/http://wiki.mobileread.com/wiki/Calibre2opds">calibre2opds</ext-link>
tool also creates an OPDS catalog from the Calibre metadata database but
doesn’t require Calibre to run in order to use the OPDS catalog. And the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611043846/http://www.pincette.biz/index.xhtml">Pincette</ext-link>
document management system automatically creates an OPDS catalog for the
ePub files dropped into a Pincette folder. I hope that more tools for
researchers start to support not only ePub but also OPDS. An OPDS
interface to the data produced by your favorite piece of lab equipment
(gel documentation system, microarray reader, etc.) would be an
interesting sight.</p>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
