<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Open access is not enough – the source is also
important</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2008-12-05">
<day>5</day>
<month>12</month>
<year>2008</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Direct to consumer advertising (DTCA) – advertising for prescription
drugs – is only allowed in the United States (since 1997, when
restrictions were loosened) and New Zealand. Drug companies pay for
direct to consumer advertising (more than $4 billion in 2005 (Donohue
2007)) because they believe that it increases prescription rates. In a
clever study published in the <italic><italic>British Medical
Journal</italic></italic> in September
<sup><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150922174115/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2008/12/05/open_access_is_not_enough_the_source_is_also_important/#fn2"></ext-link></sup>
(Law 2008) Michael Law and colleagues looked at the prescription rates
of the drugs etanercept, mometasone, and tegaserod in Canada. DTCA is
not allowed in Canada, but English-speaking Canadians see these ads in
US magazines and US TV commercials. The study authors found that
prescriptions were higher compared to French-speaking Canada (supposedly
not using the US media) for one of the three drugs studied (tegaserod).
The study authors explain:</p>
<p>The European Union is considering changes in legislation that would
allow direct to consumer advertising
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150922174115/http://www.pharmalot.com/2008/10/eu-plan-gives-pharma-direct-access-to-patients/">EU
Plan Gives Pharma Direct Access To Patients</ext-link>). Not a good
idea. Direct to consumer advertising not only means easily identified
ads, but also information campaigns about diseases and treatments that
are biased towards prescribing a particular drug.</p>
<p>The problems surrounding direct to consumer advertising are a
reminder that open access to scientific and medical information is not
enough. Similar conflicts of interest exist when car manufacturers would
talk about climate change or crop producers about genetically engineered
crops. We need not access to as much information as possible, but rather
access to independent and objective information of high quality.
Scientific journals and learned societies have traditionally played an
important role in this. Once they've built up more reputation, science
bloggers could have a bigger role in this in the future.</p>
<sec id="references">
  <title>References</title>
  <p>Donohue, J. M., Cevasco, M., &amp; Rosenthal, M. B. (2007). A
  Decade of Direct-to-Consumer Advertising of Prescription Drugs. New
  England Journal of Medicine, 357(7), 673–681.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1056/nejmsa070502">https://doi.org/10.1056/nejmsa070502</ext-link></p>
  <p>Law, M. R., Majumdar, S. R., &amp; Soumerai, S. B. (2008). Effect
  of illicit direct to consumer advertising on use of etanercept,
  mometasone, and tegaserod in Canada: controlled longitudinal study.
  BMJ, 337(sep02 1), a1055–a1055.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1136/bmj.a1055">https://doi.org/10.1136/bmj.a1055</ext-link></p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
