<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Open Access Week: a researcher’s perspective part
II</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2009-10-23">
<day>23</day>
<month>10</month>
<year>2009</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>This week (October 19-23) is
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611105548/http://www.openaccessweek.org/">Open
Access Week</ext-link> – a good opportunity to think and write about
this topic. On Monday I wrote in a
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611105548/http://network.nature.com/people/mfenner/blog/2009/10/18/open-access-week-a-researchers-perspective">blog
post</ext-link>:</p>
<p specific-use="wrapper">
  <disp-quote>
    <p>Open Access can be looked at from many different angles,
    including the researcher, the science library, the institution, the
    funding organization, the journal, the science journalist, and the
    general public. Most arguments for or against Open Access depend on
    that angle. As a researcher, I am most interested in whether Open
    Access will make my work easier. Again, a researcher can look at
    Open Access from different roles: reader, author, reviewer,
    editor.</p>
  </disp-quote>
</p>
<p>In that blog post I then wrote about the role of the researcher as a
reader. Now I want to look at the perspective of the researcher as an
author.</p>
<sec id="choice-of-journal">
  <title>Choice of journal</title>
  <p>The decision of where to publish a manuscript for most researchers
  probably works something like “find the best journal where I can
  publish my work with the least amount of trouble”.
  <italic><italic>Best journal</italic></italic> usually is a subjective
  decision, but probably correlates with the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611105548/http://thomsonreuters.com/products_services/science/free/essays/impact_factor/">Impact
  Factor</ext-link> of a journal. As the average quality of manuscripts
  is higher in a <italic><italic>better journal</italic></italic>, this
  will help to value your research in the eyes of granting agencies and
  job search committees. <italic><italic>Better
  journal</italic></italic> often means higher rejection rates and/or
  higher numbers of readers. Both factors – and journals that publish a
  relatively small number of papers – favor a subscription business
  model<sup><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611105548/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2009/10/23/open_access_week_a_researchers_perspective_part_ii/#fn1">1</ext-link></sup>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="publication-cost">
  <title>Publication cost</title>
  <p>Most Open Access journals use an author-pays model to pay for
  publication costs. Funding agencies or institutions may pick up these
  costs, but authors may be left with costs of $2500 or more.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="institutional-repositories">
  <title>Institutional Repositories</title>
  <p>Self-archiving in institutional repositories (green access) is a
  great way to make your publication freely available if the paper is
  published in a journal that is not Open Access. Unfortunately this
  often requires extra efforts by the researcher, and the publication
  will be more difficult to find in the repository than in the journal.
  This creates little incentive for a researcher to get involved in
  self-archiving.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="citation-advantage">
  <title>Citation advantage</title>
  <p>The effect of free access to the scientific literature on article
  downloads and citations is difficult to measure.
  Some<sup><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611105548/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2009/10/23/open_access_week_a_researchers_perspective_part_ii/#fn2">2</ext-link></sup>,
  but not all
  studies<sup><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611105548/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2009/10/23/open_access_week_a_researchers_perspective_part_ii/#fn3">3</ext-link></sup>
  show higher citation rates for articles that are freely available and
  this citation advantage might be
  modest<sup><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611105548/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2009/10/23/open_access_week_a_researchers_perspective_part_ii/#fn4">4</ext-link></sup>.
  Citations are generated by other researchers who have access to your
  paper, and therefore I'm not surprised if there is not much of a
  difference between papers in Open Access journals and popular journals
  that are subscribed my many institutions.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="better-access">
  <title>Better Access</title>
  <p>Researchers in poorer countries will have easier access to papers
  published in Open Access journals, although many subscription journals
  wave access fees through initiatives such as
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611105548/http://www.who.int/hinari/en/">Hinari</ext-link>.
  Open Access makes it easier for journalists, high school students,
  patient advocacy groups and many more people to read your papers. This
  is obviously of great value to these groups, but I haven't seen many
  examples where the paper author directly benefitted from this.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="social-responsibility">
  <title>Social responsibility</title>
  <p>The argument that publicly funded research should be available to
  everybody at time of publication can be a motivation for many
  scientists, but I would be careful to turn this into an obligation.
  Different countries have different traditions, but in my home country
  Germany the independence of research and researchers (including the
  decision where to publish) has become a constitutional right after the
  atrocities committed in the name of “science” in Nazi Germany. All
  major German research organizations support Open Access, but in
  contrast to other countries there is no Open Access mandate.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="summary">
  <title>Summary</title>
  <p>Publishing in an Open Access journal has surprisingly little
  benefits for the author of a paper, and often means additional costs.
  Unless we want to mandate Open Access publishing from authors because
  it benefits the other stakeholders (which at least in Germany would be
  difficult), we should make publishing in an Open Access journal more
  attractive to authors. It looks like PLoS ONE is doing exactly that,
  as 400 manuscripts published per month testify.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="references">
  <title>References</title>
  <p>Science in the open. (2009). Nature Materials, 8(8), 611–611.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/nmat2497">https://doi.org/10.1038/nmat2497</ext-link></p>
  <p>Eysenbach, G. (2006). Citation Advantage of Open Access Articles.
  PLoS Biology, 4(5), e157.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.0040157">https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.0040157</ext-link></p>
  <p>Davis, P. M., Lewenstein, B. V., Simon, D. H., Booth, J. G., &amp;
  Connolly, M. J. L. (2008). Open access publishing, article downloads,
  and citations: randomised controlled trial. BMJ, 337(jul31 1),
  a568–a568.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1136/bmj.a568">https://doi.org/10.1136/bmj.a568</ext-link></p>
  <p>Evans, J. A., &amp; Reimer, J. (2009). Open Access and Global
  Participation in Science. Science, 323(5917), 1025–1025.
  https://doi.org/10.1126/science.1154562</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
