<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Open Access Week: a researcher’s
perspective</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2009-10-18">
<day>18</day>
<month>10</month>
<year>2009</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>This week (October 19-23) is
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611105124/http://www.openaccessweek.org/">Open
Access Week</ext-link>:</p>
<p specific-use="wrapper">
  <disp-quote>
    <p>Open Access Week is an opportunity to broaden awareness and
    understanding of Open Access to research, including access policies
    from all types of research funders, within the international higher
    education community and the general public.</p>
  </disp-quote>
</p>
<p>The following video from
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611105124/http://www.arl.org/sparc/">SPARC</ext-link>
(the Scholarly Publishing &amp; Academic Resources Coalition) is a good
introduction:</p>
<p>Open Access can be looked at from many different angles, including
the <italic><italic>researcher</italic></italic>, the
<italic><italic>science library</italic></italic>, the
<italic><italic>institution</italic></italic>, the
<italic><italic>funding organization</italic></italic>, the
<italic><italic>journal</italic></italic>, the <italic><italic>science
journalist</italic></italic>, and the <italic><italic>general
public</italic></italic>. Most arguments for or against Open Access
depend on that angle. As a researcher, I am most interested in whether
Open Access will make my work easier. Again, a researcher can look at
Open Access from different roles:</p>
<list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
    <p>Reader</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>Author</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>Reviewer</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>Editor</p>
  </list-item>
</list>
<p>The role as a reviewer or editor for an open access paper should be
essentially the same as for a paper with subscription-based access. The
journal <italic><italic>Nature Communications</italic></italic> that
launches in April 2010 with a hybrid publishing model of open access and
subscription-based access will for example have reviewers and editors
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611105124/http://www.nature.com/ncomms/open_access/pdf/open-access-faqs.pdf">blinded
to the author's choice</ext-link>.</p>
<p>In this blog post I will look at Open Access from the perspective of
the researcher as a reader.</p>
<sec id="access">
  <title>Access</title>
  <p>As a researcher in a German university I am privileged to have
  institutional access to most journal articles that I need for my work.
  I use the program
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611105124/http://mekentosj.com/papers/">Papers</ext-link>
  as my main reference manager. Papers allows me to order my currently
  1715 references (and PDFs of fulltext paper to most of them) by
  journal. Among the 20 journals with the most papers in my library, my
  institution doesn't have access to three of them:</p>
  <list list-type="bullet">
    <list-item>
      <p><italic><italic>Cell</italic></italic> (don't ask)</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p><italic><italic>Lancet Oncology</italic></italic></p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p><italic><italic>Nature Reviews Clinical
      Oncology</italic></italic></p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
  <p>Obviously three important journals for someone doing clinical
  cancer research. I could ask my institution to start subscribing to
  these journals, start a personal subscription (I had a personal
  subscription to <italic><italic>Nature Clinical Practice
  Oncology</italic></italic> for two years before it was renamed to
  <italic><italic>Nature Reviews Clinical Oncology</italic></italic>)
  which would set me back 150-200 â‚¬ per journal, or I could pay for an
  individual article (either through my library or directly from the
  journal). All this requires extra time and money, worth only if I
  think a paper/journal is really important.</p>
  <p><italic><italic>PLoS Medicine</italic></italic> is the only open
  access journal among the 20 most popular journals in my Papers library
  (The <italic><italic>BMJ</italic></italic> has free access to its
  research articles and is the 24th most popular). Unfortunately there
  are only a few Open Access journals publishing papers that are
  relevant to my work.</p>
  <p>As many others I do work from home in the evening or on the
  weekend, or while travelling. I am lucky that I can access my
  university network through
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611105124/http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Virtual_private_network">VPN</ext-link>
  and therefore can get fulltext access to journal articles (one of the
  most important VPN uses for me). But some researchers might not be so
  lucky, or spend precious extra time setting up and using VPN.</p>
  <p>Researchers that work in a poorer country, or for a smaller
  university or small biotech startup will have much larger problems.
  Medical doctors in community hospitals or private practice may not
  have easy access to any of the relevant journals, and they might
  depend on reprints given to them by colleagues or representatives from
  drug companies.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sharing">
  <title>Sharing</title>
  <p>If several people work on a research project, they also want to
  share the relevant literature in the field. Most subscription-based
  journals retain the copyright to the paper and don't allow storing in
  a retrieval system or transmitting of papers without permission. This
  could mean that you can't email the PDF of a paper to a colleague even
  if you are the author or his institution also has a subscription. And
  this could also mean that you can't use a reference manager such as
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611105124/http://www.refworks.com/">Refworks</ext-link>
  or
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611105124/http://www.mendeley.com/">Mendeley</ext-link>
  to not only share references with your lab colleagues, but also the
  full-text PDF files. Strictly following the copyright can make
  something as common as a <italic><italic>journal
  club</italic></italic> a complicated affair.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="permissions">
  <title>Permissions</title>
  <p>As most subscription-based journals retain the copyright to the
  paper, you have to ask for permissions when reusing tables or figures.
  Most often this is the case when giving a lecture on a topic. For
  longer lectures this could mean a large number of required
  permissions, and the permissions might be granted just for a single
  occasion. Journals might not care much about using a single figure in
  a departmental seminar, but it definitely becomes an issue when the
  lecture is distributed electronically, e.g. as free
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611105124/http://ocw.mit.edu/OcwWeb/web/home/home/index.htm">OpenCourseWare</ext-link>
  publication of teaching material. Some journals provide Powerpoint
  slides for the tables and figures and explicitly permit the
  educational noncommercial use. In my experience most researchers
  aren't aware that they are using copyrighted material in their slides,
  and I rarely see the required copyright attributions.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="added-services">
  <title>Added services</title>
  <p>This category has great potential, but is currently not yet that
  relevant in my daily work. Open Access to fulltext articles allows
  things that aren't possible or much more complicated with
  subscription-based access. This includes fulltext searches (to find
  information not in the title, abstract or keywords), semantically
  enhanced articles, and article-level metrics
  (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611105124/http://network.nature.com/people/mfenner/blog/2009/08/15/plos-one-interview-with-peter-binfield">recently
  introduced by PLoS</ext-link>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="summary">
  <title>Summary</title>
  <p>Researchers at large research institutions often have institutional
  access to most relevant papers. They are often not aware of the
  restrictions imposed upon them by the copyright of papers retained by
  most subscription-based journals. Open Access papers not only are
  freely accessible, but allow the uncomplicated redistribution and
  reuse for research and teaching, as well as innovative ways to find
  interesting research.</p>
  <p>The perspective of the researcher as a paper author is stuff for
  another blog post…</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
