<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>ORCID has launched. What’s next?</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2012-10-22">
<day>22</day>
<month>10</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Last week has been busy. I went to Berlin for the launch of the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170518120701/http://orcid.org/">Open
Researcher &amp; Contributor ID (ORCID)</ext-link> service. ORCID allows
researchers to obtain a persistent identifier that can be used to claim
publications and other scholarly works. I’m
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170518120701/http://orcid.org/0000-0003-1419-2405">0000-0003-1419-2405</ext-link>,
and we put the ID (and the QR code linking to the profile on the ORCID
website) on the name tags for the ORCID Outreach Meeting last Wednesday
(Geek alert: I also have received a T-shirt with my name, ORCID and QR
code).</p>
<fig>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170518120701im_/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/files/2012/10/nametag-500x283.png" xlink:title="" />
</fig>
<p>I was invited to work with ORCID in early 2010 after writing about
the initiative that was started in November 2009 on this blog
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170518120701/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2010/01/03/orcid_or_how_to_build_a_unique_identifier_for_scientists_in_10_easy_steps/">ORCID
or how to build a unique identifier for scientists in 10 easy
steps</ext-link>). And now, after three years and a lot of work by a lot
of people, ORCID is real and everyone can use the system. As a
researcher, you can go to the ORCID website and register.</p>
<fig>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170518120701im_/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/files/2012/10/orcid-500x445.png" xlink:title="" />
</fig>
<p>Obtaining a number is of course not very interesting in itself, few
people get excited about the fact of having a 16-digit unique
identifier. What ORCID is really about is claiming your publications and
other scholarly works, and <bold>Connecting Research and
Researchers</bold> is the slogan of the organization. In the ORCID
system you can now claim publications found in the CrossRef database,
and other work types will be added over time.</p>
<p>What I’m particularly interested in is the claiming of research
datasets. Everyone wants to give researchers better credit for the data
they have produced, transformed and annotated, but data citation is
still not a widespread practice. I am therefore very excited to be
involved in the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170518120701/http://www.odin-project.eu/">ORCID
and DataCite Interoperability Network</ext-link> (ODIN), a EU-funded
project that had its kickoff meeting last week in Berlin.</p>
<fig>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170518120701im_/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/files/2012/10/odin-500x319.png" xlink:title="" />
</fig>
<p>In the ODIN project we will work closely with
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170518120701/http://www.datacite.org/">DataCite</ext-link>,
an organization that provides digital object identifiers (DOIs) for
research data. One of the many things I like about ODIN is that social
sciences is one of the disciplines where we will build a proof of
concept (with the British Library, the other discipline is high-energy
physics and CERN). We also want to understand how to best link
researchers, data and publications.
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170518120701/http://datadryad.org/">Dryad</ext-link>
is an ODIN project partner and obviously has a lot of experience linking
biological datasets to publications, and we will discuss how to
integrate ORCID identifiers into the workflow.</p>
<p>Unique identifiers for researchers are of course also an essential
part of any work on article-level metrics. I
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170518120701/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2012/06/25/random-notes-from-the-altmetrics12-conference/">spoke
about this</ext-link> at the altmetrics12 conference in June, and I’m
excited that we can now finally start linking things together.
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170518120701/http://impactstory.org/">ImpactStory</ext-link>
was one of the ORCID launch partners, and I demoed their ORCID
integration last week in Berlin.</p>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170518120701/http://sciencecard.org/">ScienceCard</ext-link>
is a fork of the open source
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170518120701/http://article-level-metrics.plos.org/">PLOS
Article-Level Metrics application</ext-link>, and is a project I started
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170518120701/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2011/11/20/sciencecard-named-finalist-in-mendeleyplos-api-binary-battle/">about
a year ago</ext-link>. ScienceCard allows researchers to list all their
publications, and the metrics associated with them. With the launch of
ORCID I was able to finally add one important missing piece. Through
automatic lookup of the ORCID identifier and retrieval of the
publications claimed in the ORCID profile is has become much easier to
create and maintain a ScienceCard profile – it shouldn’t take more than
5 min and a few mouse clicks (collecting all metrics takes longer
because that happens in the background). I added ORCID integration to
ScienceCard over the weekend, using the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170518120701/http://dev.orcid.org/resources">free
public ORCID API</ext-link>.</p>
<fig>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170518120701im_/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/files/2012/10/sciencecard-500x438.png" xlink:title="" />
</fig>
<p>ScienceCard is a great tool to explore how research impact can be
collected and displayed, and I appreciate feedback in the form of
feature requests and bug reports, ideally in the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170518120701/https://github.com/mfenner/alm/issues">GitHub
issue tracker</ext-link> of the project. This will also provide very
valuable feedback to improve the PLOS Article-Level Metrics application,
as they use almost the same code base. The API is for example completely
the same,
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170518120701/https://github.com/ropensci/rplos">rplos</ext-link>
and other tools using the PLOS ALM API can be used with ScienceCard by
just changing the URL. Another example is the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170518120701/http://wordpress.org/extend/plugins/plos-alm-widget/">PLOS
ALM WordPress Widget</ext-link>, with minor modifications it can be also
be used with ScienceCard, allowing a researcher to display the metrics
for his publications from PLOS and other sources on his blog. The
upcoming
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170518120701/https://sites.google.com/site/altmetricsworkshop/">Altmetrics
workshop and hackathon</ext-link> (November 1-3 in San Francisco) will
be a great opportunity to explore this further.</p>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
