<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Papers 2: the reference manager made with
love</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2011-03-08">
<day>8</day>
<month>3</month>
<year>2011</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>The reference management software
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525044214/http://www.mekentosj.com/papers/">Papers</ext-link>
has been a regular topic on this blog. I wrote about Papers in one of my
first blog posts in May 2008,
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525044214/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2008/10/03/interview_with_alexander_griekspoor/">interviewed</ext-link>
main developer Alex Griekspoor in October 2008, and held a
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525044214/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2009/02/19/papers_for_iphone_released_time_for_more_poetry/">poetry
contest</ext-link> when Papers for iPhone was released in February 2009
(Stephen Curry won the first price for
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525044214/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2009/02/19/papers_for_iphone_released_time_for_more_poetry/#comment-898">this
poem</ext-link>).</p>
<fig>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525044214im_/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/files/2011/03/Papers-2c.jpg" xlink:title="Papers 2c" />
</fig>
<p>Today Papers 2
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525044214/http://news.mekentosj.com/">was
released</ext-link>, and with this major update Papers has grown into a
full-fledged reference manager for the Macintosh (there is no Windows or
Linux version). Papers 1 was released in 2007 as a tool to manage the
PDF files of scholarly papers on your hard drive. Papers 1 did this job
very well, but it was not a reference manager in the strict sense,
because you couldn’t use Papers to insert citations into the manuscripts
you were writing.</p>
<p>In order to add this feature, Papers first had to be completely
rewritten to not only handle journal articles and the associated PDF
files, but also all the other common reference formats – conference
proceeding, book chapter, website, etc. A nice side effect that I
haven’t fully explored yet is that Papers can now also store all your
Powerpoint or Keynote presentations (but fulltext search in these
presentations doesn’t seem to work yet).</p>
<p>Inserting references into manuscripts is done using a floating window
activated from the menu bar or with a shortcut:</p>
<fig>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525044214im_/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/files/2011/03/papers2-500x475.jpg" xlink:title="papers2" />
</fig>
<p>This feature works similar to the plugins used by Endnote, Mendeley,
Zotero, etc., but in typical Papers fashion the implementation is much
nicer. The plugin is available to all applications, e.g. other word
processors besides Microsoft Word, your blogging software or your email
program.</p>
<p>The other big limitation of Papers 1 wasn’t so obvious when Papers
originally launched in 2007. But today most major reference managers
allow users to
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525044214/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/reference-manager-overview/">share
their references</ext-link> in private and/or public groups, as most
research is done in groups and most manuscripts are written by multiple
authors.</p>
<p>The sharing feature of Papers 2 is called
<bold><bold>Livfe</bold></bold>. It is not as complete as the sharing
features of some other reference managers (e.g. CiteULike or Mendeley).
It is for example not yet possible to upload a complete Papers library
to Livfe. And Livfe doesn’t have a web interface, but only works through
Papers.</p>
<fig>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525044214im_/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/files/2011/03/Papers-2a-500x243.jpg" xlink:title="Papers 2a" />
</fig>
<p>The difference between Papers 2 and other reference managers is not
so much the feature set. What sets Papers really apart is the love that
went into the design of the program. Papers doesn’t just get the job
done, it allows you to have fun searching for references or reading –
and now also writing – a paper. This makes Papers 2 a strong competitor
against some of the other established programs that for example have
more than 25 years of experience with reference management (Endnote),
think that reference management should be done as Open Source software
(Zotero), do everything in the browser (Refworks), or see reference
management primarily as a social application (Mendeley).</p>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
