<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Personal names around the world</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2011-08-14">
<day>14</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2011</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Yesterday I discovered (via a tweet by
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120610133741/https://twitter.com/#!/ostephens">Owen
Stephens</ext-link>) a very interesting document
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120610133741/http://www.w3.org/International/questions/qa-personal-names">Personal
names around the world</ext-link> that discusses the following
question:</p>
<p specific-use="wrapper">
  <disp-quote>
    <p>How do people’s names differ around the world, and what are the
    implications of those differences on the design of forms, databases,
    ontologies, etc. for the Web?</p>
  </disp-quote>
</p>
<p>The document was written by
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120610133741/http://rishida.net/">Richard
Ishida</ext-link>, Internationalization Activity Lead at the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120610133741/http://www.w3.org/International/">W3C</ext-link>
(World Wide Web Consortium). The document was published on July 26, and
Richard was seeking comments until August 7 before finalizing the
document.</p>
<p>The document is a good summary how names for people differ around the
world, e.g. multiple family names (Spain, Latin America), no family name
(Iceland), different ordering of names (China, Korea, Japan), non-latin
characters in names (many countries), and other issues.</p>
<p>The second part of the document makes a few suggestions of how these
variations in names could be handled on the web. The text should be
required reading for anybody who is designing databases that handle
international names – and there are a lot of them. A form that asks for
<bold><bold>first name</bold></bold>, <bold><bold>middle
initial</bold></bold> and <bold><bold>last name</bold></bold> will just
not be appropriate for a lot of people.</p>
<fig>
  <caption><p><italic><italic>Flickr photo by
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120610133741/http://www.flickr.com/photos/giantginkgo/37740313/">Giant
  Gingko</ext-link>.</italic></italic></p></caption>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120610133741im_/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/files/2011/08/noname.jpg" xlink:title="noname" />
</fig>
<p>I am lucky that my German name doesn’t contain any German umlauts (ä,
ö, ü) or the letter ß, so I haven’t had any bad (or funny) experiences
with my name. But I know that it can be a big problem for a lot of
people. The result is that people end up having several spellings for
their name, or write their name in ways that were not intended, e.g. a
hyphen between the two family names in Spain. The name is something very
personal, and I think the least we can do is to allow people to use
their name appropriately.</p>
<p>Science is probably no better or worse in this regard than other
domains. If we are lucky, we find a journal that prints our name
correctly, or have a database that understands that ü should be sorted
as ue. But for the most part, this seems to be an unresolved issue. And
I don’t want everybody to start using a first name and last name in that
order and only with ASCII or latin characters. That would be boring. So
please start thinking about this issue when you design systems that use
personal names, and use the W3C document by Richard Ishida as a starting
point.</p>
<p><italic><italic>Disclaimer: I sit on the Board of Directors of the
Open Researcher &amp; Contributor ID (ORCID) initiative which aims to
help solve this and related problems.</italic></italic></p>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
