<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Please keep it simple</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2014-09-16">
<day>16</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2014</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Doing scientific research is becoming increasingly complex, both in
terms of the tools and technologies used, and in the collaboration
across disciplines and locations that is increasingly commonplace. While
the way we write up and publish research is of course also very
different from 25 years ago, I would argue that our tools and services
haven’t quite evolved at the same pace.</p>
<p>Of course there are important trends that enable what the Royal
Institution
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://royalsociety.org/policy/projects/science-public-enterprise/Report/">calls</ext-link>
<italic>Science as an Open Enterprise</italic>, most importantly Open
Access, which has broken down many barriers for open collaboration. But
very few organizations - commercial or non-profit - see it as their
primary mission to make it easier for researchers to collaborate and
produce great science, in the sense that everything else is secondary
and this focus is really obvious to everyone.</p>
<p>The following are just some examples that make you laugh hard or cry
out loud:</p>
<list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
    <p>Finding relevant scholarly content. Why is still so hard?</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>Reading a paper. The majority of scholalry content is still not
    Open Access. It is embarassing how difficult it can be to get the
    fulltext paper from a subscription journal - too slow, too
    expensive, and sometimes even crippled in functionality.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>Creating figures for publication. This process is still so
    painful that it hurts. And publishers often create artificial
    limitations in file type (TIFF or Postscript) and file size (10
    MB??).</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>Licenses for scholarly content. We don’t need choice, but a few
    licenses that everyone understands and that don’t hinder sharing and
    collaboration</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>Secure login. I can use my Facebook or Google login almost
    everywhere, but as a scholar I have a different username and
    password at my institution, funder, the various publishers I submit
    too, and the scholarly services I frequently use?</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>Citation styles. Why do we still have at least 3,000 styles?</p>
  </list-item>
</list>
<p>Citation styles is a perfect example of a problem that should have
been solved as soon as we made the switch to digital publishing. I can
travel through half of Europe without showing my passport, and using the
same currency, but I need to reformat citations every time I submit to a
different journal? And I have to use the same tool for this as my
coauthors, as the different reference managers don’t work with each
other?</p>
<p>Too often there are other intentions at work in parallel. While
notable, they sometimes stand in conflict with the goal of making a
researcher’s life easier. A perfect example is the manuscript submission
process. In parallel to the tools getting better and easier to use, the
demands on the author seem to be increasing at an even greater rate,
both in the data and metadata he or she should provide, and in the work
submitting authors are asked to do that traditionally have been done by
publishers. Another good example are peer review and evaluation. The
proportion of time spent doing research vs. time spent doing
administrative work seems to decreasing and not increasing.</p>
<p>I wish more people and organizations would stand up and state that
keeping it simple is their primary goal.</p>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
