<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Please keep it simple: citations, links and
references</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2014-10-01">
<day>1</day>
<month>10</month>
<year>2014</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>In my
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://martinfenner.ghost.io/2014/09/16/please-keep-it-simple/">last
post</ext-link> I wrote about the importance of keeping things simple in
scholarly publishing, today I want to go into more detail with one
example: citations in scholarly documents.</p>
<fig>
  <caption><p>LEGO scientists discuss how they can cite their
  data</p></caption>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="https://martinfenner.ghost.io/content/images/2021/01/lego_discussion.jpg" xlink:title="" />
</fig>
<p>Citations are an essential part of scholarly documents, and they are
summarized in the references section at the end of the article or book
chapter. The problem is that not everything that is cited in a scholarly
document ends up in the references list. Examples of this include:</p>
<list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
    <p>web links, e.g. to reagents or other resources</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>identifiers for biological databases such as GenBank that are
    typically included in the text as identifiers or as links</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>footnotes with links to external resources</p>
  </list-item>
</list>
<p>In other words: we are not consistent in how we cite other content.
And this is a problem because we are making it more difficult than
necessary for authors, publishers and everyone else to handle these
various citation flavors and, more importantly, we are loosing citations
along the way. This is a particular problem for data citation, as the
seminal 2013 paper by Kafkas et al. (Kafkas, Kim, &amp; McEntyre, 2013)
has shown for citations to the three biological databases ENA (European
Nucleotide Archive), PDB and Uniprot:</p>
<list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
    <p>there is a large numbers of accession numbers in the Open Access
    subset of PubMed Central (e.g. 160,112 ENA accession numbers for
    papers published up until June 2012)</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>text mining using the
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/webservices/whatizit/">Whatizit</ext-link>
    tool can retrieve most of these identifiers</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>there is only partial overlap between database identifiers
    annotated by publishers and database identifiers found by text
    mining</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>the overlap is even smaller between papers citing database
    identifiers, and papers cited in biological databases such as
    ENA</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>the study was limited to Open Access journals, as only for them
    the fulltext articles could be text mined</p>
  </list-item>
</list>
<fig>
  <caption><p>Comparison between article-to-database and database to
  citations (Kafkas et al., 2013).</p></caption>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://martinfenner.ghost.io/content/images/2021/01/ena_overlap.png" xlink:title="" />
</fig>
<p>In other words, even though including identifiers for biological
databases has been an accepted community standard that every author and
publisher is following for a long time, the proper citation of these
identifiers is still often broken. The picture doesn’t seem to be any
better for DOIs for datasets: while they are fairly common by now, their
use in scholarly articles differs widely from appearance in the
references list to links in the materials and methods section to no
mention at all.</p>
<p>There are various ways how this can be fixed (e.g. requiring authors
to use biological database identifiers in a consistent way, better text
mining tools, opening up subscription content to text mining), but the
best solution is the simplest one: every citation in a paper should go
into the references list. As an example I have added the ENA mRNA U65091
(Shioda, Fenner, &amp; Isselbacher, 1997) - something I worked on a long
time ago - to the references list of this post.</p>
<sec id="technology">
  <title>Technology</title>
  <p>For this to work, it is essential that reference managers - the
  software authors use to generate the references list - properly
  support citations to data, including biological databases. It appears
  that all major reference managers support datasets as reference type
  and there is good community agreement what a data citation should look
  like
  (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.force11.org/datacitation">Joint
  Declaration of Data Citation Principles</ext-link>). What is missing
  is support for easily importing the required metadata for these
  datasets, and reference managers use two approaches for this:</p>
  <list list-type="bullet">
    <list-item>
      <p>query external databases via API and pull in the required
      metadata (e.g. Papers, Endnote)</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>browse to the webpage describing the database entry and import
      the metadata via bookmarklet/web importer (e.g. Zotero,
      Mendeley)</p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
  <p>Both approaches require custom code for every database. Whereas
  many reference managers use Citation Style Language
  (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://citationstyles.org/">CSL</ext-link>)
  as a standard way to format references, no such standard exists for
  web importers. Which means that every reference manager has to
  implement this separately, and most of them are not open source
  software so that the community could help.</p>
  <p>PLOS Labs is holding a
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ploslabs.org/citation-hackathon/">Citation
  Hackathon</ext-link> on October 18 in their San Francisco office.
  While I can’t attend in person, I want to contribute to this hackathon
  in three ways:</p>
  <list list-type="bullet">
    <list-item>
      <p>do an evaluation of how the reference managers Papers, Mendeley
      and Zotero (the three reference managers I use) support citations
      to the biological databases ENA, PDB and Uniprot and what is
      missing</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>look at existing aggregators of this information (e.g.
      <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://identifiers.org/">Identifiers.org</ext-link>)
      to figure out whether the import process can be simplified</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>start work on Zotero
      <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.zotero.org/support/dev/translators/coding#web_translators">web
      translators</ext-link> for these three databases. Zotero is open
      source software and the web translators are written in
      Javascript</p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
  <p>Please contact me if you are interested in helping with this, e.g.
  with a joint virtual hackathon on the 18th (or in person in London or
  Cambridge on October 15 if that works better).</p>
  <p>Together with
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://twitter.com/IanMulvany">Ian
  Mulvany</ext-link> from eLife and others from Papers and Mendeley we
  have also submitted a proposal for a pre-conference workshop/hackathon
  for the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.force11.org/meetings/force2015">Force2015
  Conference</ext-link> in January to work on this for a broader set of
  databases, which should for example also include software
  repositories. One question is how we properly handle the citation of
  large numbers of datasets (1000s to millions), we could for example
  allow a range of identifiers in a citation. We also need tools to
  convert identifiers and links in existing documents to proper
  references, something that we
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://martinfenner.ghost.io/2013/06/24/citations-in-markdown-part-3/">have
  also discussed on this blog</ext-link>, and we need to discuss how our
  bibliographic file formats (e.g. bibtex) support these citation types.
  I
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://martinfenner.ghost.io/2013/07/30/citeproc-yaml-for-bibliographies/">said
  before</ext-link> that I am a big fan of Citeproc YAML (or JSON, the
  bibliographic format used by CSL) as bibliographic exchange format,
  and I know that the PLOS Labs hackathon will also touch on this.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="community">
  <title>Community</title>
  <p>While adding reference manager support for a wider range of
  citations is the first step, the bigger challenge is community
  support. I don’t think that it is a big mental jump for an author to
  use the reference manager to cite a biological database rather than
  typing in the identifier directly in the text (the hard work is
  registering the identifier in the first place), but this needs support
  by the community, and in particular journal editors. The important
  message is that citations should be done in a consistent way and
  authors don’t have to think about doing this differently for datasets
  or other relevant resources, or different publishers implementing this
  differently. I think the paper by Kafkas et al. (2013) clearly shows
  that our current recommendations for adding identifiers to biological
  databases is broken, and that we need to do something if we take data
  citation seriously.</p>
  <p>There are several concerns about adding every citation to the
  references list. One of them is that we shouldn’t mix citations of
  scholarly articles with citations of other things, e.g. research data.
  I would argue that not only are we seeing an increasing number of
  citations to other resources in reference lists (Yang, Han, Ding,
  &amp; Song, 2012), but that we can of course group citations by
  citation type, in addition to the sorting by appearance in the text or
  last name of first author that is common now.</p>
  <p>Another concern is that citations of datasets are something else
  that citations to scholarly articles, because the former are typically
  citations of content created by the same group of people at the time
  the journal article was also created. I would argue that again we can
  highlight this by how we display the references, and that I hope that
  this changes once data citation becomes more widespread.</p>
  <p>What should or should not be cited in a scholarly document is of
  course a big discussion topic. What I am arguing is that everything
  that is cited should go into the references list, but that doesn’t
  change at all what should be cited. Personal communications are an
  example of something that should probably not be cited and therefore
  should also not go into the references list.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="references">
  <title>References</title>
  <p>Kafkas, Ş., Kim, J.-H., &amp; McEntyre, J. R. (2013). Database
  Citation in Full Text Biomedical Articles. <italic>PLoS ONE</italic>.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0063184">https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0063184</ext-link></p>
  <p>Shioda, T., Fenner, M. H., &amp; Isselbacher, K. J. (1997). Mus
  musculus melanocyte-specific gene 1 (msg1) mRNA, complete cds. ENA.
  Retrieved from
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/ena/data/view/U65091">http://www.ebi.ac.uk/ena/data/view/U65091</ext-link></p>
  <p>Yang, S., Han, R., Ding, J., &amp; Song, Y. (2012). The
  distribution of Web citations. <italic>Information Processing &amp;
  Management</italic>, <italic>48</italic>(4), 779–790.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://doi.org/10.1016/j.ipm.2011.10.002">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ipm.2011.10.002</ext-link></p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
