<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>PLoS One: Interview with Peter Binfield</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2009-08-15">
<day>15</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2009</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>At
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002113207/http://network.nature.com/people/mfenner/blog/2009/07/10/i-was-at-scibarcamp-palo-alto">SciBar
Camp Palo Alto last month</ext-link>, Peter Binfield from
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002113207/http://www.plosone.org/">PLoS
ONE</ext-link> gave a very interesting presentation on
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002113207/http://friendfeed.com/scibarcamp/3577ed2e/peter-binfield-article-level-metric-from-plos">Article-level
metrics from the PLoS perspective</ext-link>. Particularly interesting
was his announcement that <italic><italic>PLoS</italic></italic>
journals will provide usage data (HTML pageviews, PDF and XML downloads)
for all their articles in September. Usage data, like
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002113207/http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0006022">all
measures of scientific impact</ext-link>, have their problems, but they
are a welcome addition to citation-based metrics.</p>
<p>I’ve interviewed Pete to ask him not only about article-level
metrics, but also about the publishing model of <italic><italic>PLoS
ONE</italic></italic> and how these two relate to each other.</p>
<sec id="1-can-you-describe-what-plos-one-is-and-does">
  <title>1. Can you describe what PLoS ONE is and does?</title>
  <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002113207/http://www.plosone.org/">PLoS
  ONE</ext-link> is an Open Access, scholarly, peer reviewed journal for
  all of science. We will be three years old in December 2009, but
  already we are the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002113207/http://poeticeconomics.blogspot.com/2009/07/dramatic-growth-of-plos-one-soon-to-be.html">third
  largest journal (of any type) in the world</ext-link>, publishing
  approximately 4,600 articles in 2009 alone and almost doubling in
  volume every year. We are online only (publishing in HTML, XML and
  PDF) and we publish daily (about 20 articles a day at present). In my
  view <italic><italic>PLoS ONE</italic></italic> is the most dynamic,
  innovative and exciting journal in the world, and I am proud to work
  on it.</p>
  <p>In many ways <italic><italic>PLoS ONE</italic></italic> operates
  like any other journal however it diverges in several important
  respects. The founding principle of <italic><italic>PLoS
  ONE</italic></italic> was that there are certain aspects of publishing
  which are best conducted pre-publication and certain aspects which are
  best conducted post-publication. The advent of online publishing has
  allowed us to take a step back and re-evaluate these aspects of how we
  publish research, without the burden of centuries of tradition. In
  this way, we have been able to experiment with new ways of doing
  things which may result in dramatic improvements in the entire process
  of scholarly publication.</p>
  <p>The most important thing which has come out of this premise is that
  unlike almost every other journal in the world, we make no judgment
  call whatsoever on the “impact” or “significance” or “interest level”
  of any submission. What this means is that if an article appropriately
  reports on well-conducted science, and if it passes our peer review
  process (which determines whether it deserves to join the scientific
  literature) then we will publish it. In this way, no author should
  ever receive the message that their article is scientifically sound
  but “not interesting enough” for our journal, or that their article is
  “only suited to a specialized audience”. As a result, we short circuit
  the vicious cycle of submit to a “top tier” journal; get reviewed; get
  rejected; submit to the next journal down the list; repeat until
  accepted and we are therefore able to place good science into the
  public domain as promptly as possible, with the minimum of burden on
  the academic community.</p>
  <p>The most recent example of the way in which we separate
  pre-publication activity from post-publication activity is with the
  development of our
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002113207/http://everyone.plos.org/tag/article-level-metrics/">Article-Level
  Metrics program</ext-link>. <italic><italic>Article-level
  metrics</italic></italic> start from the assumption that the best way
  to measure the worth of an article is to look at the actual article
  itself (and not the journal it happens to have been published in).
  Following from this, it seems obvious that the best way to evaluate
  any article is to make use of the collective opinion of all experts in
  the field (and not a small number of peer reviewers, or a small number
  of people who ultimately go on to cite the article). An evaluation of
  this type (which requires that people actually read, and then act in a
  variety of ways, on the article) can only be done after the article is
  published (and not before, as happens when a journal rejects a paper
  because it thinks it is not “impactful” enough). Therefore, our
  development of new tools to facilitate the post-publication evaluation
  of individual articles is a great example of us separating out what is
  most appropriately conducted pre-publication vs post-publication.</p>
  <p>I have gone into some detail on these issues in a recent peer
  reviewed paper –
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002113207/http://conferences.aepic.it/index.php/elpub/elpub2009/paper/view/114">PLoS
  One: background, future development, and article-level
  metrics</ext-link> and I would also recommend Shirley Wu’s excellent
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002113207/http://shirleywho.wordpress.com/2009/08/06/the-evolution-of-scientific-impact/">recent
  blog post on this topic</ext-link>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="2-can-you-describe-what-ambra-topaz-is-and-does">
  <title>2. Can you describe what Ambra/Topaz is and does?</title>
  <p>Basically Ambra is our publishing platform, which runs on top of
  the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002113207/http://everyone.plos.org/2009/05/13/all-plos-titles-now-on-the-same-publishing-platform/">Topaz</ext-link>
  infrastructure. For the full technical detail, the best information is
  found
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002113207/http://ambraproject.org/">here</ext-link>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="3-can-you-talk-a-little-bit-more-about-the-post-publication-features-of-ambra-topaz">
  <title>3. Can you talk a little bit more about the post-publication
  features of Ambra/Topaz?</title>
  <p>Once an article is published, our platform allows users to leave
  feedback directly on the article. We were among the first journals to
  allow this, and we remain somewhat unique in this respect, although
  the concept is gaining broader acceptance and similar functionality is
  starting to appear at other publishers sites. Specifically, we allow
  users to leave a Note inline with a specific selection of text; or
  they can leave a general Comment on the entire article; or they can
  Star rate the article (on a 5 point scale in 3 categories). Comments
  and Notes form discussion threads, and users can then engage in debate
  on the points raised.</p>
  <p>Users may not be anonymous, they must follow our guidelines for
  civilized academic debate, and when leaving feedback they are
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002113207/http://www.plosone.org/static/commentGuidelines.action">asked
  to declare any competing interests</ext-link>. I want to make it clear
  that the post-publication functionality that we provide is not
  intended to provide post-publication peer review – it is
  post-publication discourse and feedback. All
  <italic><italic>PLoS</italic></italic> titles now share this same
  functionality.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="4-are-other-publishers-besides-plos-using-the-ambra-topaz-platform">
  <title>4. Are other publishers besides PLoS using the Ambra/Topaz
  platform?</title>
  <p>None that we are aware of although the NIH has an internal project.
  But Topaz is open source, so please contact us if you want to use
  it!</p>
</sec>
<sec id="5-what-article-level-metrics-does-plos-one-provide">
  <title>5. What article-level metrics does PLoS ONE provide?</title>
  <p>As of today (August 2009), on every article, in every
  <italic><italic>PLoS</italic></italic> title we provide:</p>
  <list list-type="bullet">
    <list-item>
      <p>Number of citations (as measured by
      <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002113207/http://www.scopus.com/">Scopus</ext-link>
      and
      <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002113207/http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/">PubMedCentral</ext-link>)</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Number of social bookmarks (as recorded by
      <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002113207/http://www.citeulike.org/">CiteULike</ext-link>
      and
      <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002113207/http://www.connotea.org/">Connotea</ext-link>)</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Number of star ratings left by users on our system</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Notes, Comments and any replies, as left by users of our
      system</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Number of blog posts written about the article (as counted by
      the blog aggregators
      <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002113207/http://www.postgenomic.com/">Postgenomic</ext-link>,
      <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002113207/http://blogs.nature.com/">Nature
      Blogs</ext-link> and
      <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002113207/http://www.bloglines.com/">Bloglines</ext-link>)</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Specific trackbacks to the article from any web page using our
      trackback protocol</p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
  <p>In September we will be adding additional citation data as measured
  by
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002113207/http://www.crossref.org/">CrossRef</ext-link>
  and, most significantly, the online usage for each article (going back
  to the original publication date and reported on a monthly basis,
  broken down by HTML pageviews, PDF downloads, and XML downloads). This
  development in particular is very exciting – no other publisher has
  made this data available for such a large corpus of articles.</p>
  <p>After this, the next data source we will add will be blog coverage
  as aggregated by
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002113207/http://researchblogging.org/">ResearchBlogging.org</ext-link>,
  and in subsequent months we will be adding other metrics as and when
  we can identify high quality sources which meet our criteria.</p>
  <p><italic><italic>Article-level metrics</italic></italic> are a major
  development for <italic><italic>PLoS</italic></italic> and we believe
  that we are unique in the publishing industry with the transparent
  provision of such a range of <italic><italic>article-level
  metrics</italic></italic>. No other publisher provides as much (or
  any, in most cases) article-level data in such a comprehensive and
  open manner. It is our belief that once we have demonstrated what is
  possible, as well as the power of these metrics, the academic
  community will quickly begin to expect, and demand, this level of
  information from all journals. As a result the very nature of research
  reporting and evaluation will be improved as a result.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="6-how-do-article-level-metrics-fit-in-with-how-plos-one-conducts-peer-review">
  <title>6. How do article-level metrics fit in with how PLoS ONE
  conducts peer review</title>
  <p>We peer review all submissions for their
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002113207/http://www.plosone.org/static/review.action">scientific
  content</ext-link>, but we do NOT peer review them in order to
  determine whether they are high or low impact (or interest or
  significance or relevance etc). Therefore, from the reader’s point of
  view, when you encounter a <italic><italic>PLoS ONE</italic></italic>
  article you do not necessarily know how impactful, or interesting, or
  significant, or relevant that article might be (without actually
  reading it!). In the traditional model, you would have some indication
  as to the likely importance of an article by a knowledge of the
  journal in which it was published in (although we argue that this way
  of determining quality is actually
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002113207/http://www.plos.org/cms/node/478">one
  of the worst methods you could use</ext-link>), however in
  <italic><italic>PLoS ONE</italic></italic> all you know is that the
  article is scientifically and methodologically sound (which are the
  only questions that our peer review process asks). Therefore,
  <italic><italic>article-level metrics</italic></italic> provide the
  reader with an indication as to the worth of an article once it is
  published. Until today, people have effectively said: this article was
  published in journal X, therefore knowing this one fact, I now know
  that the article is excellent/good/average/poor. I think that any sane
  person who considered that statement would realize how unscientific it
  was. With the advent of <italic><italic>article-level
  metrics</italic></italic>, a reader can now say “this article was
  published as part of the scientific literature, it is irrelevant which
  journal it was published in as I have now been given a variety of
  information about the article itself which will help me decide whether
  the article is excellent / good / average / poor for my own
  purposes”.</p>
  <p>Therefore, <italic><italic>article-level metrics</italic></italic>
  do not supplant peer review and they also do not represent
  post-publication peer review. However they do provide the reader with
  new and valuable ways to do the post-publication evaluation and
  filtering of journal content.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="7-what-are-plos-one-subject-areas-or-portals">
  <title>7. What are PLoS ONE subject areas or portals?</title>
  <p>We actually have several ways to ‘parse’ our content by
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002113207/http://www.plosone.org/static/browse.action">topic</ext-link>:
  All content is assigned to one or more of our 52 topic areas (for
  example Pathology or Oncology). These topics are assigned by the
  authors themselves and an article can appear in more than one topic.
  Having made that classification, readers can then
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002113207/http://www.plosone.org/article/browse.action">browse
  the topics</ext-link> or subscribe to
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002113207/http://www.plosone.org/static/rssFeeds.action">an
  RSS feed per topic</ext-link>.</p>
  <p>However, we appreciate that this is not a very flexible way to find
  content that doesn’t easily fall under our existing taxonomy
  structure. Therefore, we also have the ability to aggregate our
  articles into
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002113207/http://www.plosone.org/article/browseVolume.action">Collections</ext-link>.
  A Collection is literally just an aggregation tool (post-publication)
  – articles are still published as part of the normal run of the
  journal, but can then be assigned to join a Collection where they will
  also appear as part of a collection of related articles. For example,
  right now we have a very popular
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002113207/http://www.plosone.org/article/browseIssue.action?issue=info%3Adoi%2F10.1371%2Fissue.pone.c01.i02">Paleontology
  Collection</ext-link>. As we publish new Paleontology articles they
  get added to this Collection to form a single location for all
  relevant articles in the field. This Collection functionality can also
  be used for the output of a single research effort, and an example of
  this is our
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002113207/http://www.plosone.org/article/browseIssue.action?issue=info%3Adoi%2F10.1371%2Fissue.pone.c01.i01">Stress-Induced
  Depression and Comorbidities Collection</ext-link> which effectively
  replicated a “Special Issue” of a journal, and contained all the
  articles we published as written by the EUMOOD Research Consortia.
  Collections can be static, or can build up over time, and articles can
  appear in multiple Collections – as such they represent a very
  flexible way to re-present our content.</p>
  <p>Then we have <italic><italic>PLoS</italic></italic> Hubs, which are
  under development right now. We see a Hub as a way to aggregate
  journal articles (along with other types of content) about a given
  topic into a single location. Once aggregated, we can then provide
  various community specific tools and services around this content. A
  Hub should not be thought of as a portal or an overlay journal – the
  distinguishing feature will be that a Hub will physically contain (and
  not just link out to) as much content as possible. Clearly, the
  easiest way to achieve this is by making the content Open Access, and
  so we also see Hubs as an opportunity to demonstrate the power of an
  Open Access copyright license. At the moment there is only one Hub
  (the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002113207/http://clinicaltrials.ploshubs.org/home.action">PLoS
  Clinical Trials Hub</ext-link>) but this is a rather old
  implementation of the concept and only contains
  <italic><italic>PLoS</italic></italic> content – therefore we are
  proactively working on a new release which will include more of the
  functionality described above.</p>
  <p>Future developments to our platform will involve the ability to tag
  articles (perhaps by some combination of curated and user generated
  tags) which will provide yet another way to dynamically aggregate the
  content.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="8-how-has-the-ambra-topaz-platform-handled-the-enormous-growth-of-plos-one">
  <title>8. How has the Ambra/Topaz platform handled the enormous growth
  of PLoS ONE?</title>
  <p>Great! We had a few architecture issues in the past due to the
  bleeding edge nature of the platform, but all seven of our journals
  have now migrated to the same platform and no substantial issues have
  come up since the we migrated our Community Journals (back in early
  2008).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="9-what-are-your-responsibilities-at-plos">
  <title>9. What are your responsibilities at PLoS?</title>
  <p>I am the Managing Editor of <italic><italic>PLoS
  ONE</italic></italic> (one of seven titles at
  <italic><italic>PLoS</italic></italic>). Although this position is an
  Editorial one, it is the position which is ultimately responsible for
  everything associated with the journal. By this I mean that although
  other departments may not report into me, I am ultimately responsible
  for the marketing, production, operations, web etc of the journal. If
  we have a problem with any aspect of the journal, it is me that makes
  sure it gets solved!</p>
</sec>
<sec id="10-what-did-you-do-before-starting-to-work-at-plos">
  <title>10. What did you do before starting to work at PLoS?</title>
  <p>Well, I am a physicist from way back – I have a first degree in
  Physics with Astrophysics and a PhD in Underwater Optical Holography
  (which I always tell people sounds a lot more interesting than it
  was!). After my PhD I realized I wasn’t interested in a life in
  academia and so I moved into Academic Publishing, which allowed me to
  stay in touch with academia and also to interact with leading
  researchers conducting the latest research. I started out at Institute
  of Physics Publishing, in Bristol UK, doing book acquisitions, then I
  moved to Holland to work for Kluwer Academic Publishers (KAP) to start
  up a reference work program for them. Via a series of moves I ended up
  running the KAP Earth, Environmental and Plant Sciences division – a
  large portfolio of books, reference works and journals in those areas.
  Around the time that KAP merged with Springer I moved into Business
  Development for a year or so, which was an interesting period working
  on Springer’s
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002113207/http://www.springer.com/open+access/open+choice">Open
  Choice</ext-link> program, online reference works and journal
  acquisitions among others. Then I left Springer, and also Holland, to
  move to California (my wife is from San Diego) where I worked for SAGE
  Publications, just North of LA, for 3 years. There I ran the SAGE US
  Journals division, which was made up of some 200 or so journals,
  mostly in the Social Sciences. In that position a large part of the
  job involved bidding on society titles, to publish them under
  contract. And then, finally, in March 2008 I moved to San Francisco,
  to work for <italic><italic>PLoS</italic></italic> and run
  <italic><italic>PLoS ONE</italic></italic>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="11-do-you-want-to-talk-about-future-plans-for-ambra-topaz">
  <title>11. Do you want to talk about future plans for
  Ambra/Topaz?</title>
  <p>The list of upcoming projects includes:</p>
  <list list-type="bullet">
    <list-item>
      <p>More article-level metrics development</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>RDFa implementation</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Automatic article relationships</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Semantic enhancement</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>REST-based API</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>The ingest and publication of many types of content / data
      (structured and unstructured)</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Tags</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Enhanced search and browse functionality</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>A new process to submit articles directly to PubMed Central and
      other external repositories</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Direct access to our underlying triple store (sparql endpoint,
      RDFa)</p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
