<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Publication bias in clinical trials</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2009-11-18">
<day>18</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2009</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Last week the <italic><italic>New England Journal of
Medicine</italic></italic> (<italic><italic>NEJM</italic></italic>)
published a paper on selective outcome reporting in clinical trials
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003094331/http://dx.doi.org/10.1056/NEJMsa0906126">Vedula
et al. 2009</ext-link>). The primary and secondary outcome(s) of a
clinical trial could for example be survival in cancer patients or rate
of heart attacks and other cardiovascular events in patients taking
cholesterol-lowering drugs. These outcomes are defined in the study
protocol before the first patient is treated, and whether or not the
primary outcome is reached (using statistical testing) defines whether a
trial was positive or negative. The study protocol is approved by an
institutional review board (IRB) and can only be changed later (and that
includes changes in the protocol-defined outcomes) if again approved by
the IRB.</p>
<p>The study in the <italic><italic>NEJM</italic></italic> examined the
outcomes of 20 clinical trials for the drug gabapentin using internal
documents of the drug companies Pfizer and Parke-Davis, and compared
them to the outcomes reported for those trials that were published as
peer-reviewed papers. The internal company documents were obtained as
the result of litigation in which the company admitted guilt for
off-label marketing (i.e. marketing for uses that were not approved by
the Food and Drug Administration) of gabapentin.</p>
<p>12 of the 20 trials were published as peer-reviewed papers. In 8 of
these 12 papers the primary outcome differed from the primary outcome
defined in the protocol. New primary outcomes were introduced in 6
papers, and protocol-defined primary outcomes were not reported in 5
papers. Trials with primary outcomes that were not significant were
either not reported as full paper or were reported with a changed
primary outcome.</p>
<p>Selective outcome reporting has also been reported by other authors
and is not limited to trials funded by drug companies (Chan 2004).
Selective outcome reporting is a major problem because it a) distorts
our scientific knowledge and b) is unethical as it involves research on
human subjects. This could for example lead to repeated studies of a
clearly ineffective or harmful drug or intervention. The distortion of
our scientific knowledge by selective outcome reporting in scientific
journals is also a concern for research in other areas. Confirmation of
important research findings by independent groups is important, but a
lot of research is probably repeated simply because negative results
were not published. Some of these reporting biases could be avoided by
making more unpublished research data available, either by
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003094331/http://usefulchem.blogspot.com/">Open
Notebook Science</ext-link> or by publishing “unexciting negative”
findings in peer-review journals or preprint archives such as
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003094331/http://precedings.nature.com/">Nature
Precedings</ext-link>.</p>
<p>Clinical medicine tries to solve the problem of publication bias by
making public registration of clinical trials mandatory before patient
enrollment. This registration is required by most major medical journals
since 2004 (De Angelis 2004). U.S. legislation also requires clinical
trial registration and since 2008
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003094331/http://network.nature.com/people/mfenner/blog/2008/08/02/fdaaa-push-to-open-data-in-clinical-medicine">FDAAA:
Push to open data in clinical medicine</ext-link>) this includes outcome
reporting within 12 months after data for the last subject were received
in the publicly available
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003094331/http://www.clinicaltrials.gov/">Clinicaltrials.gov</ext-link>
database. These efforts should ensure ethical standards of clinical
research, and help to avoid the kinds of biases reported in the paper by
Vedula et al.</p>
<p>Clinical trial registries obviously also serve other purposes, as
they help interested patients and their relatives and treating
physicians to find clinical trials they want to participate in, and they
help researchers and clinicians to do a systematic overview of the
ongoing research in a particular field. Just as there are centralized
databases (e.g.
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003094331/http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/">PubMed
Central</ext-link> and the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003094331/http://www.controlled-trials.com/mrct/">Current
Controlled Trials</ext-link> metaRegister of controlled trials) and
institutional repositories for full-text papers, there are also both
central (e.g.
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003094331/http://clinicaltrials.gov/">Clinicaltrials.gov</ext-link>
– Both PubMed Central and Clinicaltrials.gov are efforts by the U.S.
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003094331/http://www.nih.gov/">National
Institutes of Health</ext-link>) and institutional clinical trial
registries. But in contrast to institutional repositories, there are no
standard software tools available that an institution can use. I am
involved in building a
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003094331/http://www.mh-hannover.de/studien">clinical
trial registry for our institution</ext-link>, and the effort is both
technically demanding, and socially challenging. The information in a
clinical trial registry is constantly changing and we need to keep the
efforts required by the individual researchers at a mininum. We also
have to walk a fine line of what information can be made publicly
available, and here we follow the standards provided by both
Clinicaltrials.gov and the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003094331/http://www.who.int/ictrp/en/">WHO</ext-link>.</p>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003094331/https://eudract.emea.europa.eu/">EudraCT</ext-link>,
the mandatory European clinical trials registry is regretably not
available to the public.</p>
<sec id="references">
  <title>References</title>
  <p>Vedula, S., Bero, L., Scherer, R., &amp; Dickersin, K. (2009).
  Outcome Reporting in Industry-Sponsored Trials of Gabapentin for
  Off-Label Use <italic>New England Journal of Medicine, 361</italic>
  (20), 1963-1971
  https://doi.org/<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003094331/http://dx.doi.org/10.1056/NEJMsa0906126">10.1056/NEJMsa0906126</ext-link></p>
  <p>Chan, A.-W. (2004). Outcome reporting bias in randomized trials
  funded by the Canadian Institutes of Health Research. Canadian Medical
  Association Journal, 171(7), 735–740.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1503/cmaj.1041086">https://doi.org/10.1503/cmaj.1041086</ext-link></p>
  <p>De Angelis, C., Drazen, J. M., Frizelle, F. A., Haug, C., Hoey, J.,
  Horton, R., … Weyden, M. B. V. D. (2004). Clinical Trial Registration:
  A Statement from the International Committee of Medical Journal
  Editors. New England Journal of Medicine, 351(12), 1250–1251.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1056/nejme048225">https://doi.org/10.1056/nejme048225</ext-link></p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
