<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Pubmed and other Annoyances in the Paper Writing
Process</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2008-03-31">
<day>31</day>
<month>3</month>
<year>2008</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Anna's
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120612090300/http://network.nature.com/blogs/user/U2929A0EA/2008/03/22/i-am-not-yelling-not-out-loud">recent
post</ext-link> about her struggles with Pubmed searches reminded me
that there is still a lot that could and should be done to improve the
paper (or thesis) writing process. This is my personal list of major
annoyances:</p>
<list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
    <p><bold>Pubmed</bold>. This topic has been extensively covered in
    Anna's post.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p><bold>Bibliographies</bold>. The process from finding a paper in
    Pubmed to storing it into your bibliographic software to downloading
    and storing the PDF to creating a bibliography in a paper is
    extremely complicated. In my case this process involves a web
    browser,
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120612090300/http://www.endnote.com/">Endnote</ext-link>,
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120612090300/http://mekentosj.com/papers/">Papers</ext-link>,
    a PDF viewer and Microsoft Word.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p><bold>Writing a paper</bold>. The idiosyncrasies of Microsoft
    Word (the tool probably used by most people for paper writing) would
    make for a different blog post. Microsoft Word can do many things
    that are never needed in a scientific manuscript, but lacks features
    that are important. And it likes to crash on long texts.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p><bold>Collective Writing</bold>. The process of having several
    people working on a manuscript and managing different versions is
    overly complicated.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p><bold>Paper submission</bold>. The online tools such as
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120612090300/http://www.editorialmanager.com/homepage/home.htm">Editorial
    Manager</ext-link> are nice, but there is still too much formatting
    work required (in a format that is probably different depending on
    the journal).</p>
  </list-item>
</list>
<p>Interestingly, the way we do paper writing and paper submission has
changed a lot between ca. 1985 and 1995. Basically the transition from
analog to digital. Who still remembers Index Medicus, Current Contents,
copying papers in the library, Letraset for figure numbering, mailing
hard copies of manuscripts around, etc.?</p>
<p>But what has changed in the last 10-15 years? Probably not that much.
Web 2.0 is an overused term, but there is so much potential for
improvement in the area of manuscript writing. We should
<italic><italic>not</italic></italic> be satisfied with what Pubmed,
Endnote, Microsoft Word, etc. offer today. That is why I don't
understand some of the discussion surrounding Anna's blog post,
basically advising her to just sit down and learn her Pubmed stuff.</p>
<p>If that is not enough for you, some people have already taken the
next step:
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120612090300/http://pubs.nrc-cnrc.gc.ca/jchla/jchla29/c07-035.pdf">Web
3.0 and health librarians: an introduction</ext-link>.</p>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
