<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Reference Management with the iPad</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2010-10-06">
<day>6</day>
<month>10</month>
<year>2010</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>The iPad was released six months ago, and we already have several
reference managers available for the platform. Reading the PDF of a
scientific paper on an iPad is a positive experience, and to me very
different from reading the PDF on a regular computer. While this could
also be done with generic iPad PDF readers such as
<bold><bold>iBooks</bold></bold> or
<bold><bold>Goodreader</bold></bold>, reference managers make it much
easier to organize a large collection of PDF files.</p>
<sec id="citeulike">
  <title>CiteULike</title>
  <p>CiteULike is a browser-based reference manager and works on the
  iPad as expected – and this includes the bookmarklet. CiteULike is a
  good tool to collect references when browsing with the iPad. CiteULike
  doesn’t allow offline reading of PDF files. While you can read the
  HTML versions of papers with the iPad web browser, this requires not
  only online access, but often also access through a paywall.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20101016090748/http://www.citeulike.org/">More
  Info</ext-link></p>
</sec>
<sec id="papers-for-ipad">
  <title>Papers for iPad</title>
  <p>This was the first reference manager specifically designed for the
  iPad. Papers for Mac owners can synchronize all their references and
  fulltext PDF files. The functionality is similar to the Mac version
  and also includes a good PDF reader and searching for references in
  PubMed and other online databases. This makes Papers a good
  stand-alone solution that doesn’t depend on syncing to another
  applications.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20101016090748/http://mekentosj.com/papers/ipad/">More
  Info</ext-link> –
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20101016090748/http://itunes.apple.com/app/papers/id304655618?mt=8">iTunes</ext-link></p>
  <p>Mendeley Lite</p>
  <p>Mendeley Lite syncs with all references you store in your Mendeley
  web account. I personally prefer this approach as I don’t particularly
  like syncing between iPad and desktop computer. Just like Papers, this
  application works both on iPad and iPhone. You can’t directly add
  references to Mendeley Lite. Mendeley is currently the only
  application that has both a web-based and an iPad version. This
  increases the options, but probably also adds to user confusion. Add
  reference with the web-based version, sync, then read PDF in Mendeley
  Lite?
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20101016090748/http://itunes.apple.com/de/app/mendeley-reference-manager/id380669300?mt=8">iTunes</ext-link></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sente-viewer-for-ipad">
  <title>Sente Viewer for iPad</title>
  <p>Last Friday <bold><bold>Sente Viewer for iPad</bold></bold> was
  released. Similar to Papers and Mendeley, Sente Viewer for iPad
  synchronizes with the desktop version of the application. The
  application allows browsing of all synchronized references and reading
  of the associated fulltext PDF papers. The <bold><bold>Sente for
  iPad</bold></bold> application will be released later and will also
  allow adding and editing of references. I’m looking forward to
  “targeted browsing” which will capture both reference information and
  fulltext PDF files using a built-in web browser – another variation of
  reference manager integration with the web browser.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20101016090748/http://www.thirdstreetsoftware.com/site/iPadSente.html">More
  Info</ext-link> –
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20101016090748/http://itunes.apple.com/us/app/sente-viewer/id392355663?mt=8">iTunes</ext-link></p>
</sec>
<sec id="further-reading">
  <title>Further Reading</title>
  <p>Roderic Page has done
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20101016090748/http://iphylo.blogspot.com/2010/09/viewing-scientific-articles-on-ipad.html">a
  lot of writing</ext-link> about reading scientific papers on the iPad,
  including reviews for
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20101016090748/http://iphylo.blogspot.com/2010/08/viewing-scientific-articles-on-ipad_31.html">Papers
  for iPad</ext-link> and
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20101016090748/http://iphylo.blogspot.com/2010/08/viewing-scientific-articles-on-ipad_3052.html">Mendeley
  Lite</ext-link>. Wizfolio is another web-based reference manager that
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20101016090748/http://blog.wizfolio.com/index.php/2010/07/2-thumb-power-surfing-on-the-ipad/">works
  on the iPad</ext-link>.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
