<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>ResearcherID: Interview with Renny Guida</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2010-04-26">
<day>26</day>
<month>4</month>
<year>2010</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p><italic><italic>Open Researcher and Contributor ID</italic></italic>
or
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611094015/http://blogs.nature.com/mfenner/2010/01/03/orcid-or-how-to-build-a-unique-identifier-for-scientists-in-10-easy-steps">ORCID</ext-link>
is a community effort to standardize researcher identification. The
initiative was first announced last December, and is supported by a
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611094015/http://www.orcid.org/gallery.php">growing
number</ext-link> of publishers, scholarly societies and academic
institutions.
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611094015/http://science.thomsonreuters.com/">Thomson
Reuters</ext-link> is not only one of the founding members of the
initiative, but will also provide the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611094015/http://www.researcherid.com/">ResearcherID</ext-link>
technology as a starting point for building the
<italic><italic>ORCID</italic></italic> platform.</p>
<p>I asked <italic><italic>Renny Guida</italic></italic> from Thomson
Reuters a few questions about his thoughts on unique author identifiers
in general, and <italic><italic>ResearcherID</italic></italic> and
<italic><italic>ORCID</italic></italic> in particular.</p>
<fig>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611094015im_/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/files/2010/11/researcherid.jpg" xlink:title="" />
</fig>
<p><italic><italic>Members of the ResearcherID team (from left to
right): Renny Guida, Ellen Rotenberg, Chiu Chung and Deepak
Chaturvedi.</italic></italic></p>
<sec id="1-what-is-researcherid">
  <title>1. What is ResearcherID?</title>
  <p><italic><italic>ResearcherID</italic></italic> is a freely
  available system that helps the research community overcome the issues
  of individual name ambiguity and attribution. The system is available
  to everyone and allows a researcher to establish, maintain and control
  a biographic and bibliographic profile.</p>
  <fig>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611094015im_/http://images.isiknowledge.com/WOK48B3/images/RID/rid_logo.gif" xlink:title="" />
  </fig>
  <p>The system is the result of research that found that individual
  identity touches many parts of scholarly communications and that
  researcher’s and academic institutions were ready to take some
  ownership of the issue to ensure proper attribution of
  scholarship.</p>
  <p>The Registry is composed of biographical and bibliographic
  components which are accessible at the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611094015/http://www.researcherid.com/">researcherid.com</ext-link>
  web site. A web services API makes it possible for an institution or
  organization to create and use this information in their systems.</p>
  <p>The biographical component of the registry creates a unique
  identifier and persistent web location for each user. The system is
  designed to allow a researcher to control privacy and access to the
  information in their profile, even if the information was uploaded by
  the researcher’s institution. Researchers can enter and manage
  information about themselves, their work and their affiliations
  (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611094015/http://www.researcherid.com/rid/C-3246-2009">example
  record</ext-link>).</p>
  <p>The bibliographic component of
  <italic><italic>ResearcherID</italic></italic> allows researchers to
  connect articles, patents and other scholarly items to their profile.
  Items can be loaded from
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611094015/http://www.endnote.com/">EndNote</ext-link>,
  the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611094015/http://www.isiwebofknowledge.com/">Web
  of Science</ext-link> or in a text format into one of three lists.</p>
  <p>As I mentioned, a web service makes it possible for organizations
  to create and manage both biographic and bibliographic information for
  their faculty and researchers. Upload, download and search services
  make this possible. For example, David Palmer at the University of
  Hong Kong uses ResearcherID to create
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611094015/http://hub.hku.hk/rp/rp00023">identifiers
  for HKU researchers</ext-link>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="2-what-is-orcid-and-how-does-it-relate-to-researcherid">
  <title><italic><italic>2. What is ORCID, and how does it relate to
  ResearcherID?</italic></italic></title>
  <p>Open Researcher Contributor ID (ORCID) is an initiative to better
  understand how the issue of individual name ambiguity can be solved.
  Currently a cross section of the research community is discussing ways
  to overcome the issue with the hopes of establishing an open registry
  that will be used by the global research community.</p>
  <p>One of the lessons learned from Thomson Reuters’ development of
  <italic><italic>ResearcherID</italic></italic> is that issues of name
  ambiguity and attribution are problems bigger than any one
  organization can address. And, having multiple solutions to the
  problem will not meet the needs of researchers or the scholarly
  community. Based on <italic><italic>ResearcherID’s</italic></italic>
  innovation and success in addressing these issues, Thomson Reuters
  plans to offer <italic><italic>ORCID</italic></italic> the technology
  and infrastructure for managing the biographic registry.</p>
  <p>The initiative has grown from early 2009 conversations between
  <italic><italic>Thomson Reuters</italic></italic> and
  <italic><italic>Nature Publishing Group</italic></italic> into a
  global collaboration of academic institutions, research centers,
  funding agencies, scholarly societies and publishers. To date,
  everyone involved in the effort is volunteering their time and work is
  focused on the business and technical implications of creating an
  independent organization to manage an identity registry system. More
  information on the initiative can be found at the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611094015/http://www.orcid.org/">ORCID</ext-link>
  web site.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="3-there-are-numerous-other-initiatives-for-unique-researcher-identifiers-what-is-unique-about-researcherid">
  <title>3.There are numerous other initiatives for unique researcher
  identifiers. What is unique about ResearcherID?</title>
  <p>What is unique about <italic><italic>ResearcherID</italic></italic>
  is that it is a global initiative and not focused on any one
  organization, consortia, country or application. The system also
  ensures privacy and allows researchers to control their information.
  The <italic><italic>ResearcherID</italic></italic> is portable and can
  be included in authored works and used as a dynamic link on the
  researcher’s website.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="4-how-does-researcherid-integrate-with-other-thomson-reuters-products-and-outside-tools">
  <title>4. How does ResearcherID integrate with other Thomson Reuters
  products and outside tools?</title>
  <p>The system was designed to allow all users, independent of any
  Thomson Reuters subscriptions, to benefit from the application. All
  users have the ability to establish an identifier, create and manage a
  biographical profile, and manage a list of scholarly works.</p>
  <p>The <italic><italic>ResearcherID</italic></italic> system is
  closely coupled with EndNote and by May 2010, all ResearcherID users,
  independent of any Thomson Reuters subscriptions, will have access to
  the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611094015/http://www.endnoteweb.com/">web
  version of EndNote</ext-link>.</p>
  <p>For users having access to the <italic><italic>Web of
  Knowledge</italic></italic> there are a number of additional
  integration points:</p>
  <list list-type="bullet">
    <list-item>
      <p>Researchers can claim items from the <italic><italic>Web of
      Science</italic></italic> by either performing a search or using
      the
      <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611094015/http://images.isiknowledge.com/WOK46/help/WOS/h_da_sets.html">Distinct
      Author Sets</ext-link> feature that automatically clusters
      articles believed to be authored by the same person.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Researchers can claim items from any <italic><italic>Web of
      Knowledge</italic></italic> database.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>The ResearcherID system uses the <italic><italic>Web of
      Science</italic></italic> to automatically update the ResearcherID
      system with the times cited count.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p><italic><italic>Web of Science</italic></italic> times cited
      information is used to generate personal citation reports and the
      citation visualizations (currently being tested in
      <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611094015/http://wokinfo.com/researcherid/ridlabs/">ResearcherID
      labs</ext-link> environment) to visualize collaboration and
      citation networks.</p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
</sec>
<sec id="5-do-you-plan-to-continue-with-researcherid-once-orcid-is-fully-working">
  <title>5. Do you plan to continue with ResearcherID once ORCID is
  fully working?</title>
  <p>Our plans are to adapt and enhance
  <italic><italic>ResearcherID</italic></italic> to support
  <italic><italic>ORCID</italic></italic> and allow users access to
  personal citation functionality and services on our
  <italic><italic>Web of Knowledge</italic></italic> platform. Thomson
  Reuters is one of the catalysts of the
  <italic><italic>ORCID</italic></italic> initiative and is working with
  our colleagues to help <italic><italic>ORCID</italic></italic>
  succeed. We will fully support <italic><italic>ORCID</italic></italic>
  from the enhanced <italic><italic>ResearcherID</italic></italic>
  platform and other Thomson Reuters applications.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="6-what-would-be-the-benefits-of-using-a-unique-author-identifier-for-a-researcher">
  <title>6. What would be the benefits of using a unique author
  identifier for a researcher?</title>
  <p>The unique author identifier not only addresses the issues of name
  ambiguity and attribution but benefits the scholarly communication
  process by maintaining the link between the researchers and their
  scholarship. This link is critical given the proliferation of
  information available on the Web and the demand to find information in
  less time and with greater accuracy.</p>
  <p>The real benefit comes when all involved in the scholarly
  communications can leveraged the identifier to improve the process.
  Easier tenure review, better assessment of research output, more
  intelligent discovery tools, enhanced peer review systems and tools to
  maintain scholarly networks are some of the benefits of using a unique
  author identifier.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="7-where-do-you-see-the-biggest-obstacles-in-launching-a-universally-accepted-unique-identifier-for-researchers-technical-or-social">
  <title>7. Where do you see the biggest obstacles in launching a
  universally accepted unique identifier for researchers? Technical or
  social?</title>
  <p>I see two large obstacles. The first, and I believe most important,
  is the researchers perception of security and ownership. The system
  must allow researchers to control and manage their data.</p>
  <p>The second biggest obstacle is the sustainability of an
  organization that would provide the identity service.
  <italic><italic>ORCID</italic></italic> is proving that the community
  can work together to address the technicalities of a global identity
  system. And, while there are significant technical, privacy and other
  challenges, the initiative is making great progress. However, such a
  service requires resources and the system must be supported
  financially by the community.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="8-what-is-your-thinking-with-regards-to-automatically-assigning-unique-author-identifiers-to-papers-vs-authors-claiming-their-publications">
  <title>8. What is your thinking with regards to automatically
  assigning unique author identifiers to papers vs. authors claiming
  their publications?</title>
  <p>I see these as being two complementary and important services.
  Algorithmic clustering of papers is a common feature in many
  applications including the <italic><italic>Web of
  Science</italic></italic> and other bibliographic databases. For the
  most part, these clustering systems do a good job identifying a high
  percentage of papers for a particular author. However, because none of
  the industry’s algorithms are perfect, a claiming system that enables
  the researcher to associate all of their papers is an ideal complement
  and helps to complete a career profile of a researcher’s works.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="9-what-are-your-responsibilities-at-thomson-reuters">
  <title>9. What are your responsibilities at Thomson Reuters?</title>
  <p>My title is Director of eResearch Services. Some of my
  responsibilities include individual identity initiatives (ResearcherID
  and the Web of Science Distinct Author Sets clustering system), Web of
  Knowledge web services, inbound and outbound linking, current
  awareness and alerting systems, and
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611094015/http://www.projectcounter.org/about.html">COUNTER</ext-link>
  compliant usage reporting systems.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="10-what-did-you-do-before-working-at-thomson-reuters">
  <title>10. What did you do before working at Thomson Reuters?</title>
  <p>Prior to joining Thomson Reuters in 1997 I worked for the Datapro
  division of McGraw Hill in product development and for Xerox selling
  document management systems.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
