<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>RSS Feeds for Scholarly Authors</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2013-07-26">
<day>26</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Open Researcher &amp; Contributor ID
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://speakerdeck.com/mfenner/orcid-connecting-research-and-researchers-1">ORCID</ext-link>)
provides a persistent identifier for researchers and lets them claim
their research outputs in the ORCID Registry. I have been involved with
ORCID since early 2010 and I am happy to see that nine months after
launch 200,000 researchers have signed up for the service, and the
organisation has more than
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://orcid.org/about/community/members">70
member organizations</ext-link>.</p>
<boxed-text>
</boxed-text>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://orcid.org/register">Registering
for an ORCID identifier</ext-link> is easy, and can be done in a few
minutes. Claiming works in the profile is also straighforward, and works
by integration with CrossRef Search, Scopus, Web of Science, DataCite
Metadata Search, and other services. Even though about 1.5 million works
have been claimed by now, many users have still not claimed any works or
added profile information in other ways.</p>
<p>These numbers should go up as more academic institutions sign up for
ORCID and help their researchers create ORCIDs and claim works. In the
meantime we need more incentives for researchers to add publications to
their ORCID profile. Publication lists are a very good reason to add
your papers and other research outputs to your ORCID profile.</p>
<sec id="publication-lists">
  <title>Publication Lists</title>
  <p>Every researcher maintains a list of his publications in some form.
  These publication lists are used for grant and job applications, for
  academic websites to attract collaborators and students, and more.
  Publication lists can be generated in many different ways, but I have
  never heard that someone finds this process fun or easy. The challenge
  is multiplied when the publication list is not generated for an
  individual, but for a research group, department or institution (my
  university goes through this process every year uisng RefWorks and
  produces an
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.refworks.com/RefShare2?site=047931198213200000/RWWS6A619751/2013%20Hochschulbibliografie">annual
  institutional bibliography</ext-link>).</p>
  <p>Although the library usually takes care of the larger publication
  lists and can help researchers setting up their own lists, there still
  is much that needs to be done by individual researchers, and the
  process needs to be easier. Some recommendations are:</p>
  <list list-type="bullet">
    <list-item>
      <p>don’t reinvent the wheel</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>use persistent identifiers</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>use standards</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>don’t worry about citation styles</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>keep everything upstream, not locally</p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
  <p>Don’t try to invent a new way of managing publication lists. Other
  people have worked on this problem before, and there are many tools
  available. This doesn’t mean you shouldn’t try something new, but
  please build it on top of all the infrastructure and services we have
  already.</p>
  <p>Managing publication lists becomes much easier when you use
  persistent identifiers such as DOIs. They make it much easier to
  obtain metadata (e.g. authors, title, journal) and the fulltext
  version. Some disciplines use other identifiers, but a local
  identifier such as a URL is usually a bad idea.</p>
  <p>Use standard protocols, standard file formats and standard
  metadata. BibTex and RIS are file formats for references that almost
  every piece of software handling references understands.</p>
  <p>Citation styles come from a time when publications were printed on
  paper. They make no real sense anymore, and as a researcher you
  shouldn’t bother which one of 3000+ styles is the appropriate one.</p>
  <p>The last recommendation is the most important one. Don’t try to
  manage publication lists in your local system, or your department, but
  rather do this as much upstream as possible. ORCID is an ideal service
  for this. But don’t try to manually add or edit publications in the
  ORCID registry, but rather claim them from CrossRef, DataCite or
  similar services, because these are the places that have authoritative
  information about publication. If you try to “fix” information
  (because all metadata can contain mistakes), nobody will notice. If
  something is wrong with your works, notify the publisher so that the
  CrossRef metadata can be updated.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="orcid-profiles-as-rss-feeds">
  <title>ORCID Profiles as RSS Feeds</title>
  <p>ORCID is a good place to manage publication lists, but it is often
  not easy to get the information out of the system. The standard way is
  via a REST API (XML or JSON). This might work really well for a
  software developer who wants to connect his system to ORCID, but most
  researchers have other things to do.</p>
  <p>RSS was invented to publish information about frequently updated
  works, and a good example are Tables of Content (TOC) for journals.
  RSS is also a great tool to manage publication lists, as it can be
  easily integrated into content management systems such as Wordpress or
  Drupal. There is a
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://oxford.crossref.org/best_practice/rss/">Recommendation
  on RSS Feeds for Scholarly Publishers</ext-link>, and we can apply the
  same guidelines to <bold><bold>RSS Feeds for Scholarly
  Authors</bold></bold>. With
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/OPML">OPML</ext-link>
  we also have a standard format to aggregate multiple RSS feeds, and
  this is true not only for journal RSS feeds, but also author RSS
  feeds.</p>
  <p>Unfortunately there is one missing piece in this workflow: turning
  ORCID profiles into RSS feeds. At the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://occamstypewriter.org/trading-knowledge/2012/11/13/solo-hackday/">SpotOn
  London hackathon</ext-link> last November I worked with
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://twitter.com/easternblot">Eva
  Amsen</ext-link> and
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://twitter.com/graemedmoffat">Graeme
  Moffat</ext-link> to hack this workflow together using available
  tools. But we really need a more mature solution. Until RSS feeds are
  provided by the core ORCID service - and there is so much other stuff
  to do right now that this will take time - the best solution might be
  a web service that turns ORCID profiles into scholarly RSS as
  described above for journal articles.</p>
  <p>Today I finally came around implementing a first version of this -
  hacking together a Ruby Sinatra application hosted on Amazon Web
  Services
  (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hack4ac.com/">#hack4ac</ext-link>
  attendees know why). The application takes an ORCID ID (e.g. mine:
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://feed.labs.orcid-eu.org/0000-0003-1419-2405.rss">http://feed.labs.orcid-eu.org/0000-0003-1419-2405.rss</ext-link>)
  and returns an RSS feed. The first version just returns just the name
  and biography from the profile, but I only started working on this
  today. ORCID Feed can be found at
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://feed.labs.orcid-eu.org/">http://feed.labs.orcid-eu.org</ext-link>
  and the source code is available at
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/mfenner/orcid-feed">Github</ext-link>.
  Please add suggestions and comments to the Github issue tracker
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/mfenner/orcid-feed/issues">here</ext-link>.</p>
  <p><bold><bold>Update 7/28/13</bold></bold>: <italic>I’ve added
  publications to the output, and additional content types. Use them as
  extension (e.g. <monospace>.json</monospace>), as format parameter
  (e.g. <monospace>?format=rss</monospace>), or use an accept-header,
  e.g. <monospace>Accept: application/x-bibtex</monospace>. I’ve also
  added basic error checking with cleanup of names and removal of
  duplicates.</italic></p>
  <list list-type="bullet">
    <list-item>
      <p>html (the default): forward to profile on the ORCID website</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>rss - RSS feed</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>bib - bibtex file</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>json - Citeproc JSON</p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
