<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Scientific meetings need more bloggers</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2008-05-17">
<day>17</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2008</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>In one of my first blog posts (before I joined Nature Network) about
a year ago I wrote about the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611102648/http://blog.xartrials.com/2007/6/6/asco_2007_meeting">American
Society of Clinical Oncology (ASCO) 2007 Meeting</ext-link>. I was
surprised that only a handful of blogs reported about the event, one of
the largest and most important meetings for clinical cancer
research.</p>
<p>One would think that blogging and scientific meetings would be a
natural combination. Those that can't go to a meeting need a filtered
summary, and a blogging scientist would be a perfect person for the job.
The experience with blog posts about technology meetings also says that
this should work.
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611102648/http://blogs.nature.com/news/blog/">In
the Field</ext-link> is Nature's blog about conferences and events and
there is the occasional blog post about a meeting.</p>
<p>So why are there not more bloggers at science meetings? I think that
this is simply a problem of critical mass. 1) there are still not enough
science bloggers around and 2) most science blogs (including this one)
don't write about research results, but rather about other aspects of
science. This could well change in a few years and I expect to see an
increasing number of science blogs reporting from meetings. And I will
try to blog about the most interesting sessions in the fields of
leukemia and lymphoma when I go to ASCO 2008 in Chicago at the end of
the month.</p>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
