<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>ScienceOnline09: Providing public health and medical
information to all</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2009-01-16">
<day>16</day>
<month>1</month>
<year>2009</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>This Sunday I will moderate a session called
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003022812/http://www.scienceonline09.com/index.php/wiki/Public_health_and_medical_information/">Providing
public health and medical information to all</ext-link> at
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003022812/http://www.scienceonline09.com/index.php/wiki">ScienceOnline09</ext-link>.
I didn't pick the title, but it is a topic I care a lot about. Because
the session is intended as an open discussion, I thought that a blog
post would be good way to organize my thoughts and ideas that I have for
this
session<sup><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003022812/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2009/01/16/scienceonline09_providing_public_health_and_medical_information_to_all/#fn1">1</ext-link></sup>.
And even though there are only two days left, I might even get some
valuable feedback.</p>
<p>We science bloggers have many recurring themes, and this session is
again about access to information and filtering out the important
information.</p>
<sec id="access">
  <title>Access</title>
  <p>The traditional format to provide important medical information is
  the peer-reviewed journal article. Unless you work at a large research
  institution or university hospital, only part of these papers will be
  available as full-text articles. Notable examples of journals with
  immediate open access to peer reviewed research are the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003022812/http://www.bmj.com/channels/research.dtl">British
  Medical Journal</ext-link>,
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003022812/http://medicine.plosjournals.org/">PLoS
  Medicine</ext-link>,
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003022812/http://www.biomedcentral.com/bmcmed/">BMC
  Medicine</ext-link> and
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003022812/http://www.openmedicine.ca/">Open
  Medicine</ext-link>. Many other medical journals provide free fulltext
  access 6-12 months after publication, and this is now a requirement
  for research funded by many funding agencies, including the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003022812/http://publicaccess.nih.gov/policy.htm">NIH</ext-link>,
  the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003022812/http://www.wellcome.ac.uk/About-us/Policy/Spotlight-issues/Open-access/Policy/index.htm">Wellcome
  Trust</ext-link>,
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003022812/http://www.hhmi.org/about/research/journals/main?action=search">Howard
  Hughes Medical Institute</ext-link>.</p>
  <p>Clinical trials are essential to improve the prevention, diagnosis
  and treatment of many medical conditions. Since 2005 all clinical
  trials have to registered in one of several central databases (e.g.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003022812/http://www.clinicaltrials.gov/">clinicaltrials.gov</ext-link>)
  before the first patient is treated. The information in these publicly
  accessible databases includes the trial design and participating
  centers. Since September 2008, clinicaltrials.gov started to also
  report key results, as required by the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003022812/http://network.nature.com/people/mfenner/blog/2008/08/02/fdaaa-push-to-open-data-in-clinical-medicine">Federal
  Drug Administration Amendment Act</ext-link>. It is important to
  remember that
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003022812/http://network.nature.com/people/mfenner/blog/2009/01/10/what-science-is-worth-shouting-about">not
  all clinical trials eventually will be published</ext-link>, so that
  looking just at the published literature will not give a complete
  picture.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="filtering">
  <title>Filtering</title>
  <p>Access to important medical information is only the first step. The
  filtering of this information is at least as important. With filtering
  I mean both finding the important research papers and evaluating them
  in a larger context. A meta-analysis is a systematic review that
  follows a standard set of rules for finding and evaluating research
  papers, a format championed by the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003022812/http://www.cochrane.org/">Cochrane
  Collaboration</ext-link>. A meta-analysis can not only summarize
  published research papers, but sometimes also uses the raw data of the
  published research (the so-called individual patient data
  meta-analysis). I would wish that the meta-analysis receives the same
  kind of attention in the blogosphere as the open access to research
  papers.</p>
  <p>Whereas a positive outcome in a good meta-analysis is the best
  evidence for the usefulness of a healthcare intervention, most
  filtering of biomedical research papers comes to us in different
  ways:</p>
  <list list-type="bullet">
    <list-item>
      <p>Review articles</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Journal editorials</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Science blogging</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Articles by science journalists</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003022812/http://network.nature.com/people/mfenner/blog/2008/12/05/open-access-is-not-enough-the-source-is-also-important">Direct
      to consumer advertising</ext-link> (United States and New Zealand
      only)</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Social networking sites such as
      <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003022812/http://www.connotea.org/">Connotea</ext-link>,
      <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003022812/http://www.citeulike.org/">CiteULike</ext-link>
      or
      <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003022812/http://www.friendfeed.com/">FriendFeed</ext-link></p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
  <p>I would argue that science articles in traditional media (e.g.
  newspapers) and direct to consumer advertising may work in drawing
  your attention to a research paper, but they are usually useless in
  evaluating biomedical research. And obviously I believe that science
  blogging has great potential to help in both the finding and
  evaluation of important biomedical research. Meta-analyses take a very
  long time and review articles take a long time. A thoughtful blog post
  on a recently published paper can provide an important service.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003022812/http://researchblogging.org/">Research
  Blogging</ext-link> and
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003022812/http://blogs.nature.com/">Nature
  Blogs</ext-link> are two services to help find these blog posts.
  Social networking sites for scientists are a great tool to find
  interesting research papers, but I don't know how they can help
  evaluate a research paper.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003022812/http://www.f1000medicine.com/">Faculty
  of 1000 Medicine</ext-link> is a very interesting approach to the
  filtering problem, but I haven't used the service enough to comment on
  it here.</p>
  <p><italic><italic>Addendum (01/18/09)</italic></italic>
  It can be a good thing to have your presentation on the second day of
  a conference. You come up with new ideas. I changed the title to
  better convey what I would like to talk about in this session:
  <italic><italic>Reporting medical research:</italic></italic>
  <italic><italic>specific problems and specific
  solutions</italic></italic>. And I've added another topic besides
  access and filtering:</p>
</sec>
<sec id="motivation">
  <title>Motivation</title>
  <p>There are many reasons why people are interested in reporting or
  learning about medical research. But betroffenheit and financial
  interests are two very strong reasons that should always be kept in
  mind. Betroffenheit is a German word that means something that is
  directly affecting your life. If you are a patient with a serious
  medical condition, or have a sick friend or relative, you obviously
  have very different needs than someone who just wants to catch up on
  the latest research on the release of calcium from intracellular
  stores. Betroffenheit is not confined to medical research, climate
  change is another example.
  Obviously there are often important financial interests behind the
  outcome of medical research. And this not only means the interests of
  drug companies or device manufacturers. Most presentations of medical
  research in larger meetings now begin with a financial disclosure
  slide.</p>
  <p>I've updated the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003022812/http://www.slideshare.net/mfenner/providing-public-health-and-medical-information-to-all-presentation-924116">Slideshare
  Presentation</ext-link> that I want to give as an introduction to the
  session. And the conference Wiki page for the session is
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003022812/http://www.scienceonline09.com/index.php/wiki/Public_health_and_medical_information/">here</ext-link>.</p>
  <p>fn1. Yet another argument for the usefulness of science
  blogging.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
