<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Science blogging is the new email</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2008-08-31">
<day>31</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2008</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>The just finished conference
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150906080125/http://www.nature.com/natureconferences/sciblog2008/index.html">Science
Blogging 2008: London</ext-link> was a wonderful chance for real-life
socialising networking. I started to upload some fotos to Flickr (e.g.
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150906080125/http://www.flickr.com/photos/mfenner/2813527160/">Scott
Keir explaining sign language</ext-link>, see all fotos tagged
<italic><italic>sciblog</italic></italic>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150906080125/http://www.flickr.com/photos/tags/sciblog/">here</ext-link>),
some of them are too embarrassing and I will keep them for bribes
reference later on.</p>
<p>The meeting was also a great opportunity to think about where we are
today with scienceblogging. Having a conference is a good sign that the
field is
evolving<sup><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150906080125/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2008/08/31/science_blogging_is_the_new_email/#fn1">1</ext-link></sup>,
and you can see several subdisciplines evolving:</p>
<list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
    <p>conference blogging (also includes event blogging)</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>edublogging</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>metablogging (blogging about blogging, by far the largest
    discipline)</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>research blogging (blogging about scientific experiments, the
    smallest discipline)</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>investigational blogging (the keynote lecture by Ben Goldacre
    described this very well)</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>evolution blogging (a large subdiscipline)</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>news blogging (blogging about science news)</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>watercooler blogging (small pieces of interesting or funny
    thoughts/pictures)</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>summary blogging (summarizing other blog posts and linking to
    them)</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>diary blogging (blogging as a personal diary of
    self-expression)</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>hoax blogging (see
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150906080125/http://phylogenomics.blogspot.com/2008/04/confessions-of-april-fool-and-dope-on.html">this</ext-link>
    example by Jonathan Eisen)</p>
  </list-item>
</list>
<p>There is no particular order to this list and there are certainly
more disciplines and some of the names could be catchier. Most bloggers
will blog in more than one category. But these categories can help to
think about what you are doing in your own blogging. And it helps when
you think about blogrolls or blogging networks such as Nature Network or
scienceblogs.com. Could we for example see a conference blogging network
in the future?</p>
<p>We ended the conference with a challenge to recruit more senior
faculty for science blogging. Jonathan Eisen is a professor at U.C.
Davis and might try an April Fools joke again next year, but faculty new
to blogging will probably be more interested in conference blogging,
edublogging and research blogging (the boundaries between the three can
be blurry). I am all for this challenge, as it will move science
blogging forward. And next week I will meet a department head that wants
to start blogging. Maybe we can put up another challenge for the next
science blogging conference: have a
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150906080125/http://network.nature.com/blogs/user/mfenner/2008/07/12/nobel-blogging">blogging
Nobel Prize winner</ext-link> as keynote speaker.</p>
<p>I finally get to the title of this post. Henry Gee made some
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150906080125/http://network.nature.com/blogs/user/henrygee/2008/08/30/professor-steve-steve-to-claim-political-asylum-shock-horror-probe">very
thoughtful comments</ext-link> in the plenary session at the end.
Blogging is much closer to the informal discussions you have in the
hallway or via email than it is to peer-reviewed papers. We have to
convince faculty members (and other people involved in science) that
blogging is the new email. Just as email was either unknown or looked at
in a funny way 20 years ago, blogging will become a tool of daily life
for most scientists. We can wait until the current generation of
children and young students is old enough to become faculty members
themselves, or we can promote the use of science blogging to shorten
this time.</p>
<p>fn1. Will we soon have a discussion about starting a journal?</p>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
