<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>ScienceFeed: Interview with Ijad Madisch</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2010-02-15">
<day>15</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2010</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Microblogging is blogging of short text messages, photos or other
media and is best exemplified by
<italic><italic>Twitter</italic></italic>. Twitter use has grown
tremendously in 2009, and this also includes many
scientists.<sup><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611032951/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2010/02/15/sciencefeed_interview_with_ijad_madisch/#fn1">1</ext-link></sup>
<italic><italic>FriendFeed</italic></italic> is a another microblogging
tool that not only allows sending of short text messages, but connects
them together in groups and discussions threads similar to what you can
do in online forums. FriendFeed, especially
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611032951/http://friendfeed.com/the-life-scientists">The
Life Scientists</ext-link> group has been a popular place for many
scientists for the last 18 months or so.
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611032951/http://network.nature.com/people/U42E63119/profile">Cameron
Neylon</ext-link> wrote a good introduction to the service back in June
2008:
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611032951/http://blog.openwetware.org/scienceintheopen/2008/06/12/friendfeed-for-scientists-what-why-and-how/">FriendFeed
for scientists: what, why, and how?</ext-link>. FriendFeed is a great
tool for conference blogging, and the ISBM 2008 conference was probably
the first scientific conference where it was used extensively, resulting
in a <italic><italic>PLoS Computational Biology</italic></italic>
paper.<sup><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611032951/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2010/02/15/sciencefeed_interview_with_ijad_madisch/#fn2">2</ext-link></sup>
FriendFeed is also often used to comment on blog posts, and here it is
competing for attention with comments that are put directly on a blog.
FriendFeed is a good example for a generic Web 2.0 tool that is much
more useful to scientists than many Web 2.0 tools targeted specifically
at scientists (the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611032951/http://fcw.com/Articles/2009/10/26/NIH-grant-creates-Facebook-for-Scientists.aspx">Facebooks
for scientists</ext-link>).</p>
<p>FriendFeed
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611032951/http://www.facebook.com/press/releases.php?p=116581">was
acquired by Facebook</ext-link> in August 2009, and users started to
worry about the long-term future of FriendFeed. An Open Source version
of the FriendFeed web server was recently released as
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611032951/http://bret.appspot.com/entry/tornado-web-server">Tornado</ext-link>
(source code on
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611032951/http://github.com/facebook/tornado">GitHub</ext-link>).
Although other services (including
<italic><italic>Facebook</italic></italic>) offer similar functionality,
no service has (yet) emerged as an alternative popular with scientists.
FriendFeed use seemed to be declining at the two recent
<italic><italic>Science Online London 2009</italic></italic> and
<italic><italic>ScienceOnline2010</italic></italic> conferences, as more
and more people were using Twitter.</p>
<p>Last Tuesday
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611032951/http://www.google.com/buzz">Google
Buzz</ext-link> was released. <italic><italic>Buzz</italic></italic> is
also a microblogging service, tightly integrated with
<italic><italic>Google Mail</italic></italic> and <italic><italic>Google
Reader</italic></italic>. If offers many of the same features as
<italic><italic>FriendFeed</italic></italic>, and because it integrates
with Google Mail, it has a large number of potential users from the
start – including a large number of people involved in the Science
Bloggosphere. <italic><italic>Buzz</italic></italic> will certainly get
some of the features that are still missing, e.g. an easy way to import
content from other sources, including a bookmarklet. And
<italic><italic>Buzz</italic></italic> works very well on iPhone and
Android phones and there also uses location information – e.g. all the
<italic><italic>Buzz</italic></italic> discussions near you. But at the
moment many people wonder how best to integrate
<italic><italic>Buzz</italic></italic> with
<italic><italic>FriendFeed</italic></italic> and
<italic><italic>Twitter</italic></italic>, and all the other online
tools they use – it doesn't make sense to read the same content again
and again on all these services.</p>
<p>In this context it is very interesting to see
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611032951/http://www.sciencefeed.com/">ScienceFeed</ext-link>
launching as a new microblogging service this week.
<italic><italic>ScienceFeed</italic></italic> in many ways is similar to
<italic><italic>FriendFeed</italic></italic>, but tries to add features
of particular interest to scientists. I spoke with <italic><italic>Ijad
Madisch</italic></italic> about ScienceFeed.</p>
<fig>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611032951im_/http://gallery.me.com/mfenner/100079/ijad_madisch/web.jpg" xlink:title="" />
</fig>
<sec id="1-what-is-sciencefeed">
  <title>1. What is ScienceFeed?</title>
  <p>ScienceFeed is science as it happens, communicated through a
  microblogging platform. Conceptualized and designed by scientists, it
  is a bridge between online scientific networking platforms, scientific
  databases, and the wider online science community. The ScienceFeed
  platform allows users to post microblogs, sometimes just a few
  sentences, on scientific headlines, new findings, controversy,
  conferences and ideas related to science. Community members can follow
  the feeds of fellow members and comment on topics in which they are
  interested, allowing real-time communication and transfer of
  ideas.</p>
  <fig>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611032951im_/http://gallery.me.com/mfenner/100079/sciencefeed_screenshot/web.jpg" xlink:title="" />
  </fig>
  <p>ScienceFeed is an interactive and dynamic platform – like science
  itself. Here, scientists, journalists, librarians, students, and those
  with an interest in science, will be able to communicate in a way that
  has no borders. Individuals from all over the world are able to
  participate and observe, helping to make science accessible to all.
  Integral to the concept of Science 2.0 is having online resources that
  are archivable and searchable – ScienceFeed will do just this. Science
  is not limited to the laboratory: it happens through interactions of
  communities. ScienceFeed is excited to build such a community.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="2-how-is-sciencefeed-different-from-friendfeed">
  <title>2. How is ScienceFeed different from FriendFeed?</title>
  <p>In basic functionality, ScienceFeed isn't much different to
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611032951/http://friendfeed.com/the-life-scientists">FriendFeed</ext-link>.
  However, I think with the help of the community we will develop and
  add applications to the platform that could make it very efficient for
  scientific communication. There are two differences from FriendFeed
  which we have already implemented: 1) Specific scientific publications
  can easily be searched for and then entered as a linked-in reference
  within a feed, and, 2) Groups can be marked as an event (e.g. a
  conference). My vision is to have event streams in ScienceFeed, which
  then can be visualized and presented in a much better way. However,
  the most important part is that we listen to the feedback of the
  community and develop specific applications based on their ideas and
  feedback.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="3-what-special-features-does-sciencefeed-provide-for-conference-microblogging">
  <title>3. What special features does ScienceFeed provide for
  conference microblogging</title>
  <p>An important feature from ScienceFeed is that groups can be marked
  as a specific event, such as a conference. Administrators of these
  groups will be able to import hashtags from Twitter, so all tweets
  will be aggregated and displayed within this group. A possibility for
  future growth is the integration of an entire conference program
  (sessions, panels, etc.) into the group, which then can be commented
  on by group members. It is important to us that the scientific
  community has an input into the development of this feature so that we
  can build a stronger, more efficient platform based on the needs of
  our users.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="4-can-you-import-references-into-sciencefeed-only-via-your-reference-database-or-also-via-citeulike-or-other-bookmarking-service">
  <title>4. Can you import references into ScienceFeed only via your
  reference database, or also via CiteULike or other bookmarking
  service?</title>
  <p>Martin, thank you so much for this great idea. Based on your
  feedback we worked hard to make this happen before launch. Yes, now
  ScienceFeed can import from other bookmarking services such as
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611032951/http://www.citeulike.org/">CiteUlike</ext-link>
  or
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611032951/http://www.connotea.org/">Connotea</ext-link>.
  Furthermore ScienceFeed supports
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611032951/http://www.oclc.org/productworks/coins.htm">CoiNS</ext-link>,
  which identifies automatically based on a weblink whether or not
  bibliographic data is in the specified URL.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="5-how-is-sciencefeed-different-from-twitter">
  <title>5. How is ScienceFeed different from Twitter?</title>
  <p>There are several differences, but the largest are that in
  ScienceFeed there is no character limitation and groups can be tagged
  as a specific event – facilitating real-time, online communication
  about the event.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="6-what-is-the-advantage-of-having-a-social-networking-tool-specifically-for-scientists">
  <title>6. What is the advantage of having a social networking tool
  specifically for scientists?</title>
  <p>I think the most important part is the non-dilution of information
  in an environment where the platform and focus is specifically on
  science. Consider the following: You can find a biomedical scientific
  paper by searching in Google, but you could also use PubMed, which has
  a high probability of faster and better results. It is the same as
  within
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611032951/https://www.researchgate.net/">ResearchGATE</ext-link>:
  You have large groups (Methods, Immunology, Neuroscience, Philosophy,
  etc.) with a very focused population, which again makes your search
  more directed and efficient with better results.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="7-what-is-the-relationship-between-sciencefeed-and-researchgate">
  <title>7. What is the relationship between ScienceFeed and
  ResearchGATE?</title>
  <p>ScienceFeed will be a scientific microblogging platform completely
  autonomous from ResearchGATE, because I think they target the same
  group, but with various usage patterns.</p>
  <p>The publication reference tool used for inserting papers into
  ScienceFeed accesses the custom-built database of ResearchGATE. This
  database now has a public API which makes it possible for everyone to
  connect to the ResearchGATE literature database. I think that
  microarticles which are pretty successful in Researchgate (published
  in our ResearchBLOG) could be a part of ScienceFeed as well. I see
  ScienceFeed as a platform which will be useful to various scientific
  platforms as
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611032951/http://www.mendeley.com/">Mendeley</ext-link>,
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611032951/http://www.academia.edu/">Academia</ext-link>,
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611032951/https://www.researchgate.net/">ResearchGATE</ext-link>,
  etc. It could be a platform that helps connect all these different
  platforms.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="8-will-there-be-a-publicly-available-api-for-sciencefeed">
  <title>8. Will there be a publicly available API for
  ScienceFeed?</title>
  <p>Yes, there will be an API.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="9-what-are-your-responsibilities-in-sciencefeed">
  <title>9. What are your responsibilities in ScienceFeed?</title>
  <p>I am, as in ResearchGATE, one of the co-founders and a kind of CEO.
  I want to build a team of innovative and forward-thinking individuals
  to help develop ideas and work conceptually on the future directions
  of ScienceFeed.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="10-what-did-you-do-before-working-on-sciencefeed">
  <title>10. What did you do before working on ScienceFeed?</title>
  <p>I am a co-founder and CEO of ResearchGATE and I am also working at
  Massachusetts General Hospital, Harvard Medical School, in Boston as a
  researcher. Before ResearchGATE I studied Medicine and Computer
  Science and completed my doctoral thesis in Virology, while working
  for some time in Gastroenterology as a medical doctor.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="11-could-you-provide-contact-information-for-people-that-have-further-questions-about-sciencefeed">
  <title>11. Could you provide contact information for people that have
  further questions about ScienceFeed?</title>
  <p>I can be contacted anytime at:
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611032951/mailto:ijad.madisch@sciencefeed.com">ijad.madisch@sciencefeed.com</ext-link>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="references">
  <title>References</title>
  <p><italic><italic>Bonetta L.</italic></italic> Should You Be
  Tweeting? <italic><italic>Cell</italic></italic> 2009
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611032951/http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.cell.2009.10.017">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cell.2009.10.017</ext-link></p>
  <p><italic><italic>Saunders N et al.</italic></italic> Microblogging
  the ISMB: A New Approach to Conference Reporting. <italic><italic>PLoS
  Comput Biol</italic></italic> 2009
  https://doi.org/<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611032951/http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000263">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000263</ext-link></p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
