<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>ScienceCard named Finalist in Mendeley/PLoS API Binary
Battle</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2011-11-20">
<day>20</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2011</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>I’m very proud to report that
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525033358/http://sciencecard.org/">ScienceCard</ext-link>
last week has been
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525033358/http://dev.mendeley.com/api-binary-battle">named
finalist</ext-link> in the Mendeley/PLoS API Binary Battle. Not bad for
a project that started only two months ago in a hackathon following the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525033358/http://www.scienceonlinelondon.org/">Science
Online London</ext-link> conference and is done in my spare time. The
winners of the contest will be named on November 30, but I’m more than
happy that the project has even gotten this far.</p>
<fig>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525033358im_/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/files/2011/11/sciencecard.jpg" xlink:title="sciencecard" />
</fig>
<p>The idea of ScienceCard is threefold:</p>
<list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
    <p>make it as easy as possible to create a profile page with your
    publications</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>Automatically collect citations and other metrics for these
    publications</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>make it as easy as possible to reuse this information, e.g. in
    your personal blog or reference manager</p>
  </list-item>
</list>
<p>Registration with ScienceCard is easy. You create an account by
logging in via Twitter (using the OAuth 2 protocol for the technically
inclined), and then add your account name from one or more author
identifier services. I added Google Scholar today, the other options are
Microsoft Academic Search, AuthorClaim and Mendeley (I’m working on
Scopus Author ID). If you add an Microsoft Academic Search or
AuthorClaim identifier, ScienceCard will import all your publications
from these services. ScienceCard currently only understands publications
with a DOI, other scholarly items could be added in the future. With
Mendeley and Google Scholar you only link to these services, I’m still
having trouble with the Mendeley OAuth 1 authentication and Google
Scholar doesn’t have an API.</p>
<p>ScienceCard is importing all the relevant bibliographic information
using the CrossRef service. And ScienceCard is creating a
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525033358/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2011/10/17/serving-shortdois/">shortDOI</ext-link>
for all papers. But more interestingly, ScienceCard is calculating
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525033358/http://article-level-metrics.plos.org/">article-level
metrics</ext-link> for all publications, and composite numbers for
authors. For this ScienceCard is using the PLoS Article-Level Metrics
API code, but I have added more sources, including Mendeley, Microsoft
Academic Search and altmetric.com (but here only the number of blog
posts citing a paper). ScienceCard links to most sources so that you can
see the actual citations there, only CrossRef and altmetric.com don’t
offer that. A future update will show all citations directly in
ScienceCard.</p>
<p>ScienceCard tries to display a nice profile page for each researcher,
but also makes it easy to reuse the information somewhere else. Each
author page is available in six different formats, simply add the
extension after the (Twitter) username, e.g.
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525033358/http://sciencecard.org/mfenner.json">http://sciencecard.org/mfenner.json</ext-link></p>
<list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
    <p>HTML – for regular viewing</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>XML – for reuse by another computer</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>JSON – for reuse by another computer</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>CSV – comma-separated values for import into a spreadsheet</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>RIS – for reuse by a reference manager</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>BIB – BibTeX, for reuse by a reference manager</p>
  </list-item>
</list>
<p>JSON is the most interesting format, because it makes it very easy to
connect two different services. If you for example want to use
ScienceCard data on your personal WordPress blog you can simply download
my
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525033358/http://wordpress.org/extend/plugins/contact-info-options/">Contact
Info Options WordPress</ext-link> plugin, add your ScienceCard username
in your WordPress settings and do some hacking of the author template.
The process is unfortunately different for every WordPress theme, but
you can see an example WordPress profile that uses the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525033358/http://annotum.wordpress.com/">Annotum</ext-link>
theme (and publishing platform)
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525033358/http://blogs.scienceonlinelondon.org/annotum/author/mfenner/">here</ext-link>:</p>
<fig>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525033358im_/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/files/2011/11/annotum2.jpg" xlink:title="annotum2" />
</fig>
<p>This WordPress author profile is generated on the fly using
ScienceCard data, and will therefore automatically update.</p>
<p>The ScienceCard project is still at the beginning, and there are
enough ideas to move this project forward in interesting ways. I’m
particularly interested in improving the user interface and display of
information, in adding datasets and other scholarly content, and in
integrating with the ORCID unique author identifier service once the
service launches in spring 2012. If you are interested to learn more
about ScienceCard, please contact me via email or Twitter, or attend the
altmetrics session at
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525033358/http://scienceonline2012.com/">ScienceOnline2012</ext-link>,
which I will do together with Euan Adie from altmetric.com and
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525033358/http://altmetric.com/interface/plos.html">PLoS
Impact Explorer</ext-link>, and Jason Priem from
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120525033358/http://total-impact.org/">Total
Impact</ext-link> (two other Mendeley/PLoS API Binary Battle
finalists).</p>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
