<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Scientists and librarians: friend or foe?</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2010-01-24">
<day>24</day>
<month>1</month>
<year>2010</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Following the
<italic><italic>ScienceOnlin</italic>e<italic>2010</italic></italic>
conference, librarian Dorothea Salo
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611111844/http://scienceblogs.com/bookoftrogool/2010/01/science_online_2010_scientists.php">wrote
on her blog</ext-link>:</p>
<p specific-use="wrapper">
  <disp-quote>
    <p>This disconnect is the number one threat to science librarianship
    today – perhaps to all academic librarianship. How can science
    libraries persist when scientists haven't the least notion that
    libraries or librarians are relevant to their work?</p>
  </disp-quote>
</p>
<p>These are serious questions, and of course I don't have the answers.
But I would like to add my thoughts from a researcher perspective. The
role of libraries in providing teaching material for students
(textbooks, etc.) is another story that I will not touch today.</p>
<fig>
  <caption><p>Flickr image by Radioher</p></caption>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611111844im_/http://farm1.static.flickr.com/34/101350718_fa52fcef35_d.jpg" xlink:title="" />
</fig>
<p>I'm old enough to remember the time (maybe 15 years ago) before
literature searches were possible via the internet and scientific papers
were available in electronic form. I had to go to the library to use
Medline or Current Contents in printed form (and later on CD-ROM), or to
flip through the newest issues of the most interesting journals. I would
photocopy the papers I would then read at home, and then file away for
later use.</p>
<p><italic><italic>PubMed</italic></italic>,
<italic><italic>Scopus</italic></italic>, <italic><italic>Web of
Science</italic></italic>, and <italic><italic>Google
Scholar</italic></italic> now allow me to search the literature from my
desk at work (or from home). Most researchers (including myself)
probably don't have the skills for sophisticated searches, but these
tools
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611111844/http://network.nature.com/people/U2929A0EA/blog/2008/03/22/i-am-not-yelling-not-out-loud">more
or less</ext-link> get the job done. Electronic publishing means that I
can obtain a paper directly from the journal (as long as I access the
journal from a computer in the university network), and licensing is
handled (almost) transparently by the library.</p>
<p>These developments have dramatically reduced the time researchers
spend at a library. This is good, as this saves them a lot time. But
interactions between researchers and librarians have also been
dramatically reduced. Publishers and other companies (e.g.
<italic><italic>Thomson Reuters</italic></italic>,
<italic><italic>Mendeley</italic></italic>, <italic><italic>Faculty of
1000</italic></italic>, to name just a few) have used the opportunities
to adapt their offerings to the internet (e.g. electronic-only
journals), and to create new products that weren't possible (or even
thinkable) before. Although libraries have in many ways adapted to the
internet as well, they probably haven't seized the opportunity to the
same degree. The homepage of my university library is a place I visit
much less often than <italic><italic>PubMed</italic></italic> or the
pages of my favorite journals. Some ideas of how this could be changed
are listed below. Most of them are not new, but maybe at least some
libraries haven't gone all the way to make their pages an attractive
destination for the researchers of their
institution.<sup><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611111844/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2010/01/24/scientists_and_librarians_friend_or_foe/#fn1">1</ext-link></sup></p>
<sec id="provide-and-support-online-reference-manager">
  <title>Provide and support online reference manager</title>
  <p>Institutions should support at least one online reference manager,
  possible options include (in no particular order) Zotero, Mendeley,
  Endnote Web, Refworks and CiteULike. RefWorks and Endnote Web are
  commercial products and require a private (Endnote) and/or
  institutional license. The institution should either pick a free
  reference manager as their primary choice, or buy an institutional
  license in order to allow every researcher and student to use these
  tools without additional
  cost.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611111844/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2010/01/24/scientists_and_librarians_friend_or_foe/#fn2">2</ext-link></p>
  <p>As we can't expect everybody to use the same reference manager,
  libraries have to help with several products. The easiest way to do so
  is via an online forum (see next paragraph), as this is more efficient
  than one-to-one support and allows experienced users to help out.
  Online reference managers provide additional features (e.g. they can
  be used from different computers, allow shared folders for groups of
  users) and should therefore be preferred over standalone
  applications.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="online-user-training-and-support">
  <title>Online user training and support</title>
  <p>User support is obviously one of the central functions of science
  libraries. This has two aspects: helping with a specific problem (e.g.
  finding scientific literature), but also training users to do this on
  their own. The required skills include use of
  <italic><italic>PubMed</italic></italic> and other databases, and
  reference managers such as <italic><italic>Endnote</italic></italic>
  or <italic><italic>Zotero</italic></italic>. Skills in
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611111844/http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Evidence-based_medicine">evidence-based
  medicine</ext-link> are critical to find and appreciate the
  appropriate medical literature, but in my experience many physicians
  and medical students would benefit from additional training in this
  area.</p>
  <p>Introductory classes, help in person or a phone call are sometimes
  the best way to do this, but often users require quick help for a
  specific situation that can best done with online tools. Appropriate
  tools include email, online forum,
  <italic><italic>Twitter</italic></italic>,
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611111844/http://www.yammer.com/">Yammer</ext-link>
  (a microblogging tool similar to Twitter but for institutions),
  <italic><italic>SlideShare</italic></italic>,
  <italic><italic>FaceBook</italic></italic> (and
  <italic><italic>StudiVZ</italic></italic> in Germany),
  <italic><italic>FriendFeed</italic></italic>, and Wikis. Every
  institution should make a decision about the services they plan to
  support, with emphasis on tools that are easy to use.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="institutional-bibliographies">
  <title>Institutional bibliographies</title>
  <p>A regularly updated listing of all publications of an institution
  is not only a valuable PR service, but is often also required by
  administrations to evaluate research output. Librarians are often
  involved in this, but there is probably a lot of untapped potential.
  As
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611111844/http://network.nature.com/people/mfenner/blog/2010/01/03/orcid-or-how-to-build-a-unique-identifier-for-scientists-in-10-easy-steps">unique
  identifiers for researchers</ext-link> become more widespread, there
  really no longer is a need for researchers to compile publication
  lists
  themselves.<sup><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611111844/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2010/01/24/scientists_and_librarians_friend_or_foe/#fn3">3</ext-link></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="article-deposition-in-institutional-repositories">
  <title>Article deposition in institutional repositories</title>
  <p>Most journals allow researchers to post their accepted papers in
  institutional repositories of their institution. But because this
  requires technical skills and extra time, many researchers aren't
  particularly eager to make use of them. Institutional bibliographies
  can obviously be nicely integrated with institutional repositories,
  thus reducing redundant work.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="help-authors-with-article-submissions">
  <title>Help authors with article submissions</title>
  <p>Article processing charges for authors are often handled by their
  libraries, and sometimes libraries have
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611111844/http://www.biomedcentral.com/info/libraries/membership">membership
  deals</ext-link> with publishers that give authors a discount. But
  researchers often are left alone with the article submission process.
  Most authors submit at most a handful of papers each year, and they
  have to deal not only with different article formats between journals
  (most notably different reference styles), but also different article
  submission systems (e.g.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611111844/http://network.nature.com/people/mfenner/blog/2009/03/25/editorial-manager-interview-with-richard-wynne">Editorial
  Manager</ext-link>,
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611111844/http://www.ejpress.com/index.shtml">eJournal
  Press</ext-link>,
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611111844/http://scholarone.com/products/manuscript/">Manuscript
  Central</ext-link> or
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611111844/http://benchpress.highwire.org/">BenchPress</ext-link>).
  The total number of papers submitted by an institution is much larger,
  and thus at least some recurring problems could be avoided or at least
  the time required reduced with centralized support from the
  library.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="help-with-web-2-0-tools-for-scientists">
  <title>Help with Web 2.0 tools for scientists</title>
  <p>Libraries don't have to reinvent all the Web 2.0 tools for
  scientists that are already out there, but they are a good place to
  help interested researchers get started with some of them (e.g.
  <italic><italic>ResearchGate</italic></italic>, <italic><italic>Nature
  Network</italic></italic>, or
  <italic><italic>Academia.edu</italic></italic>). Ideally, these tools
  could be integrated into the library webpages via an API.</p>
  <p>fn1. I would like to be proven wrong by great examples of libraries
  gone Web 2.0.</p>
  <p>fn2. My university picked
  <italic><italic>RefWorks</italic></italic> as their primary reference
  manager.</p>
  <p>fn3. <italic><italic>Scopus</italic></italic> is already pretty
  good in this.</p>
  <p><italic>Three events from last week inspired me to write this: a
  blog post by (and short Twitter conversation with) Dorothea Salo
  (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611111844/http://scienceblogs.com/bookoftrogool/2010/01/science">Science
  Online 2010: Scientists and
  librarians</ext-link>online_2010_scientists.php), a meeting with the
  other organizers of
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611111844/http://bibcamp.wordpress.com/">BibCamp
  Hannover</ext-link> (“a BarCamp for librarians and other hackers” in
  May 2010), and a discussion via email with
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611111844/http://network.nature.com/people/obst/profile">Oliver
  Obst</ext-link> from the Medical Library, University of
  Münster.</italic></p>
  <fig>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611111844im_/http://www.linkwithin.com/pixel.png" xlink:title="" />
  </fig>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
