<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Some Thoughts on Beyond the Paper</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2013-03-20">
<day>20</day>
<month>3</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Today the journal <italic>Nature</italic> has released a special on
the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170731155331/http://www.nature.com/news/specials/scipublishing/index.html">Future
of Publishing</ext-link>. It includes a lot of interesting reading, but
I want to focus on the comment
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170731155331/http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/495437a">Beyond
the Paper</ext-link> by Jason Priem. In the comment Jason describes his
vision of the future of scholarly communication, a future where many of
today’s roles for articles and journals will be replaced by the
<italic>decoupled journal</italic> and online tools taking the lead in
dissemination and filtering of scholarly content.</p>
<p>Jason makes a strong case for this vision, and takes his time to also
discuss the concerns and challenges. He doesn’t have the space to
discuss in more detail how we get to that future, and in particular what
the role of researchers, publishers, libraries and funders be in that
transition.</p>
<p>Jason’s vision will probably be overwhelming for many researchers,
and might not directly address what is probably the biggest issue for
most researchers: funding for grants and jobs is limited, and the
processes we use to select for good science and good scientists are
inefficient and often arbitrary. Most students entering graduate school
will not be able to have a career in academia, and most academics will
say that they spend far too much time with evaluations – of their own
work and the work of others. It is unclear to me how we can get from the
current system – where one misstep such as denied grant or submission to
the wrong journal can mean the end of a career – to the system that
Jason envisions. The current climate doesn’t really foster
experimentation by researchers and I am interested to understand how
researchers can take part in this process of change.</p>
<p>The vision of the decoupled journal is very threatening for some of
the stakeholders of the current scholarly communication ecosystem, in
particular publishers and libraries. Every journal publisher and library
knows that it has to reinvent itself to survive the digital
transformation, but a vision that is build around a new ecosystem of
service providers needs to be clear how publishers and libraries can be
part of the transformation process.</p>
<p>Lastly, I disagree with the notion that <italic>today’s publication
silos will be replaced by a set of decentralized, interoperable services
that are built on a core infrastructure of open data and evolving
standards — like the Web itself.</italic> I would argue that both
scholarly communication and the web in general have a tendency for
centralization, and that scientific infrastructure needs to be
interoperable first and decentralized second. Without a focus on
interoperability the future of scholarly communication will not be open
and in the hands of many, but will be a race to become one of the
dominant players in this new ecosystem, and we might end up with not
1000s of libraries and publishers but just a handful of technology
companies holding the keys to our scientific infrastructure.</p>
<sec id="references">
  <title>References</title>
  <p>Priem, J. (2013). Scholarship: Beyond the paper <italic>Nature,
  495</italic> (7442), 437-440 DOI:
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170731155331/http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/495437a">10.1038/495437a</ext-link></p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
