<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Streamosphere: Interview with Euan Adie</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2009-08-20">
<day>20</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2009</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003123050/http://network.nature.com/people/euan/profile">Euan
Adie</ext-link> in June announced the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003123050/http://streamosphere.nature.com/">Streamosphere</ext-link>
service on the Nascent blog:
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003123050/http://blogs.nature.com/wp/nascent/2009/06/welcome_to_the_streamosphere.html">Welcome
to the Streamosphere</ext-link>. His simple explanation of what
Streamosphere does:</p>
<p specific-use="wrapper">
  <disp-quote>
    <p><italic><italic>Streamosphere lets you track scientific
    discussion on the web, in real time.</italic></italic></p>
  </disp-quote>
</p>
<p>The Nascent blog post explains Streamosphere in more detail,
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003123050/http://blogs.nature.com/wp/nascent/2009/07/streamosphere_update.html">in
another post from July</ext-link> Euan talks about some updates to the
service. I've asked Euan a few questions to learn more about
Streamosphere.</p>
<sec id="1-can-you-explain-what-streamosphere-is-and-does">
  <title>1. Can you explain what Streamosphere is and does?</title>
  <p>Streamosphere is an aggregator of scientific activity on the web.
  It tracks what scientists are talking about on Twitter, wikis, blogs,
  social bookmarking services, forums and other web 2.0 services.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="2-why-do-we-need-such-a-tool">
  <title>2. Why do we need such a tool?</title>
  <p>I think scientific attention (any time you read an abstract, cite a
  paper or search for a particular gene in a database you're giving it
  attention) is valuable to aggregate. Traditionally scientists and
  publishers have measured attention with citation counts and to a
  lesser extent downloads but there's lots of other online activity –
  like blogging, commenting and bookmarking – that could be used in new
  metrics.</p>
  <p>At the moment the relevant activity is</p>
  <list list-type="bullet">
    <list-item>
      <p><italic><italic>distributed</italic></italic> people could be
      talking about a paper I'm interested in on Friendfeed, blogs,
      forums…</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p><italic><italic>noisy</italic></italic> there are tens of
      thousands of research scientists on Twitter but most of the time
      they're posting pictures of lolcats</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p><italic><italic>lacking provenance</italic></italic> it's not
      easy to know whose opinions to trust</p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
  <p>Streamosphere attempts to tackle these issues by aggregating
  activity from lots of different sites, removing spam, providing
  filters and disambiguating users on different services. If I'm
  interested in what other scientists think about a particular paper
  then I can search for it on Streamosphere. If I want to keep track of
  everything related to a particular field then I can do that too.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="3-what-is-the-difference-between-streamosphere-postgenomic-and-nature-com-blogs">
  <title>3. What is the difference between Streamosphere, Postgenomic
  and Nature.com Blogs?</title>
  <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003123050/http://www.postgenomic.com/">Postgenomic</ext-link>
  and
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003123050/http://blogs.nature.com/">Nature.com
  Blogs</ext-link> only aggregate and analyze blog posts. Streamosphere
  gets a feed from Nature.com Blogs but covers other services too.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="4-what-is-the-difference-to-other-aggregators-such-as-friendfeed">
  <title>4. What is the difference to other aggregators such as
  FriendFeed?</title>
  <p>The main difference is that you can't interact with content on
  Streamosphere – if you want to comment on a blog post or paper you
  have to visit it and leave your comment there.</p>
  <p>Another would be that you don't follow people on Streamosphere,
  you'd follow topics.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="5-how-do-you-decide-whether-something-or-someone-is-related-to-science">
  <title>5. How do you decide whether something or someone is related to
  science?</title>
  <p>If you bookmark or discuss things with
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003123050/http://www.doi.org/">DOIs</ext-link>,
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003123050/http://arxiv.org/help/faq/whynostamp">arxiv
  IDs</ext-link> or
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003123050/http://blogs.library.ucla.edu/biomedical/2008/09/02/convert-a-pubmed-id-to-a-pubmedcentral-id/">PubMed
  IDs</ext-link> then you're added to the database. At this point any of
  your activity that doesn't look scholarly doesn't get aggregated.</p>
  <p>After that it's down to manual checks and whether or not you're
  following / being followed by other people in Streamosphere.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="6-can-we-follow-streamosphere-via-rss-or-twitter">
  <title>6. Can we follow Streamosphere via RSS or Twitter?</title>
  <p>Not yet! I'm hoping to open up the data in Streamosphere via a
  public API that can output RSS and other formats but don't want to do
  it before the system is stable. There are also questions surrounding
  how some messages can be republished. I'm not sure if Streamosphere's
  API output can include the contents of any tweets, for example, as to
  receive streaming updates from Twitter you need to sign an agreement
  saying that you won't distribute them outside of your application
  (can't remember the exact wording).</p>
  <p>The best way to track updates about Streamosphere is to watch
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003123050/http://blogs.nature.com/wp/nascent/">Nascent</ext-link>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="7-what-are-your-responsibilities-at-nature-com">
  <title>7. What are your responsibilities at Nature.com?</title>
  <p>I'm a product manager in the web publishing group. Generally
  speaking the areas I'm responsible for are aggregation, the Nature.com
  Blogs homepage and mobile platforms.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="8-what-did-you-do-before-working-for-nature-com">
  <title>8. What did you do before working for Nature.com?</title>
  <p>I was a bioinformatician at the University of Edinburgh in the
  medical genetics unit, working on candidate disease gene
  prioritization.</p>
  <p>Before that I'd co-founded and worked on a start-up that tried to
  extract entities and sentiment from forum posts. We brought in very
  little revenue for eighteen months, ran out of funding and went bust
  in 2001. It was an education…. 😉</p>
</sec>
<sec id="9-do-you-want-to-talk-about-future-plans-for-streamosphere">
  <title>9. Do you want to talk about future plans for
  Streamosphere?</title>
  <p>Sure – the main thing I'm looking forward to is personalization –
  being able to log in and tell the system what you're interested in.
  From then on whenever you visit the site particularly relevant items
  will be highlighted.</p>
  <p>The API is another key development… I'm really interested in seeing
  what other people can do with the data.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
