<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>The trouble with keynotes</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2013-07-23">
<day>23</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>A keynote is a presentation typically given at a start of a
conference that sets the central theme for the event. A keynote speaker
usually has more time (45-60 min) than other presenters, and has the
full attention of everyone attending the conference. The keynotes at the
conferences I attended the last several years (mostly scholarly
communication conferences) seem to work like this:</p>
<list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
    <p>find a prominent speaker, ideally not a core member of the
    community attending the conference</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>tell him to talk about something he knows a lot about, not
    necessarily a central theme of the conference</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>the keynote should be inspiring and eye-opening, instead of
    focussing on the conference</p>
  </list-item>
</list>
<p>The problem with this approach is that it focusses too much on the
<italic>prominent speaker</italic> and it runs the risk of the keynote
speaker talking about what he always talks about. Meaning that we don’t
learn much if we have heard the keynote speaker before. Which is too
bad, because keynotes should contain things that are unexpected and
exciting.</p>
<p>One of the best keynotes I had the pleasure of listening to in the
last several years was the one given by
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://michaelnielsen.org/blog/michael-a-nielsen/">Michael
Nielsen</ext-link> at
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://martinfenner.ghost.io/2013/07/23/the-trouble-with-keynotes/(http://www.nature.com/spoton/)">Science
Online London 2011</ext-link> (disclaimer: I was one of the conference
organizers). Not only is Michael a very good speaker, but his
presentation about <bold><bold>Open Science</bold></bold> fit perfectly
into the conference, and it was clear that he had made the presentation
specifically for this conference (with an audience that knows a lot
about Open Science). One of the main themes of his presentation - the
<italic>collective action problem</italic>, or to get started with
something that benefits everyone, but where there is a cost doing the
first step - is something I later picked up in a publication about the
Open Researcher &amp; Contributor ID (Fenner, Gomez, &amp; Thorisson,
2011).</p>
<boxed-text>
  <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://vimeo.com/29784152"></ext-link></p>
  <boxed-text id="crawler_player">
    <p>Play</p>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://f.vimeocdn.com/p/images/crawler_logo.png" />
  </boxed-text>
</boxed-text>
<p><italic>Keynote by Michael Nielsen at the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nature.com/spoton/">Science
Online London 2011 Conference</ext-link>, video recording and editing by
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://river-valley.tv/keynote-solo2011/">River
Valley TV</ext-link>.</italic></p>
<p>Luckily we increasingly have video recordings of keynote
presentations available online, making it easier to listen to the good
presentations.
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ted.com/tedx">TED
and TEDx</ext-link> have of course made the format of recordings of
carefully prepared talks popular. For large scholarly and academic
conferences the best starting point is
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://river-valley.tv/">River
Valley TV</ext-link>. The
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mediatheque.lindau-nobel.org/">Lindau
Nobel Laureate Meeting</ext-link> has hundreds of presentations by Nobel
laureates. And as video recording and streaming has become easier
technically (e.g. with
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://googleblog.blogspot.de/2011/09/google-92-93-94-95-96-97-98-99-100.html">Google
Hangouts on Air</ext-link>), recording good keynotes should become the
norm and not the exception.</p>
<p><italic>After several hundred blog posts here and elsewhere, this may
well be my first blog post with embedded video.</italic></p>
<sec id="references">
  <title>References</title>
  <p>Fenner, M., Gomez, C. G., &amp; Thorisson, G. A. (2011). Key issue:
  Collective action for the open researcher &amp; contributor iD
  (oRCID). <italic>Serials: The Journal for the Serials
  Community</italic>, <italic>24</italic>(3), 277–279. Retrieved from
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1629/24277">http://doi.org/10.1629/24277</ext-link></p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
