<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>The Price of Innovation – my Thoughts for Beyond the
PDF</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2013-03-20">
<day>20</day>
<month>3</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>The
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170731155123/http://www.force11.org/taxonomy/term/27">Beyond
the PDF Conference</ext-link> is currently taking place in Amsterdam.
Unfortunately I am unable to attend in person this time (I took part in
the first Beyond the PDF in January 2011), but I was watching the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170731155123/http://www.force11.org/beyondthepdf2/live">livestream</ext-link>
of the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170731155123/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2013/03/20/the-price-of-innovation-my-thoughts-for-beyond-the-pdf/ww.force11.org/Business_Case">Business
Case</ext-link> panel disucssion yesterday afternoon.</p>
<fig>
  <caption><p>Globe of Science and Innovation at CERN,
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170731155123/http://www.flickr.com/photos/nico_h/291798596/">Flickr
  photo</ext-link> by <bold>nico h</bold>.</p></caption>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170731155123im_/http://farm1.staticflickr.com/120/291798596_dbfcfc26d7_m.jpg" xlink:title="" />
</fig>
<p>How to pay for the development of new scientific infrastructure and
tools is something that I think a lot about science moving away from
academia to become a developer of scientific software last year. I would
assume three things:</p>
<list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
    <p>there are a lot of great ideas out there to improve scholarly
    communication</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>there is enough money out there to pay for improvements in
    scholarly communication</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>we are frustrated because progress is much slower than we
    anticipate</p>
  </list-item>
</list>
<p>If we have enough great ideas and enough money, but don’t see the
results we expect, something must be going wrong. A simple answer would
be that it is different people and organizations that have the ideas
from those that have the money, but I don’t think that this is the
reason. My suspicion is that there is a deeper problem, and that the
approach we take to scholarly innovation is broken. Below is how
innovation is approached by the major players:</p>
<list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
    <p>individual scientists and/or software developers come up with
    great ideas, but don’t get past the prototype stage because of
    limited resources</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>academic tools and infrastructure are built as part of a funded
    project (anywhere from 6 months to a few years), but there are no
    resources to turn this into a service that is persistent beyond the
    project</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>publishers and large academic institutions have the resources to
    build these tools. They are often less innovative because of their
    size</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>funders pay for projects (see above), but rarely for
    infrastructure, and they rarely get involved in innovative projects
    themselves</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>commercial organizations can quickly bring great ideas to market
    (in particular small startups), but it is often unclear how their
    services are paid for in the long run</p>
  </list-item>
</list>
<p>At the end of the day it seems that we have a lot of great ideas, but
many of them never reach critical mass, and an even smaller number has
long-term sustainability. I can think of a number of great projects that
have never gained traction, and of a number of great tools and services
where I have no idea how their development and service is paid for. The
idea to get to a large number of users no matter what it costs, and
figure out the business plan later is popular with internet startups,
but dangerous when we care about tools we want to still use two years
from now. Two projects that are not specific to science, but are
important for science and have made this work are <bold>Wikipedia</bold>
and <bold>Github</bold>. From the long list of tools for scientists I
would not pick <bold>Mendeley</bold> or <bold>figshare</bold> (both
great services, but still in search of sustainability), but
<bold>ArXiV</bold> and <bold>Papers</bold>.It also doesn’t help that
most scientists are a conservative bunch when it comes to technology,
and that the scientific market is fairly small compared to the overall
number of users. Another big challenge is to innovate in an open
environment, i.e. to make the innovation available to as many people as
possible without barriers of access. Some of my personal conclusions
from all this are the following:</p>
<list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
    <p>we should acknowledge that we have an innovation problem, and it
    is not simply solved by getting more money</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>we have a collaboration problem, too many people are doing
    similar things without talking to each other and working
    together</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>scientific infrastructure and tools cost money. We need the right
    people to pay (ideally not the individual researcher), fair prices
    and intelligent business models</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>funders should reconsider how they pay for scientific
    infrastructure, as the project-based approach is broken</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>large organizations (commercial, non-commercial and academic)
    should think about their approach to innovation, in particular how
    they support innovation outside of their organization</p>
  </list-item>
</list>
<p>You can follow the Beyond the PDF
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170731155123/http://www.force11.org/beyondthepdf2/live">livestream</ext-link>
today or follow the Twitter hashtag
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170731155123/https://twitter.com/search?q=%23btpdf2&amp;src=hash">#btpdf2</ext-link>.</p>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
