<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>The Complete Article</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2013-10-20">
<day>20</day>
<month>10</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Open access to research data is becoming increasingly important, as
manifested by memos or press releases from the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wellcome.ac.uk/About-us/Policy/Policy-and-position-statements/WTX035043.htm">Wellcome
Trust</ext-link>, the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://europa.eu/rapid/press-release_IP-12-790_en.htm">European
Commission</ext-link>, and the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.whitehouse.gov/blog/2013/02/22/expanding-public-access-results-federally-funded-research">the
Office of Science and Technology Policy</ext-link> (OSTP) from the White
House.</p>
<p>Open access to research data is important as this makes it easier for
other researchers to reproduce the research, and to build upon the
research by others by re-analysis of data or combination with other
research data. In other words,
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://royalsociety.org/policy/projects/science-public-enterprise/report/">Science
as an open enterprise</ext-link>.</p>
<p>The major challenge to open access to research data is that data
sharing is not a widespread practice. Several strategies have been
developed to create incentives for researchers to share research data,
including services that make it easier to share research data (e.g.
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://figshare.com/">figshare</ext-link>,
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dataup.cdlib.org/">DataUp</ext-link>
and
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.zenodo.org/">Zenodo</ext-link>),
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.knowledge-exchange.info/Default.aspx?ID=586">metrics
for research data</ext-link>, and data journals such as
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.earth-system-science-data.net/">Earth
System Science Data</ext-link>,
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.gigasciencejournal.com/">GigaScience</ext-link>
or the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://openarchaeologydata.metajnl.com/">Journal
of open archaeology data</ext-link>. Some of the sticks that have been
tried in addition to the carrots above include data management plan
requirements such as those
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nsf.gov/bfa/dias/policy/dmp.jsp">set
forth by the National Science Foundation (NSF)</ext-link> in 2011.</p>
<p>I would argue that all these carrots and sticks will eventually fall
short, unless we redefine what the journal article (and similarly
monograph) in the digital age should be about. Research data should
become a required part of any research article, rather than an optional
afterthought, or taking on a life on their own in a separate data
journal.</p>
<p>The <italic>complete article</italic> - as I would like to call this
journal article made fit for the digital age - should not only include
the research data used to create figures and tables and reportes as
results. Equally important are descriptions of reagents, workflows and
software tools that go into much more detail compared to what is common
practice today.</p>
<fig>
  <caption><p><bold>Ingredients of the complete
  article</bold></p></caption>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="http://blog.martinfenner.org/images/complete_paper.png" xlink:title="" />
</fig>
<p>The <italic>complete article</italic> does not have to come as one
big file. More likely the research data will be hosted at one or more
data centers elsewhere. Authorship will turn into contributorship and
will include all roles required to put the <italic>complete
article</italic> together, including for example data collection and
-analysis, and writing software needed to analyze the data. The
<italic>complete article</italic> can be shorter or longer than the
typical article today, important is not article length, but the
combination of text, data, and description of reagents and analysis
tools.</p>
<p>The <italic>complete article</italic> should also include (or link
to) the text of the peer reviews and previous article versions,
including preprints. This makes it much easier to understand the article
(and the data) in context. The <italic>complete article</italic> should
also link to article-level metrics post-publication for similar
reasons.</p>
<p>This idea of a <italic>complete article</italic> is not too far away
from the best practices used today, but it is important to make it the
default for scientific publication. Too much of what we publish today is
still centered around the concept of what can be printed on paper, and
telling exciting stories that have impact counts more than telling
complete stories that can be reproduced.</p>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
