<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>The Value of Peer Review</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2009-07-13">
<day>13</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2009</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>This weekend I was at
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20161107033419/http://www.nature.com/scifoo/everything.html">SciFoo</ext-link>,
an invitation-only unconference by <italic>O'Reilly Media</italic>,
<italic>Nature</italic> and <italic>Google</italic> that took place at
Google. I was fortunate to be invited, and I'm still digesting all the
impressions and discussions that I had (there were
<italic>many</italic>). This post is the indirect result of two sessions
and several related discussions on one particular topic that I'm most
interested in – the process of scientific publication.</p>
<p>Peer review
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20161107033419/http://www.nature.com/nature/peerreview/debate/index.html">is
usually seen as essential</ext-link> for the quality of a published
paper. At the same time peer review puts a large burden of work on the
research community, and in general is unpaid work. But peer review is
not living up to its full potential. We should start to see it not as a
necessary, costly and time-consuming burden, but rather as a business
opportunity. But for this the information communicated in the peer
review process needs to leave the (digital) drawers of the journal
editorial offices.</p>
<p>The published research paper is the most important piece of
information used to evaluate the reputation of a scientist (the
published book takes that role in many social sciences). This evaluation
is most important when large sums of money and the personal careers of
the involved scientists (in the form of research grants and jobs) depend
on it. We usually begin with applying some sort of metrics to the
publications of the scientist(s) under evaluation, most often the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20161107033419/http://thomsonreuters.com/products_services/science/free/essays/">Journal
Impact Factor</ext-link>. Once we have reduced the number of scientists
and papers to a small enough number, we can start reading the full-text
papers in order to evaluate the quality of the science. Both approaches
have shortcomings that I don't want to go into detail here (citation
metric: artificial number, delay of several years if relying on citation
counts; reading full-text paper: time constraints, often needs outside
experts as science has become so specialized). The information contained
in the peer review process is a large untapped resource that could
potentially overcome many of these shortcomings.</p>
<p>The typical revenue streams of a scientific journal are currently
subscriptions and author submission fees, and to a lesser extend
advertising and subscription-based added value in the form of news items
and editorials. The information contained in the peer review process is
extremely valuable to granting agencies and job search committees and
has the potential to become an additional major revenue source for
scientific journals, thus allowing a reduction in author submission fees
and/or free full-text access without a subscription. Many research
organizations and funding agencies currently pay for journal
subscriptions and author submission fees. If they would pay the journal
publishers similar amounts of money for peer review information, they
would obviously get much more value out of their money. Whereas this
revenue would probably come mainly from granting agencies, large
research organizations or companies would also pay for this information,
as would the typical academic journal reader (obviously a much smaller
sum) if it helps in filtering out the most relevant scientific
papers.</p>
<p>The peer review process obviously would have to change in this model.
If peer review becomes a major source of revenue for the journals,
reviewers need to get paid for their efforts. And it will affect of what
reviewers and editors write in their assessment if that information
might later be seen by third parties – even if they remain anonymous. It
is also not clear if the peer review information of rejected papers
should be used (a large body of information at journals with high
rejection rates). And if journal publishers don't buy in that model of
selling peer review information, nobody stops other parties from doing
additional peer review of papers already published and selling that
information. Which sounds pretty much like what
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20161107033419/http://www.f1000biology.com/">Faculty
of 1000</ext-link> is doing, although they seem to be targeting the
academic journal reader rather than the much more important funding
agencies.</p>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
