<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Thomson Scientific launches ResearcherID to uniquely
identify authors</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2008-01-21">
<day>21</day>
<month>1</month>
<year>2008</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Thomson Scientific last week
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611092246/http://scientific.thomson.com/press/2008/8429910/">announced</ext-link>
<italic><italic>ResearcherID</italic></italic>. ResearcherID tries to
solve a problem that has annoyed me for many years. In contrast to
papers and journals, authors are not associated with a unique ID in
databases such as PubMed. You are lucky if you have an uncommon last
name that contains only letters from the English alphabet. For the rest
of us, a typical PubMed search for your name will also pick up papers by
other authors. In my case for example papers by my cousin Mathias
Fenner.</p>
<p>The missing unique ID for authors makes it impossible to automate the
creation of publication lists for authors or insitutions. You already
can get email alerts or RSS feeds of papers published by a specific
person (colleague or competitor), but without unique ID, this is tricky.
ResearcherID will also automate the maintenance of your
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611092246/http://network.nature.com/blogs/user/mfenner/2007/08/17/do-you-know-your-hirsch-number">Hirsch
number</ext-link> (for those interested in this kind of metric).</p>
<p>Scientists interested in ResearcherID should register at the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611092246/http://www.researcherid.com/">reseacherID.com</ext-link>
website. Registration is currently by invitation only.</p>
<p>There is one major problem with ResearcherID. It is not clear from
the press release of who owns and controls this information. This is a
very sensitive issue and Thomson Scientific a major player in this
field. Remember
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611092246/http://www.passport.net/">Microsoft
Passport</ext-link>? The majority of web users was uncomfortable having
a central user ID and password managed by Microsoft. The service
eventually failed, and we now have the open standard
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611092246/http://openid.net/">Open
ID</ext-link>. Similarly, ResearcherID can only work if the user
database is either shared openly or hosted by someone like the NIH.</p>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
