<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Thoughts on the PubMed Redesign</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2009-10-11">
<day>11</day>
<month>10</month>
<year>2009</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>It was
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611025631/http://network.nature.com/people/U2929A0EA/profile">Anna
Kushnir</ext-link> who started it all. Frustrated with the limitations
of PubMed when finishing her PhD thesis, she wrote a blog post in March
2008
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611025631/http://network.nature.com/people/U2929A0EA/blog/2008/03/22/i-am-not-yelling-not-out-loud">I
Am Not Yelling. Not Out Loud.</ext-link>) about her experience. The blog
post created quite a stir in the blogosphere, especially among
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611025631/http://mbanks.typepad.com/my_weblog/2008/04/the-anna-kushni.html">science
librarians</ext-link>. At the heart of the controversy was Anna's
complaint that PubMed is too complicated to use, and that some science
librarians felt PubMed simply is complicated and that users such as Anna
should take better advantage of the resources available to better use
PubMed. David Lipman, director of the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611025631/http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/">NCBI</ext-link>
and responsible for PubMed, said:</p>
<p specific-use="wrapper">
  <disp-quote>
    <p>Although the current engine works well for some users and some
    queries, I understand Anna's frustration and we are in the midst of
    a number of changes that will make PubMed work better for her and
    many other users.</p>
  </disp-quote>
</p>
<p>In May 2009 a PubMed redesign
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611025631/http://www.nlm.nih.gov/pubs/techbull/mj09/ppt/sunrise_gillikin/sunrise_2009_gillikin.html">was
shown</ext-link> at the 2009 Annual Meeting of the Medical Library
Association (MLA) in Honolulu, and the presentation explains a lot of
the ideas behind the redesign. On September 30 the redesigned PubMed
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611025631/http://www.nlm.nih.gov/pubs/techbull/so09/so09_pm_redesign.html">was
unveiled to the public</ext-link>, and as early as next week it will
become the default PubMed web interface.</p>
<fig>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611025631im_/http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/portal/portalrc.fcgi/35308/img/35053" xlink:title="" />
</fig>
<p>Several science bloggers have already written about the PubMed
redesign, including a
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611025631/http://laikaspoetnik.wordpress.com/2009/10/01/pubmed&amp;Acirc;&amp;reg;-redesign-is-here-to-try/">very
detailed blog post</ext-link> by Jacqueline Limpens.</p>
<sec id="what-is-pubmed">
  <title>What is PubMed?</title>
  <p>MEDLINE is a database of more than 19 million citations for
  biomedical articles, hosted by the U.S. National Library of Medicine.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611025631/http://www.pubmed.gov/">PubMed</ext-link>
  is the freely available Web interface to that database. Not only is
  the content of PubMed available from other databases (e.g.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611025631/http://www.scopus.com/">Scopus</ext-link>
  or
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611025631/http://thomsonreuters.com/products_services/science/science_products/scholarly_research_analysis/research_discovery/web_of_science">Web
  of Science</ext-link>), but PubMed can be searched not only via the
  Web interface, but also from within other applications, e.g. a
  reference manager such as
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611025631/http://www.endnote.com/">Endnote</ext-link>
  or
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611025631/http://mekentosj.com/papers">Papers</ext-link>.
  And PubMed doesn't cover all scientific journals, many disciplines
  (e.g. physics, social sciences) aren't included at all. In other
  words, the Pubmed web interface is not the only way to find biomedical
  articles, and in fact will not find literature not related to the life
  sciences. But the PubMed web interface is probably by far the most
  popular way to search for biomedical literature.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="what-is-the-target-audience">
  <title>What is the target audience?</title>
  <p>The PubMed website is intended for at least 5 different
  audiences:</p>
  <list list-type="bullet">
    <list-item>
      <p>science librarian</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>researcher in the life sciences</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>clinician</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>patient or patient relative</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>teacher, high school student, journalist and anybody else
      interested in life sciences research</p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
  <p>Before PubMed
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611025631/http://www.nlm.nih.gov/archive//20050113/news/press_releases/free_medline.html">was
  announced in June 1997 by the U.S. vice president Al Gore</ext-link>
  as free web-based access to the MEDLINE database, most users were
  librarians, plus of a small group of academics with paid access
  (remember
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611025631/http://www.annals.org/cgi/content/abstract/105/2/321">Grateful
  Med</ext-link> ?). Now we have a number of target audiences with
  different experience in literature search strategies and different
  intentions:</p>
  <list list-type="bullet">
    <list-item>
      <p>librarian vs. academic vs. the general public</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>basic life sciences research vs. clinical research</p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
  <p>As PubMed is the most popular but not the only interface to the
  MEDLINE database, the primary target audience will not be a librarian,
  but someone with less experience in searching the biomedical
  literature (and less time). I would lump academics together with the
  general public here, and think that the typical PubMed search should
  be as simple as the typical Google search. Everything much more
  complicated than a simple input box should be moved to an
  <italic><italic>advanced search options</italic></italic> page, or
  should be done via a different interface to the MEDLINE database.</p>
  <p>Searching for clinical literature is very different from searching
  for basic science research. Here a search is often done to help in the
  decision making for a particular patient, and
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611025631/http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Evidence-based_medicine">evidence-based
  medicine</ext-link> is used to find the most relevant scientific
  literature (with meta-analyses and randomized controlled trials
  providing the best evidence).</p>
  <p>Searching for basic science literature has very different goals. It
  is either finding the needle in the haystack, e.g. you want to find
  all the published literature on the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611025631/http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.1176325">C3PO</ext-link>
  gene, or you want to find a review article as an overview over a
  particular field. But basic science review articles don't have the
  rigourous tools available to evaluate clinical research mentioned
  above, and here review articles only differ in the personal
  perspective of the reviewers and completeness and actuality of the
  primary literature that was covered. Searching for basic science
  literature should also be tightly integrated with the other databases
  at the NCBI. This is done via the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611025631/http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sites/gquery">Entrez
  Search Page</ext-link>, so that a search for
  <italic><italic>C3PO</italic></italic> also links to the organisms it
  was described in, e.g. this one:</p>
  <fig>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611025631im_/http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/f/fe/Tribolium.castaneum.jpg/91px-Tribolium.castaneum.jpg" xlink:title="" />
  </fig>
  <p>I don't think that a search interface to MEDLINE can be good at
  both the clinical and basic science literature. The current PubMed is
  much closer to the latter, so I think that the primary target audience
  for PubMed is the <italic><italic>academic or general public interest
  in basic life sciences research</italic></italic>. A good search
  interface for the clinical literature would be something very
  different and has to include both databases of evidence-based
  evaluations (particularly from the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611025631/http://www.cochrane.org/">Cochrane
  Collaboration</ext-link>) and from ongoing and completed clinical
  trials (particularly
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611025631/http://clinicaltrials.gov/">Clinicaltrials.gov</ext-link>,
  just like PubMed also hosted at the NIH).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="where-is-web-2-0">
  <title>Where is Web 2.0?</title>
  <p>A PubMed redesign in 2009 can't be complete without looking at what
  Web 2.0 has to offer. This means that users should be offered a
  personal PubMed account that links to their libraries for fulltext
  articles, stores common searches, creates RSS outputs, allows sharing
  of search results with other users, publishes a link to an interesting
  article on Twitter, and possibly other enhancements (e.g. a public
  profile page of all your PubMed articles, but that wouldn't work
  without
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611025631/http://themindwobbles.wordpress.com/2009/08/22/breakout-3-author-identity-creating-a-new-kind-of-reputation-online/">author
  identifiers</ext-link>). This also means a clean design, use of
  Javascript/AJAX for the user interface, a version for mobile users
  (particularly iPhone), and frequent small updates instead of a big
  desgin change every 2-3 years.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="and-how-is-the-redesigned-pubmed">
  <title>And how is the redesigned PubMed?</title>
  <p>After this rather long introduction, what do I like about the
  PubMed Redesign?</p>
  <fig>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611025631im_/http://gallery.me.com/mfenner/100079/pubmed/web.jpg" xlink:title="" />
  </fig>
</sec>
<sec id="like">
  <title>Like</title>
  <list list-type="bullet">
    <list-item>
      <p>Clean, uncluttered design</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Saving a search as RSS is faster and more obvious. I hope that
      this will make many more people use RSS than email alerts for
      their regular searches
      (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611025631/http://network.nature.com/people/mfenner/blog/2009/06/21/recipe-receiving-journal-table-of-contents-automatically">why
      I like RSS</ext-link>)</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Auto suggest: some of the most popular PubMed searches will be
      displayed based on the terms entered</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Some use of Javascript/AJAX</p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
</sec>
<sec id="dislike">
  <title>Dislike</title>
  <list list-type="bullet">
    <list-item>
      <p>The
      <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611025631/http://www.doi.org/">DOI</ext-link>
      (the best unique identifier for a paper and the easiest way to
      link to the full-text article) is still not displayed in the
      standard abstract view (you find the DOI in the Medline and XML
      views)</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Small design flaw: no easy way to go back from advanced search
      to basic search</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Layout is now different from MyNCBI and the other NCBI
      databases (maybe this is work in progress)</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>(As far as I know) no version for mobile users</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>No send to CiteULike/Connotea/Twitter/FriendFeed, etc. buttons
      (popular with many journals)</p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
  <p>The redesign will make it easier for inexperienced users to do
  quick searches (as mentioned above, probably the target audience).
  Experienced librarians might like the redesign less, as advanced
  searches have not become easier. But overall the changes are minor. My
  biggest complaint is the lack of DOI integration. A wasted
  opportunity. And – as mentioned above – I think we need a different
  MEDLINE interface for searching the clinical medicine literature.</p>
  <p>How do you like the redesign? Jacqueline Limpens is
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611025631/http://laikaspoetnik.wordpress.com/2009/10/01/pubmed&amp;Acirc;&amp;reg;-redesign-is-here-to-try/">doing
  a poll on her blog</ext-link>.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
