<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Tired of Impact Factors? Try the SJR
indicator</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2008-01-07">
<day>7</day>
<month>1</month>
<year>2008</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Picking the right journal is one of the most important decisions when
you start to work on a paper. You probably have a gut feeling of the
journals that are best suited for your paper in progress. To make this
decision more objective, you can rely on the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170910200523/http://scientific.thomson.com/free/essays/journalcitationreports/impactfactor/">Impact
Factor</ext-link> of a journal. The Impact Factor is roughly the average
number of citations per paper in a given journal and is published by
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170910200523/http://scientific.thomson.com/index.html">Thomson
Scientic</ext-link>. Higher Impact Factors mean more prestigious
journals. This information is also frequently used for job or grant
applications.</p>
<p>Impact factors have been around for more than 40 years and they
generally been very helpful. But there are two big problems:</p>
<sec id="impact-factors-are-published-by-one-privately-owned-company">
  <title>Impact Factors are published by one privately owned
  company</title>
  <p>Given the importance of Impact Factors for many aspects of
  scientific publishing, it would be preferable if there were
  alternatives. And Impact Factors are not freely available, but must be
  purchased from Thomson Scientific.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="impact-factors-might-not-be-the-best-tool-to-measure-scientific-quality">
  <title>Impact Factors might not be the best tool to measure scientific
  quality</title>
  <p>Impact factors have several shortcomings. Because they are a
  convenient way to judge the scientific output of a person,
  organization, journal or country, they are often overused. They should
  for example not be used to compare journals in different fields, e.g.
  cell biology and particle physics. Measures like the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170910200523/http://network.nature.com/blogs/user/mfenner/2007/08/17/do-you-know-your-hirsch-number">Hirsch
  Number</ext-link> might be a better tool to measure the scientific
  output of an individual scientist. And sometimes the judgement of your
  peers in the field is more important than simple numbers.</p>
  <p>The
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170910200523/http://www.scimagojr.com/">SCImago
  Journal Rank</ext-link> indicator tries to overcome these two
  shortcomings. The index was created by the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170910200523/http://www.scimago.es/">SCImage
  Research Group</ext-link>, located at several Spanish universities.
  The index uses information from the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170910200523/http://www.scopus.com/">Scopus</ext-link>
  abstract and citation database of research literature owned by
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170910200523/http://www.elsevier.com/">Elsevier</ext-link>.</p>
  <p>In contrast to the Impact Factor, the SJR indicator measures not
  simply the number of citations per paper. Citations from a journal
  with a higher SJR indicator lead to a higher SJR indicator for the
  cited journal (more details
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170910200523/http://www.scimagojr.com/SCImagoJournalRank.pdf">here</ext-link>).
  This approach is similar to PageRank (described in
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170910200523/http://infolab.stanford.edu/~backrub/google.html">this</ext-link>
  paper), the algorithm for web searches by Sergey Brin and Lawrence
  Page that made
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170910200523/http://www.google.com/">Google</ext-link>
  what it is today.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170910200523/http://www.eigenfactor.org/">Eigenfactor</ext-link>
  is another scientific ranking tool that uses a PageRank algorithm.</p>
  <p>Most of the time, journals with high Impact Factors have high SJR
  indicators. Nature and Science are still head to head. We will find
  unexpected results and discrepancies between the two over time. In my
  field of oncology, both the Journal of the NCI and Cancer Research are
  ranked higher than the Journal of Clinical Oncology.</p>
  <p>You can read more about the SJR indicator in this
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170910200523/http://www.nature.com/news/2008/080102/full/451006a.html">Nature
  News article</ext-link>.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
