<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Two reviews of new reference manager
ReadCube</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2011-10-11">
<day>11</day>
<month>10</month>
<year>2011</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<fig>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120610121628im_/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/files/2011/10/readcube3.jpeg" xlink:title="readcube3" />
</fig>
<p>Today,
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120610121628/http://www.digital-science.com/">Digital
Science</ext-link> announced an investment in startup
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120610121628/http://www.labtiva.com/">Labtiva</ext-link>.
And Labtiva released a “community preview” of their reference manager
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120610121628/http://www.readcube.com/">ReadCube</ext-link>.
The community preview is a free download for Windows and Mac, and this
is the summary of my first impressions.</p>
<p>You could write two different reviews about ReadCube. The first
version would mention the really slick interface, and the fun you have
using the program. ReadCube is doing a good job importing the PDFs on
your hard drive and adding bibliographic information to them. In
addition to PDF import you can also search PubMed and Google Scholar.
ReadCube helps you find related papers by listing the references and
citing papers of the paper you imported. ReaderCube also gives
recommendations based on the papers in your library.</p>
<fig>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120610121628im_/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/files/2011/10/readcube1-500x276.jpg" xlink:title="readcube" />
</fig>
<p>ReadCube includes an integrated PDF viewer that also allows text
highlighting and note taking.</p>
<fig>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120610121628im_/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/files/2011/10/readcube-500x275.jpg" xlink:title="readcube" />
</fig>
<p>The community preview is free, so please download ReadCube to find
out whether you like it.</p>
<p>The second review would take a different approach. It would ask what
problem ReadCube tries to solve, and why researchers should start using
ReadCube rather than the tools they already use, maybe for many years.
ReadCube is a reference manager with a particular focus on organizing
the PDFs of scholarly papers. There a number of programs out there that
can do the same.
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120610121628/http://www.mekentosj.com/papers/">Papers</ext-link>
for Macintosh for example is a very similar program, but the first
version of it has been released four years ago. Even more traditional
reference managers now include inline PDF readers with annotation
support, including the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120610121628/http://www.endnote.com/enx5info.asp">latest
version of Endnote</ext-link>. Mendeley and Zotero are two other
alternatives, and they are both free and available for Windows, Mac and
Linux. It’s difficult to see what is unique in ReadCube, and on the
other hand some important features are missing (e.g. no bookmarklet to
import from other sources, no reference type other than journal
articles, no group sharing feature, no integration with Microsoft Word).
And ReadCube is based on Adobe Air, a cross-platform development
environment that you either love or hate.</p>
<p>It will be interesting to watch what direction ReadCube development
will take. They started a few years later than their competitors, and it
will be a lot of work to catch up. I wish the Labtiva team good
luck.</p>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
