<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>UK PubMed Central: Interview with Phil
Vaughan</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2009-11-04">
<day>4</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2009</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<fig>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611110953im_/http://ukpmc.ac.uk/ppmc-localhtml/images/ukpmc_145.jpg" xlink:title="" />
</fig>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611110953/http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/">PubMed
Central</ext-link> was launched in February 2000 by the U.S. National
Institutes of Health (NIH) as a free digital archive of journal
articles. Just as PubMed, PubMed Central covers research in the life
sciences, but not other areas of research, e.g. engineering, physical
sciences or astronomy.</p>
<p>Some journal articles are available as full text as soon as they are
published, and most journals provide free access to full text articles
within a year of publication. Some journals only provide the full text
of some articles, including research funded by the NIH under the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611110953/http://publicaccess.nih.gov/policy.htm">NIH
Public Access Policy</ext-link>. The majority of fulltext articles in
PubMed Central are not Open Access, but are protected by copyright.
These articles are often made available under a license that allows
redistribution and reuse.</p>
<p>All articles are deposited using the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611110953/http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/">NLM-DTD</ext-link>
XML format, which is a standard text format suitable for text mining and
long-term archiving. Most articles are deposited directly by the
journals, so that authors do not have to get involved in the technical
aspects of article deposition.</p>
<p>PubMed Central is a centralized archive of full text papers and not
simply an interface to search these articles at the websites of the
participating journals. Neither is PubMed Central an interface to search
the various institutional repositories at universities and institutions.
The NIH thinks that this centralized approach makes it easier to develop
additional functionality, including the integration with other databases
(e.g. the protein or nucleotide databases) hosted at the NIH.</p>
<p>UK PubMed Central was launched in 2007 as the first PubMed Central
outside the United States
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611110953/http://pubmedcentralcanada.ca/">PubMed
Central Canada</ext-link>, the second international PubMed Central,
launched this week). In January 2010 UK PubMed Central will launch a
number of new services, and I used the opportunity to ask UK PubMed
Central Programme Manager Philip Vaughan a few questions.</p>
<fig>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611110953im_/http://gallery.me.com/mfenner/100079/philip_vaughan/web.jpg" xlink:title="" />
</fig>
<sec id="1-what-is-uk-pubmed-central">
  <title>1. What is UK PubMed Central?</title>
  <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611110953/http://ukpmc.ac.uk/">UK
  PubMed Central</ext-link> offers free access to 1.6 million full text
  journal articles in the fields of Life Sciences, Biomedicine and
  Health. Our content is free to read, print off and download. There is
  no registration process required: users can simply visit our site and
  start searching!It has been developed in consultation with the UK
  biomedical and health research community, and is about to launch some
  exciting new services in January 2010. Usage of our service has been
  growing steadily; we average 300,000 downloads a month currently.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="2-why-do-we-need-more-than-one-pubmed-central-and-how-are-they-connected">
  <title>2. Why do we need more than one PubMed Central, and how are
  they connected</title>
  <p>UKPMC gives the UK research community access to all the content of
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611110953/http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/">PMC</ext-link>,
  but with added value specifically for the UK. For example, it offers
  Grant Reporting features, whereby users can search for current grants
  from all of our 8 Funders, can link the publications they produce to
  the grants they originated from, and view the impact of their work
  through access to citations. UK researchers can also
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611110953/https://ukmss.mimas.ac.uk/ukmss">deposit
  their manuscripts directly</ext-link> into UKPMC.We will also be
  accessing additional content not in PMC; around 475,000 extra
  articles, reviews, guidelines and theses. Through the involvement of
  our funders, we are capturing around 90% of recently published journal
  articles from biomedical research conducted in the UK.We are therefore
  increasing the visibility of UK research in the field.</p>
  <p>Our colleagues at NCBI in the US have been very supportive of our
  activities: they have been keen for the PMC “project” to expand beyond
  the US. A Canadian version
  (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611110953/http://pubmedcentralcanada.ca/">PMC
  Canada</ext-link>) launched this week.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="3-why-does-a-search-use-pubmed-central-and-not-the-uk-version">
  <title>3. Why does a search use PubMed Central and not the UK
  version?</title>
  <p>The current UKPMC site searches PMC as it “mirrors” its content.
  But this about to change; from January UKPMC will be a “stand alone”
  service with its own up to date archive of content, as well as access
  to all the content of PubMed and PubMed Central.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="4-what-is-the-relationship-between-uk-pubmed-central-and-institutional-repositories">
  <title>4. What is the relationship between UK PubMed Central and
  institutional repositories?</title>
  <p>UKPMC is a subject repository and as such receives content from
  researchers at Higher Education institutions across the UK. Deposition
  in UKPMC is mandatory if a researcher has a grant from any of our 8
  Funders:
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611110953/http://www.wellcome.ac.uk/">Wellcome
  Trust</ext-link>,
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611110953/http://www.cancerresearchuk.org/">Cancer
  Research UK</ext-link>,
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611110953/http://www.mrc.ac.uk/">Medical
  Research Council</ext-link>,
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611110953/http://www.bhf.org.uk/">British
  Heart Foundation</ext-link>,
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611110953/http://www.arc.org.uk/">Arthritis
  Research Campaign</ext-link>,
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611110953/http://www.bbsrc.ac.uk/">Biotechnology
  and Biosciences Research Council</ext-link>,
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611110953/http://www.nihr.ac.uk/">National
  Institute for Health Research</ext-link> and the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611110953/http://www.sehd.scot.nhs.uk/cso/">Chief
  Scientists Office</ext-link>. Consequently we do not need to harvest
  content from other repositories. However, institutional repositories
  are welcome to harvest our content; we have an OAI-PMH interface to
  enable this. On the other hand, there are no plans to develop of
  institutional repositories from within UK PubMed Central.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="5-what-is-the-material-that-can-t-be-put-into-uk-pubmed-central">
  <title>5. What is the material that can't be put into UK PubMed
  Central?</title>
  <p>If the material is not peer-reviewed research published in a
  recognized journal by a known publisher, it would not be deposited
  into UK PubMed Central. One aspect of our development programme has
  been to identify what further content we could provide links to, for
  example published research theses and NHS clinical guidelines. But, we
  have rigid quality control procedures in place even to provide links
  to material. That said, we do remain open minded, in terms of what
  material we may consider linking to in the future. And who knows what
  might arise in the future. For example, there does seem to be an
  appetite to include images.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="6-can-i-submit-my-accepted-manuscript-if-it-was-not-funded-by-one-of-the-uk-pubmed-central-funders">
  <title>6. Can I submit my accepted manuscript if it was not funded by
  one of the UK PubMed Central funders?</title>
  <p>Unfortunately not at this time. We are hopeful that other UK
  research councils and funders of life sciences research will come on
  board in due course. The more funders that come on board, the stronger
  our service will become and the stronger our message on the importance
  of OA.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="7-what-is-the-uk-pubmed-central-oai-service">
  <title>7. What is the UK PubMed Central OAI service?</title>
  <p>The UK PubMed Central OAI service,
  (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611110953/http://ukpmc.ac.uk/ppmc-localhtml/oai_service.html">UKPMC-OAI</ext-link>)
  provides access to metadata of all items in the UKPMC archive, as well
  as to the full text of a subset of these items.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="8-what-are-your-responsibilities-at-uk-pubmed-central">
  <title>8. What are your responsibilities at UK PubMed Central?</title>
  <p>I am the Programme Manager. I am responsible for the current
  service which has been in existence since January 2007. I also
  co-ordinate all our current development activities, which are
  undertaken by ourselves at the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611110953/http://www.bl.uk/">British
  Library</ext-link>, by the University of Manchester
  (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611110953/http://mimas.ac.uk/">MIMAS</ext-link>),
  the National Centre for Text Mining
  (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611110953/http://www.nactem.ac.uk/">NacTEM</ext-link>
  – based at the University of Manchester) and the European
  Bioinformatics Institute
  (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611110953/http://www.ebi.ac.uk/">EBI</ext-link>)
  based at Hinxton in Cambridgeshire.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="9-what-did-you-do-before-starting-to-work-on-uk-pubmed-central">
  <title>9. What did you do before starting to work on UK PubMed
  Central?</title>
  <p>I originally trained as a librarian. Since then I have worked
  mainly in health and medical information work, both in Higher
  Education and in the National Health Service. My most recent post was
  for
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611110953/http://www.jisc.ac.uk/">JISC</ext-link>
  (Joint Information Systems Committee) as a Programme Manager. I was
  responsible for a portfolio of development projects in the digital
  library sphere. I joined UKPMC at the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611110953/http://www.bl.uk/">British
  Library</ext-link> in May 2008.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="10-do-you-want-to-talk-about-future-plans-for-uk-pubmed-central">
  <title>10. Do you want to talk about future plans for UK PubMed
  Central?</title>
  <p>Yes please! We are soon to launch some exciting new initiatives in
  January 2010. Our website has been completely redesigned with a new
  more intuitive interface, and we will be expanding our content to
  include all content from PubMed (c. 18m references), patents, theses
  and
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611110953/http://www.library.nhs.uk/GUIDELINESFINDER/">NHS
  Clinical Guidelines</ext-link>. Consequently our users will be able to
  access a vast collection of relevant content through one portal.</p>
  <p>Our search engine will be utilising innovative new techniques such
  as text mining to retrieve more contextually relevant information,
  link to other relevant databases and provide a richer search
  experience for the user. We are also expanding our Grant Reporting
  functions to allow Grantees and Funders to assess the impact and value
  of their funded research, and increase their visibility.</p>
  <p>Our Funders are keen to expand the programme, possibly towards a
  future <italic><italic>European PubMed Central</italic></italic>.We
  are hopeful that as part of this process some European Funders may be
  joining the programme shortly. Our Funders hope to make an
  announcement regarding this shortly.</p>
  <p>We are holding a Showcase event on January 12th at the British
  Library in London to highlight these new developments and the future
  potential of the service.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="11-could-you-provide-contact-information-for-people-that-have-further-questions-about-pubmed-central">
  <title>11. Could you provide contact information for people that have
  further questions about PubMed Central?</title>
  <p>By all means, people can email us at
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611110953/mailto:ukpmc%40bl.uk">ukpmc@bl.uk</ext-link>
  and my email is
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611110953/http://bl.uk/">Philip.Vaughan@bl.uk</ext-link>.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
