<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Using RNA interference to identify genes that protect
from cancer</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2008-02-07">
<day>7</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2008</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Cancer is caused by genetic
changes<sup><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611110843/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2008/02/07/using_rna_interference_to_identify_genes_that_protect_from_cancer/#fn1">1</ext-link></sup>.
Oncogenes harbor activating mutations that cause or promote cancer,
whereas tumor suppressor
genes<sup><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611110843/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2008/02/07/using_rna_interference_to_identify_genes_that_protect_from_cancer/#fn2">2</ext-link></sup>
protect from cancer. In this model, genetic changes in one copy of an
oncogene, but both copies of a tumor suppressor gene are required to
initiate cancer. This simple model is complicated by the fact that more
than one genetic change is usually required to initiate cancer, and that
other so called epigenetic changes (such as promoter hypermethylation)
are also important.</p>
<p>Myelodysplastic syndromes are malignant disorders of the bone marrow
that show insufficient production of blood cells and harbor the risk of
progressing to acute myeloid leukemia. The 5q syndrome is a distinct
subtype that is characterized by loss of genetic material at chromosome
5q31, a characteristic morphology of the bone marrow, and a fairly
benign clinical course. We would expect to find a tumor suppressor gene
in the deleted region on chromosome 5, but no genetic changes on the
other allele of chromosome 5 could be detected. The traditional
strategies to identify the genetic changes responsible for the 5q
syndrome therefore didn't work.</p>
<p>Research by Benjamin Ebert et al. presented at the American Society
of Hematology meeting in December and now published in
Nature<sup><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611110843/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2008/02/07/using_rna_interference_to_identify_genes_that_protect_from_cancer/#fn3">3</ext-link></sup>
claims to have finally identified the genetic change responsible for 5q
syndrome. They used RNA interference to in turn knock out each of the 40
genes in the common deleted region on chromosome 5q31. They observed the
phenotype of human hematopoetic progenitor cells transfected with short
hairpin RNAs. The shRNA targeting the gene RPS14 recapitulated the
phenotype of patients with 5q syndrome.</p>
<p>To confirm the role of RPS14 in 5q syndrome, RPS14 was overexpressed
in hematopoetic cells from patients with 5q syndrome and indeed reverted
the erythroid differentiation effect. Reduced expression or inactivating
mutations of the one remaining RPS14 gene in 5q syndrome patients was
ruled out by sequencing and gene expression profiling.</p>
<p>Further evidence for the importance of RPS14 in 5q syndrome comes
from studies of related genes. Expression of RPS14 is required for
proper function of the 40s ribosomal subunit. Germline mutations of two
other ribosomal proteins, RPS19 and RPS24, have been identified in the
congenital disorder Diamond-Blackfan anemia, and the disease in these
children has similar features.</p>
<p>As a medical student, I was fortunate enough to listen to Alfred
Knudson give a talk about is two-hit hypothesis of tumor suppressor
genes<sup><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611110843/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2008/02/07/using_rna_interference_to_identify_genes_that_protect_from_cancer/#fn2">2</ext-link></sup>,
and I was fascinated by cancer genetics ever since. Genetics continues
to be a driving force in our understanding of cancer. The next big step
in the 5q syndrome story will be a better understanding of why the drug
lenalidomide works so well in this disease, and how this relates to
RPS14 function. More information about the Ebert paper can be found in
this Nature
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611110843/http://www.nature.com/nature/journal/v451/n7176/full/451252a.html">News
and Views</ext-link> article.</p>
<p>fn1.
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611110843/http://content.nejm.org/cgi/content/short/358/5/502">Croce
C. Oncogenes and Cancer</ext-link></p>
<p>fn2.
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611110843/http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/articlerender.fcgi?tool=pubmed&amp;pubmedid=5279523">Knudson
AG. Mutation and Cancer: Statistical Study of
Retinoblastoma</ext-link></p>
<p>fn3.
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611110843/http://www.nature.com/nature/journal/v451/n7176/full/nature06494.html">Ebert
BL et al. Identification of RPS14 as a 5qsyndrome gene by</ext-link>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611110843/http://www.nature.com/nature/journal/v451/n7176/full/nature06494.html">RNA
interference screen</ext-link></p>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
