<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Using Google Wave for a week – it’s still
great!</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2009-07-18">
<day>18</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2009</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150922174142/http://wave.google.com/">Google
Wave</ext-link> is a new tool for communication and collaboration on the
web. When Wave was first announced May 28 at the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150922174142/http://code.google.com/intl/de-DE/events/io/">Google
I/O conference</ext-link>, many people immediately saw its potential as
a great collaboration tool for scientists:</p>
<list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
    <p>Ricardo Vidal:
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150922174142/http://my.biotechlife.net/2009/05/29/using-the-google-wave-to-surf-the-streams/">Using
    Google Wave to surf the streams</ext-link></p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>Me:
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150922174142/http://network.nature.com/people/mfenner/blog/2009/05/28/google-wave-dont-forget-the-scientists">Google
    Wave – don't forget the scientists</ext-link></p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>Cameron Neylon:
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150922174142/http://blog.openwetware.org/scienceintheopen/2009/05/30/omg-this-changes-everything-or-yet-another-wave-of-adulation/">OMG!
    This changes EVERYTHING! – or – Yet Another Wave of
    Adulation</ext-link> and
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150922174142/http://blog.openwetware.org/scienceintheopen/2009/06/08/google-wave-in-research-the-slightly-more-sober-view-part-i-papers/">Google
    Wave in Research – the slightly more sober view – Part I –
    Papers</ext-link></p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>Peter Murray-Rust:
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150922174142/http://wwmm.ch.cam.ac.uk/blogs/murrayrust/?p=2026">Google
    Wave first reactions</ext-link> and
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150922174142/http://wwmm.ch.cam.ac.uk/blogs/murrayrust/?p=2032">Google
    Wave and implications for science</ext-link></p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>Björn Brembs:
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150922174142/http://bjoern.brembs.net/news.php?item.521.3">Will
    science ride the Google Wave into the 21st century</ext-link></p>
  </list-item>
</list>
<p>We based our first impressions on the material available online,
especially the video of the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150922174142/http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=v_UyVmITiYQ&amp;feature=player_embedded">Google
Wave presentation</ext-link> at Google I/O. The problem is, Wave is
currently only available to selected developers, and will not be
generally available until the end of the year. Wave is currently not
even beta software and was announced now so that third-party developers
have enough time to build (and test) extensions to Wave.</p>
<p>Those of us being invited to
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150922174142/http://www.nature.com/scifoo/index.html">SciFoo</ext-link>
(which took place July 10-12 at Google) were lucky not only in attending
a great conference, but also in getting a Wave account. Wave product
manager <italic><italic>Steph Hannon</italic></italic> gave us an
introduction to Wave on the first evening, and <italic><italic>Cameron
Neylon</italic></italic> organized a session about Wave the next day.
The session was mainly about the Wave extensions that we scientists
would need (and I'm sure that Cameron will blog about that), but we
could also ask two developers from the Wave team a lot of questions.</p>
<p>After using Wave for one week, I obviously have a much better feeling
for how it can help scientists to communicate and collaborate. The best
way to start is to think of Wave as email on steroids. Wave is web-based
(which means that it currently only works when you have an internet
connection) with a nice interface similar to Gmail or other webmail
products. One big advantage over email is that all reply messages are
directly connected to the original message (similar to comments on a
blog). This is especially helpful for longer email threads and when more
than two people are involved.</p>
<p>But Wave is also instant messaging. You see a small green dot next to
your contacts that are currently online, and you can see them typing in
real-time (which looks really creepy the first time you see that).</p>
<p>And Wave is also like a Wiki. You can not only respond to a message,
but everybody participating in the Wave can also change the original
message (and several people can work on the same message
simultaneously). This works great for things such as listing all the
blog posts about SciFoo.</p>
<p>The combination of wiki-style editing plus comments make Wave an
interesting alternative to project management tools such as
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150922174142/http://basecamphq.com/">Basecamp</ext-link>.
And this means that Wave can also be used to work on longer documents –
something that the Wave developers regularly do for documentation, etc.
Wave documents can also contain images, videos, links, etc. Wave
supports different fonts, text colors, bold and italic text, and four
different heading levels (for titles and subtitles).</p>
<p>But in contrast to most online collaboration tools, Wave can be
extended with additional functionality that scientists require.
Bibliographic references would be an obvious example, and here tools
such as
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150922174142/http://docs.google.com/">Google
Docs</ext-link> or
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150922174142/http://buzzword.acrobat.com/">Adobe
Buzzword</ext-link> fall short.</p>
<p>Wave extensions come in the form of gadgets (that work on the client)
and robots (that work on the server). Wave gadgets are XML files,
whereas robots can currently be developed in either Java or Python.
Other programming languages (PHP, Ruby, Perl, etc.) for robots will soon
become possible when robots no longer have to be hosted on
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150922174142/http://code.google.com/appengine">Google
App Engine</ext-link>. Using the tools provided by Google, writing a
robot is actually not that difficult and it took me only an hour to have
a sample “Hello World!” robot running in Wave. It will obviously take
weeks or months to develop more sophisticated robots (e.g. for
management of bibliographic references), but I'm sure that a number of
exciting science-related extensions will be ready by the time Wave
becomes publicly available later this year.</p>
<p>We plan a session with a live Wave demo at the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150922174142/http://www.scienceonlinelondon.org/">Science
Online London</ext-link> conference in August so that more scientists
and science communicators become familiar with Wave. About 10 people
that registered for the conference already have Wave accounts and I hope
that some of them will come up with interesting science-related robots
or gadgets. If you are a Wave user, you can reach me at
mfenner@wavesandbox.com. And if you want to develop great
science-related extensions for Wave, please contact
<italic><italic>Cameron Neylon</italic></italic>.</p>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
