<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Webinar on Writing Zotero Translators</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2014-10-17">
<day>17</day>
<month>10</month>
<year>2014</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>In a
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://blog.martinfenner.org/2014/10/01/please-keep-it-simple-citations-links-and-references/">blog
post two weeks ago</ext-link> I argued for the need for reference
managers to properly support data citation, if we want data citation to
become a standard activity. I am happy to announce two events working
towards that goal.</p>
<sec id="november-3rd-webinar-on-writing-zotero-web-translators">
  <title>November 3rd: Webinar on writing Zotero web translators</title>
  <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.zotero.org/blog/community-spotlight-sebastian-karcher/">Sebastian
  Karcher</ext-link>, one of the most prolific authors of Zotero web
  translators (and citation styles), has kindly offered to hold an
  introductory webinar on writing Zotero web translators. These web
  translators allow Zotero to import metadata about a scholarly work
  from a variety of places, and new web translators for repositories
  that hold research data (or software) would go a long way towards
  making data citation easier for authors.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.zotero.org/support/dev/translators">Web
  translators</ext-link> are written in Javascript and only basic
  Javascript knowledge is required. The free webinar takes place on
  November 3rd on 5 PM UK time (12 PM EST) and the registration form is
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.eventbrite.com/e/writing-zotero-translators-webinar-tickets-13768797845">here</ext-link>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="january-11-force11-pre-conference-workshop-on-data-citation-support-in-reference-managers">
  <title>January 11: Force11 Pre-Conference workshop on Data Citation
  Support in Reference Managers</title>
  <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.force11.org/meetings/force2015/pre-conference-meeting-list">This
  workshop</ext-link>, coorganized with Ian Mulvany, will extend the
  Zotero web translator work to other reference managers, including
  Papers and Mendeley. This will be a hackathon with the goal to get
  some things working in these reference managers, but it should also be
  interesting for others, as we will discuss what is missing to make
  data citation work in reference managers.</p>
  <p>My personal goal is to learn to write a Zotero web translator in
  the webinar, and then write a working web translator for the three
  biological databases ENA, PDB and Uniprot before the January workshop.
  And hopefully these activities generate enough interest that other
  people write web translators for their favorite research data database
  or software repository, and that the proprietary reference managers
  Papers and Mendeley (and hopefully others) also add support for these
  data sources.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
