<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>What are the right numbers for JUPITER?</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2008-11-23">
<day>23</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2008</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Results of clinical trials can sometimes not only change our
understanding of the condition studied, but may also affect the way we
practice medicine. The Justification for the Use of Statins in Primary
Prevention: an Intervention Trial Evaluating Rosuvastatin
(<italic><italic>JUPITER</italic></italic>) is such a study.</p>
<p>JUPITER was investigating the prevention of major cardiovascular
events (myocardial infarction, stroke, hospitalization for unstable
angina, arterial revascularization, death from cardiovascular causes) by
treatment with rosuvastatin compared to placebo. Many clinical trials
before have looked at the reduction of cardiovascular events by statin
treatment in people with elevated cholesterol levels. But in the JUPITER
trial, 17,802 apparently healthy men and women with normal levels of LDL
cholesterol (&lt; 130 mg/dl) were included based on age (&gt; 50 years
for men, &gt; 60 years for women) and elevated levels of
high-sensitivity C-reactive protein (&gt; 2,0 mg/l), a marker for
inflammation. The trial was stopped early in March of this year (after a
median follow-up of 1.9 years instead of the planned 4 years) because
treatment with rosuvastatin significantly reduced the number of
cardiovascular events: 0.77 per 100 person-years compared to 1.36 per
100 person-years for placebo. In other words, treating 120 people for
1.9 years with rosuvastatin (at a cost of about $287.000) would prevent
one cardiovascular event.</p>
<p>The JUPITER trial is important not only because it shows that a
statin can have a beneficial effect in people with normal LDL
cholesterol. Which complicates our understanding on how statins work.
More importantly, we now have to reconsider who should be treated with
statins. What do we do with a small but significant effect in a large
group of apparently healthy people? The treatment is expensive
(cardiovascular events can probably be prevented for less than $287.000
by other means, e.g. changes in diet and exercise) and can have side
effects (e.g. an increase in newly diagnosed diabetes in the JUPITER
trial). And, like most important studies, the JUPITER trial raises a
number of important new questions. But instead of discussing some of
these questions I rather want to look at how we can obtain information
about the JUPITER trial.</p>
<sec id="clinical-trial-databases">
  <title>Clinical Trial Databases</title>
  <p>Since 2005 all clinical trials have to be registered in publicly
  available databases, and information about JUPITER is
  available.<sup><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053051/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2008/11/23/what_are_the_right_numbers_for_jupiter/#fn1">1</ext-link></sup>
  Since September 2008, newly registered trials also have to report
  their main
  outcomes.<sup><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053051/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2008/11/23/what_are_the_right_numbers_for_jupiter/#fn2">2</ext-link></sup>
  This will become important in the future, as the main outcomes of
  unpublished trials (most likely trials with negative results) will
  become publicly available no later than 12 months after data for the
  last subject were received.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="press-releases">
  <title>Press Releases</title>
  <p>JUPITER was stopped early in March 2008 and AstraZeneca (the
  sponsor of the trial and manufacturer of rosuvastatin) issued a press
  release.<sup><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053051/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2008/11/23/what_are_the_right_numbers_for_jupiter/#fn3">3</ext-link></sup>
  Another press release was issued on November 9 when the JUPITER
  results were first presented
  publicly.<sup><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053051/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2008/11/23/what_are_the_right_numbers_for_jupiter/#fn4">4</ext-link></sup>
  As can be expected from press releases, there is selective reporting
  of the trial results. No absolute numbers for risk reductions were
  reported, and emphasis was put on relative risk reductions. Instead of
  the actual number needed to treat (NNT, 120 patients treated for 1.9
  years), a projected NNT (25 patients treated for 5 years) was
  reported. And a significant increase in newly diagnosed diabetes (3.0%
  vs. 2.4%, p=0.01) was reported as <italic><italic>“there was a small
  increase in physician reported diabetes consistent with data from
  other large placebo controlled statin trials.”</italic></italic></p>
</sec>
<sec id="presentation-at-a-meeting">
  <title>Presentation at a Meeting</title>
  <p>The JUPITER results were presented on November 9 at the annual
  meeting of the American Heart Association (AHA) in New Orleans. More
  than 6,000 people were listening to this presentation according to
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053051/http://network.nature.com/people/UD280A82C/profile">James
  Butcher</ext-link> on the Nature in the Field
  blog<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053051/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2008/11/23/what_are_the_right_numbers_for_jupiter/#fn5">5</ext-link>.
  The abstract of the presentation is available
  here.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053051/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2008/11/23/what_are_the_right_numbers_for_jupiter/#fn6">6</ext-link>
  The abstract also lists the potential conflicts of interest of the
  study authors (the senior author Paul Ridger Ridker is co-inventor of
  patents on CRP testing in cardiovascular disease). The AHA issued a
  press release on that
  day<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053051/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2008/11/23/what_are_the_right_numbers_for_jupiter/#fn7">7</ext-link>
  and commented primarily on the role of CRP testing in the trial.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="journal-paper">
  <title>Journal Paper</title>
  <p>The JUPITER study was published in the <italic><italic>New England
  Journal of Medicine (NEJM)</italic></italic> on November
  20<sup><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053051/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2008/11/23/what_are_the_right_numbers_for_jupiter/#fn8">8</ext-link></sup>,
  but the paper was preleased on the day of the presentation at the AHA
  meeting. The full-text PDF of the paper is available without
  subscription. The full paper is of course the best source to all the
  primary data. As is typical for many medical journals, it contains a
  structured abstract, which is a nice summary of the paper.
  Interestingly, the <italic><italic>NEJM</italic></italic> is
  conducting a poll and asks the readers two questions on how the
  JUPITER results changed their clinical
  practice.<sup><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053051/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2008/11/23/what_are_the_right_numbers_for_jupiter/#fn9">9</ext-link></sup>
  And there are over 400 reader comments as of today.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="editorials">
  <title>Editorials</title>
  <p>The full paper is discussed in an editorial in the same
  issue<sup><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053051/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2008/11/23/what_are_the_right_numbers_for_jupiter/#fn10">10</ext-link></sup>,
  and is also discussed in an editorial in the British Medical
  Journal<sup><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053051/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2008/11/23/what_are_the_right_numbers_for_jupiter/#fn11">11</ext-link></sup>.
  Only the editorial in the <italic><italic>NEJM</italic></italic> is
  available without subscription, but both critically discuss the paper
  and put it in perspective.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="traditional-news">
  <title>Traditional News</title>
  <p>The JUPITER trial was of course discussed in many traditional news
  media such as newspapers, radio and television. The
  <italic><italic>New York Times</italic></italic> had a long
  article<sup><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053051/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2008/11/23/what_are_the_right_numbers_for_jupiter/#fn12">12</ext-link></sup>
  where the author had interviewed not only the study authors but also
  several experts in the field. The article discusses several issues
  surrounding the study, but failed to report the absolute risk
  reduction or the number needed to treat (important numbers for the
  reasons discussed above). National Public Radio discussed the story
  with two cardiologists, including the author of the editorial in the
  <italic><italic>NEJM</italic></italic> (available as transcript and
  audio
  file).<sup><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053051/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2008/11/23/what_are_the_right_numbers_for_jupiter/#fn13">13</ext-link></sup>
  The interview is again short on actual numbers, but puts JUPITER in
  perspective for the typical radio listener. The Nature News
  article<sup><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053051/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2008/11/23/what_are_the_right_numbers_for_jupiter/#fn14">14</ext-link></sup>
  also didn't mention the number needed to treat. Stopping a trial early
  can be controversial, because the numbers for risks and benefits might
  look different at the planned end of the trial. Nature News should
  have talked to someone that was not involved in that decision in the
  JUPITER trial.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="blogs">
  <title>Blogs</title>
  <p>Scintilla has aggregated the blog posts on this
  study<sup><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053051/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2008/11/23/what_are_the_right_numbers_for_jupiter/#fn15">15</ext-link></sup>.
  Harriet Hall on the Science-Based Medicine Blog not only has the story
  with the best title (<italic><italic>Statins Are Better on
  JUPITER</italic></italic>), but gives a detailed analysis of the study
  results. Ben Goldacre on Bad Science has a shorter blog post that is
  more of a discussion of absolute risk, relative risk and number needed
  to treat (as the title of the blog post
  suggests).<sup><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053051/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2008/11/23/what_are_the_right_numbers_for_jupiter/#fn16">16</ext-link></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="conclusions">
  <title>Conclusions</title>
  <p>There are many ways we can learn more about the JUPITER trial, and
  most of this information is freely available, including the full-text
  of the paper. It is not the access to the primary data that is the
  problem, but rather the many different ways the results can be put
  into perspective. And for that we need not only a basic understanding
  of cardiovascular risks, but also clinical trials. And we should not
  forget the financial and other interests that are always connected to
  large trial like this. I didn't do a systematic analysis of the
  newspaper articles and blog posts about the study, but it is clear to
  me that science blogs can add an important perspective.</p>
  <p>fn1. JUPITER – Crestor 20mg Versus Placebo in Prevention of
  Cardiovascular (CV) Events.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053051/http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00239681">ClinicalTrials.gov
  NCT00239681 October 13, 2005</ext-link></p>
  <p>fn2.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053051/http://network.nature.com/people/mfenner/blog/2008/08/02/fdaaa-push-to-open-data-in-clinical-medicine">FDAAA:
  Push to open data in clinical medicine</ext-link></p>
  <p>fn3. Crestor Outcomes Study JUPITER Closes Early Due To Unequivocal
  Evidence Of Benefit.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053051/http://www.astrazeneca.com/pressrelease/5385.aspx">AstraZeneca
  Press Release March 31, 2008</ext-link></p>
  <p>fn4. CRESTOR Demonstrates Dramatic CV Risk Reduction in a Large
  Statin Outcomes Study.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053051/http://www.astrazeneca.com/pressrelease/5412.aspx">AstraZeneca
  Press Release November 9, 2008</ext-link></p>
  <p>fn5. AHA 2008: Should statins be put in the water? James Butcher.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053051/http://blogs.nature.com/news/blog/2008/11/should_statins_be_put_in_the_w.html">In
  the Field November 11, 2008</ext-link></p>
  <p>fn6. Late-breaking abstracts.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053051/http://americanheart.mediaroom.com/index.php?s=54&amp;item=212">News
  Conference November 9, 2008</ext-link></p>
  <p>fn7. American Heart Association Comment on JUPITER trial.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053051/http://americanheart.mediaroom.com/index.php?s=43&amp;item=582">AHA
  Press Release November 9, 2008</ext-link></p>
  <p>fn8. P. M Ridker, E. Danielson, F. A.H. Fonseca, J. Genest, A. M.
  Gotto, J. J.P. Kastelein, W. Koenig, P. Libby, A. J. Lorenzatti, J. G.
  MacFadyen, B. G. Nordestgaard, J. Shepherd, J. T. Willerson, R. J.
  Glynn (2008). Rosuvastatin to Prevent Vascular Events in Men and Women
  with Elevated C-Reactive Protein <italic>New England Journal of
  Medicine, 359</italic> (21), 2195-2207 DOI:
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053051/http://dx.doi.org/10.1056/NEJMoa0807646">10.1056/NEJMoa0807646</ext-link></p>
  <p>fn9. The JUPITER Trial: Will You Change Your Practice?
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053051/http://www.nejm.org/clinical-directions/jupiter-statins-trial/?query=TOC">Clinical
  Directions</ext-link></p>
  <p>fn10. M. A. Hlatky (2008). Expanding the Orbit of Primary
  Prevention — Moving beyond JUPITER <italic>New England Journal of
  Medicine, 359</italic> (21), 2280-2282 DOI:
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053051/http://dx.doi.org/10.1056/NEJMe0808320">10.1056/NEJMe0808320</ext-link></p>
  <p>fn11. N. Donner-Banzhoff, A. Sonnichsen (2008). Statins and primary
  prevention of cardiovascular events <italic>BMJ, 337</italic> (nov14
  2) DOI:
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053051/http://dx.doi.org/10.1136/bmj.a2576">10.1136/bmj.a2576</ext-link></p>
  <p>fn12. Cholesterol-Fighting Drugs Show Wider Benefit. Pam Belluck.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053051/http://www.nytimes.com/2008/11/10/health/10heart.html">New
  York Times November 10, 2008</ext-link></p>
  <p>fn13. Study Finds Statins Benefit Patients With no History of Heart
  Problems.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053051/http://www.pbs.org/newshour/bb/health/july-dec08/statins_11-10.html">PBS
  Newshour November 10, 2008</ext-link></p>
  <p>fn14. Should healthy people take statins too? Katharine Sanderson.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053051/http://www.nature.com/news/2008/081110/full/news.2008.1218.html">Nature
  News November 10, 2008</ext-link></p>
  <p>fn15. Search for term rosuvastatin.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053051/http://scintilla.nature.com/search/feed_item?t=rosuvastatin">Scintilla</ext-link></p>
  <p>fn16. Statins Are Better on JUPITER. Harriet Hall.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053051/http://www.sciencebasedmedicine.org/?p=282">Science-Based
  Medicine November 11, 2008</ext-link></p>
  <p>fn17. You are 80% less likely to die from a meteor landing on your
  head if you wear a bicycle helmet all day. Ben Goldacre.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150924053051/http://www.badscience.net/2008/11/you-are-80-less-likely-to-die-from-a-meteor-landing-on-your-head-if-you-wear-a-bicycle-helmet-all-day/">Bad
  Science November 15, 2008</ext-link></p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
