<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>What comes after Google Wave?</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2010-08-09">
<day>9</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2010</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Google
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120524201336/http://googleblog.blogspot.com/2010/08/update-on-google-wave.html">announced
last week</ext-link> that they will stop further development of Google
Wave, and essentially shut down the service by the end of the year. Some
of the more exciting parts of Wave will be reused in other Google
products or – since many parts of Google Wave have been made available
under an Open Source license, in products by other companies. But the
announcement is an admission that the adoption by users and developers
had not been what Google had hoped for with this very ambitious
project.</p>
<p>Google Wave was first announced at Google I/O in May 2009, and
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120524201336/http://blogs.nature.com/mfenner/2009/07/18/using-google-wave-for-a-week-its-still-great">I
had a Google Wave account</ext-link> since July 2009 thanks to being
invited to the SciFoo conference (where every attendee got one of those
then still rare Wave invites). Like
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120524201336/http://cameronneylon.net/blog/the-triumph-of-document-layout-and-the-demise-of-google-wave/">others</ext-link>,
I saw the tremendous potential to improve on existing tools for
researchers to collaborate. But after 12 months, Google Wave hasn't
replaced email as communication tool in at least some of my
collaborations. Many people have pointed out the reasons for the lack of
user adoption of Google Wave. I want to focus on something else: Google
Wave tried to solve a problem that is very relevant to scientists, and
we still don't have a solution for that problem.</p>
<p>Email has become the primary tool for many scientists to collaborate
with colleagues both within the same institution, and between different
institutions. Despite this popularity, email and the typical workflow
around it has several significant shortcomings:</p>
<p><italic><italic>Email is not good in tracking longer conversations
between more than two people.</italic></italic> Even though email
messages can be grouped together, it quickly becomes difficult to follow
the discussion. And it is even more complicated for those joining the
discussion later.</p>
<p><italic><italic>Email is not good in sharing
documents.</italic></italic> Sending large documents repeatedly back and
forth is not only a waste of network bandwidth and limited email storage
capacities, but is also not a very productive way to collaboratively
work on a longer document, as it quickly becomes difficult to merge the
different document versions together.</p>
<p><italic><italic>Word processors are not good tools to write
scientific documents.</italic></italic> Traditional word processors such
as Microsoft Word or LaTeX care too much about document formatting, and
still approach a document primarily as something an individual user
edits on a single computer.</p>
<p>Maybe user uptake for Google Wave was low because the approach to
tackle these problems was too radical. Many other, less radical tools
try to solve the same problems, including mailing lists, wikis, social
bookmarking sites such as CiteULike, collaborative writing tools such as
Google Docs, and project management tools such as Basecamp.</p>
<p>Where do we go from here? Because most of the technology behind
Google Wave has been made available, we could continue to use and
develop Google Wave and Wave extensions for scientists. But that is a
very risky strategy that not many people would follow. We can also wait
for new tools that help scientists collaborate, and there interesting
products announced every few months. For the time being I will continue
trying to convince my colleagues to use some of the existing tools
instead of email where appropriate, something that is surprisingly
difficult.</p>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
