<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>What is holding us back?</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2013-11-11">
<day>11</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Last Friday and Saturday the 6th
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nature.com/spoton/event/spoton-london2013/">SpotOn
London conference</ext-link> tool place at the British Library. I had a
great time with many interesting sessions and good conversations both in
and between sessions. But I might be biased, since I helped organize the
event, and in particular did help put the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nature.com/spoton/?cat=11">sessions
for the Tools strand</ext-link> together.</p>
<fig>
  <caption><p><bold>SpotOn London name tags</bold>. Flickr photo by
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/keatl/10739125344/in/photolist-hmYPPw-9CVkfd/">keatl</ext-link>.</p></caption>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="http://blog.martinfenner.org/images/blendology.jpg" xlink:title="" />
</fig>
<p>The following blog post summarizes some of my thoughts before, during
and after the conference, and I want to focus on innovation in scholarly
publishing, or rather: what is holding us back?</p>
<sec id="reason-1">
  <title>Reason #1</title>
  <p>The
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nature.com/spoton/event/spoton-london-2013-whats-your-number-altmetrics-session/">#solo13alt</ext-link>
  session on Saturday looked at <italic>the role of altmetrics in the
  evaluation of scientific research</italic>. I was one of the panelists
  and had summarized my ideas prior to the session in a
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://blogs.plos.org/tech/evaluating-impact-whats-your-number/">blog
  post</ext-link> written together with Jennifer Lin. It was an
  interesting session, although a bit too controversial for my taste.
  But it became obvious to me in this and a few other sessions that
  other obsession with quantitative assessment of science is
  increasingly dangerous. Other people have said this more
  eloquently:</p>
  <list list-type="bullet">
    <list-item>
      <p>The mania for measurement - Stephen Curry in the
      <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nature.com/spoton/event/spoton-london-2013-whats-your-number-altmetrics-session/">#solo13alt</ext-link>
      session</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Why research assessment is out of control -
      <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.theguardian.com/education/2013/nov/04/peter-scott-research-excellence-framework">Peter
      Scott</ext-link></p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Universities are becoming metrics factories, driven by large
      corporates -
      <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://blogs.ch.cam.ac.uk/pmr/2013/11/10/spoton2013-yet-another-wonderful-meeting/">Peter
      Murray-Rust</ext-link></p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>The ‘real’ revolution in science will come when the scientific
      egosystem gets rid of the credit-imperative -
      <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://twitter.com/Villavelius/status/399157271793762304">Jan
      Velterop</ext-link></p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Excellence by Nonsense: The Competition for Publications in
      Modern Science -
      <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://book.openingscience.org/basics_background/excellence_by_nonsense/">Mathias
      Binswanger</ext-link></p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
  <p>My job title is <italic>Technical Lead Article-Level
  Metrics</italic> so it might sound surprising that I say this. But we
  have to differentiate of what we do now and in the next few years -
  which is mainly to get away from the Journal Impact Factor to more
  reasonable metrics that look at individual articles and include other
  metrics besides citations - to where we want to be in 10 or more
  years. And for the latter it is essential that journal articles and
  other research outputs are valued for the research they contain,
  rather than serving as a currency for <italic>merit</italic> that can
  be exchanged into grants and acadmic advancement. This is a very
  difficult problem to solve and I have no answers yet. Going back to
  how science was conducted until about 50 years ago - as a small elite
  club that worked based on closed personal networks - is definitely not
  the answer.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="reason-2">
  <title>Reason #2</title>
  <p>In
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nature.com/spoton/event/spoton-london-2013-keynote-1-boson-50-years-50003-scientists-understanding-our-universe-through-global-scientific-collaboration-and-open-access/">his
  keynote</ext-link> Salvatore Mele from CERN explained to us that Open
  Access in High Energy Phsics is 50 years old, and that the culture of
  sharing preprints preceeded the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://arxiv.org/">ArXiv</ext-link>
  e-prints service - scientists were mailing their manuscripts to each
  other at least 20 years before ArXiV launched in 1991. A similar
  culture doesn’t exist in the life sciences and therefore the preprint
  services for biologists launched this year (e.g.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://peerj.com/preprints/">PeerJ
  Preprints</ext-link> and
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://biorxiv.org/">bioRxiv</ext-link>)
  will have a hard time gaining traction.</p>
  <p>Email is one of those services that every researcher uses, and we
  should think much more about how we can create innovative services
  around email rather than only considerung new tools and services that
  are still used only by early adopters. AJ Cann had coordinated a
  workshop around email at SpotOn London that he called
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nature.com/spoton/event/spoton-london-2013-the-dark-art-of-dark-social-email-the-antisocial-medium-which-will-not-die-workshop/">the
  dark art of dark social: email, the antisocial medium that will not
  die</ext-link>. I am still puzzled why most researchers prefer to
  receive tables of content by email rather than as a RSS feed, but we
  shouldn’t confuse what we get excited about as software developers and
  early adopters of online tools with what the mainstream scientist
  would be likely to use.</p>
  <p>Another good example is
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://royalsociety.org/policy/projects/science-public-enterprise/report/">data
  sharing</ext-link>, a topic that was discussed in at least three
  SpotOn sessions. Even though most attendees at SpotOn London agreed
  that sharing of research data is important, it is obvious that this is
  currently not common practice in most scientific disciplines. Funders
  have created data sharing policies (e.g.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nsf.gov/bfa/dias/policy/dmp.jsp">NSF</ext-link>
  or the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wellcome.ac.uk/About-us/Policy/Spotlight-issues/Data-sharing/">Wellcome
  Trust</ext-link>), as
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0067111">have
  publishers</ext-link>, and many organizations are thinking about
  incentives for data sharing, including data journals such as
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nature.com/scientificdata/">Scientific
  Data</ext-link> that will launch in 2014 and was presented by Ruth
  Wilson in the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nature.com/spoton/event/spoton-london-2013-how-can-we-encourage-data-sharing-discussion/">motivations
  for data sharing</ext-link> session. Even though incentives can help
  promote changes, I am pessimistic that something as central to the
  conduct of science as data sharing can be changed without more
  scientists being intrinsically motivated to do so. This is a much
  slower process that should start as early as possible during training,
  as pointed out by Kaitlin Thaney in the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nature.com/spoton/event/spoton-london-2013-how-can-we-encourage-data-sharing-discussion/">#solo13carrot</ext-link>
  session.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="reason-3">
  <title>Reason #3</title>
  <p>In terms of the technology that is holding us back, I increasingly
  think that publisher manuscript submission systems may be the single
  most important place that is slowing down innovation. I participated
  in the first
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://sites.google.com/site/beyondthepdf/">Beyond
  the PDF</ext-link> workshop in 2011, and I think now that
  <bold><bold>Beyond the MTS (or manuscript tracking
  system)</bold></bold> might have been a better motto than
  <bold><bold>Beyond the PDF</bold></bold>, as many of the problems we
  discussed relate to typical editorial workflows we use today. These
  systems need to implement many of the ideas discussed at SpotOn London
  and other places, from opening up peer review
  (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nature.com/spoton/event/spoton-london-2013-how-should-peer-review-evolve/">#solo13peer</ext-link>)
  to making it easier to integrate research data into manuscripts
  (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nature.com/spoton/event/spoton-london-2013-how-should-peer-review-evolve/">#solo13carrot</ext-link>)
  and to ideas of how the scientific record should like in the digital
  age
  (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nature.com/spoton/event/spoton-london-2013-what-should-the-scientific-record-look-like-in-the-digital-age-discussion/">#solo13digital</ext-link>).
  In the latter panel we discussed both new authoring tools such as
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.writelatex.com/">WriteLaTeX</ext-link>,
  and new ideas of what a research object should look like and how the
  different parts are linked to each other. A major theme here was
  reproducibility highlighted both by Carol Goble (also see her
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.slideshare.net/carolegoble/ismb2013-keynotecleangoble">ISMB/ECCB
  2013 Keynote</ext-link>) and Peter Kraker (see also his
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://science.okfn.org/2013/10/18/its-not-only-peer-reviewed-its-reproducible/">Open
  Knowledge Foundation blog post</ext-link>).</p>
  <p>The problem with today’s manuscript submission systems is that they
  have grown so big and complex that any change is slow and cumbersome,
  rather than iterative and part of an ongoing dialogue. I don’t want to
  blame any single vendor of these systems, but rather suggest that we
  carefully re-evaluate the workflow from the manuscript written by one
  or more authors to the accepted manuscript. My personal interest is
  mainly in authoring tools, and I have recently written about and
  experimented with
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://localhost:4000/tags.html#markdown-ref">Markdown</ext-link>.
  This process of re-evaluating manuscript tracking systems is not
  simply about technology, but is rather about how we approach this
  problem as author, publisher, tool vendor and as a community.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
