<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>What a publication timeline can tell you</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2013-08-06">
<day>6</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Now that I can
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://blog.martinfenner.org/2013/08/04/automatically-list-all-your-publications-in-your-blog/">automatically
import my publications from my ORCID profile and display them</ext-link>
in this blog, I also want to visualize them. I have started with
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/mfenner/blog/blob/master/_includes/by_year.js">d3.js
code</ext-link> that displays the number of publications per year -
using the list of my publications in Citeproc JSON format. The chart is
displayed on my
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://blog.martinfenner.org/about.html">About
page</ext-link>, but I have also embedded the Javascript here:</p>
<p>I am a big fan of data visualizations because they can highlight
something that you would otherwise miss. In this case I was really
surprised to see how well my different academic jobs over the years
(1991-1993, 1994-1998, 1998-2000, 2000-2005, 2005-2012) are reflected in
my publication pattern. You clearly see the gaps between the jobs,
indicating that I not only switched jobs, but also changed the research
focus every time. The publications are listed chronologically on the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://blog.martinfenner.org/about.html">About
page</ext-link> page and you can look at the papers I wrote since my
first publication in 1993. My publication pattern seems to indicate that
I was never really on track for a typical academic career, so it should
not be a surprise that I left academia in 2012.</p>
<p>There are at least two other visualizations I want to do:
publications by type (journal article, book chapter, dataset, etc.), and
author position with number of co-authors. You can reuse the Javascript
code with small modifications (CSS and the JSON query) even if you are
not running a Jekyll blog.</p>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
