<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>What science is worth shouting about?</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2009-01-10">
<day>10</day>
<month>1</month>
<year>2009</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>A few weeks ago I wrote about the different ways results of a
clinical trial can be reported
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003033024/http://network.nature.com/people/mfenner/blog/2008/11/23/what-are-the-right-numbers-for-jupiter">What
are the right numbers for JUPITER</ext-link>). Inspired by blog posts by
<italic><italic>Eva Amsen</italic></italic>
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003033024/http://network.nature.com/people/eva/blog/2008/12/29/failure">Failure</ext-link>)
and <italic><italic>Sally Church</italic></italic>
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003033024/http://www.pharmastrategyblog.com/2009/01/over-hyped-cancer-drugs-or-sensational-journalism.html">Over
hyped cancer drugs or sensational journalism?</ext-link>), I thought
more about what makes scientific findings worth talking about outside of
your immediate research community. I will look at cancer research, and
it is obvious that some research findings are more exciting than others.
But it less obvious that it is as important who is communicating the
research and what is the intended audience. This is especially true for
translational research
<sup><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003033024/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2009/01/10/what_science_is_worth_shouting_about/#fn1"></ext-link></sup>
(Translational Research 2008), where research findings can change the
way we treat patients and drug companies (and others) can potentially
earn a lot of money.</p>
<sec id="the-academic-researcher">
  <title>The academic researcher</title>
  <p>Academic researchers involved in basic or clinical cancer research
  are interested in publications and grant money. As Eva
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003033024/http://network.nature.com/people/eva/blog/2008/12/29/failure">said</ext-link>:
  the unit of success is the publication record. Basic cancer research
  can be very exciting and touches many related fields from signal
  transduction to epigenetics. But what confuses me is when basic
  research findings are related to the treatment of human cancer, which
  is a completely different story. Cell lines are not living organisms,
  mice are not men and very few basic research findings make it into a
  clinical trial.
  Unfortunately less than one in five studies in cancer (they all have
  to be registered with
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003033024/http://www.clinicaltrials.gov/">clinicaltrials.gov</ext-link>
  since 2005) have been published in peer-reviewed journals (Ramsey
  2008). Negative results will usually not be published, and this
  so-called publication bias creates many problems. Just imagine 5
  clinical trials with a new drug where one trial will show an advantage
  for the new treatment. This trial will be published in a nice journal,
  probably one negative trial will be published in a small journal and
  the remaining 3 trials will remain unpublished. Just looking at the
  published literature will of course give the wrong impression, but
  these are the only data that are available to most people.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="the-drug-company">
  <title>The drug company</title>
  <p>A drug company is interested in marketing approval of a drug. This
  approval is obtained from the <italic><italic>Food and Drug
  Administration</italic></italic> (FDA) in the United States and from
  the <italic><italic>European Medicines Agency</italic></italic> EMEA
  for most of Europe. Approval of a cancer drug usually requires one or
  more large randomized trials (so-called phase III trials) that shows
  that the drug improves survival. And up to 50% of these phase III
  trials fail to show the desired effect, even when earlier (so-called
  phase II) trials were positive
  <sup><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003033024/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2009/01/10/what_science_is_worth_shouting_about/#fn3"></ext-link></sup>
  (Chan 2008).
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003033024/http://www.gpc-biotech.com/en/anticancer_programs/satraplatin/clinical_trials/index.html">Satraplatin</ext-link>
  is one recent example of a drug that showed promising results in the
  treatment of prostate cancer but failed to prolong survival – and
  therefore was not approved by the FDA.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="the-insurance-company-or-whoever-pays-for-medical-care-">
  <title>The insurance company (or whoever pays for medical
  care)</title>
  <p>The drug erlotinib was approved for the treatment of pancreatic
  cancer, but the median benefit in overall survival was less than 2
  weeks
  <sup><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003033024/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2009/01/10/what_science_is_worth_shouting_about/#fn4"></ext-link></sup>
  (Moore 2007). Insurance companies are interested in treatments that
  are not only effective, but also cost-effective. For cancer treatments
  one can calculate the cost per quality-adjusted life year (QALY).
  Adding erlotinib to gemcitabine in the treatment of pancreatic cancer
  would cost about $410,000 per year of life saved
  <sup><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003033024/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2009/01/10/what_science_is_worth_shouting_about/#fn5"></ext-link></sup>
  (Miksad 2007). Costs over $100.000 per year of life saved are
  considered high and the high cost is the reason that the British
  National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE) decided
  to not recommend
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003033024/http://www.medscape.com/viewarticle/579628">4
  new drugs for the treatment of renal cancer</ext-link> in August 2008.
  NICE doesn't question the effectiveness of these drugs, but wants
  these drugs to become cheaper.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="the-media">
  <title>The media</title>
  <p>Cancer research sells. Cancer is very common and many people can
  tell sad stories of friends or relatives that died because of cancer.
  And we want to hear encouraging stories. But the media often confuse
  promising findings in basic research or early clinical trials with a
  new cure for cancer. One of the more famous examples is the statement
  <italic><italic>Judah is going to cure cancer in two
  years</italic></italic> by James Watson in a 1998 <italic><italic>New
  York Times</italic></italic> story on angiogenesis research
  (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003033024/http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E6D6113EF930A35756C0A96E958260&amp;sec=&amp;spon=&amp;partner=permalink&amp;exprod=permalink">A
  Cautious Awe Greets Drugs That Eradicate Tumors in Mice</ext-link>).
  Another example is this recent article (cited by <italic><italic>Sally
  Church</italic></italic> in her blog post mentioned above) in the
  <italic><italic>Times</italic></italic>
  (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003033024/http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/life_and_style/men/article4375429.ece">Cancer
  drug could save the lives of 10,000 a year</ext-link>).
  <italic><italic>Ben Goldacre</italic></italic> has written more than
  one critical blog post about how traditional media report cancer
  research (e.g.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003033024/http://www.guardian.co.uk/commentisfree/2008/jul/19/cancer.foodtech">Still
  no cure for cancer hysteria</ext-link>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="the-patient">
  <title>The patient</title>
  <p>A patient with cancer needs a drug treatment that either cures his
  cancer or prolongs survival. The new treatment should either be better
  or have fewer side effects than the current standard of care. But many
  cancer patients can't wait until a new cancer drug is approved and
  available for prescription. So whenever possible, patients should
  participate in a clinical trial. Clinical trial participation by adult
  cancer patients is unfortunately low (less than 5% compared to more
  than 50% for children with cancer
  <sup><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003033024/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2009/01/10/what_science_is_worth_shouting_about/#fn6"></ext-link></sup>
  (Sateren 2002)), but this is the best way to receive a promising new
  drug as early as possible (and to stop receiving it when the drug has
  been shown to be ineffective or toxic).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="conclusions">
  <title>Conclusions</title>
  <p>We should be careful how we report research findings outside of
  specialist journals or research meetings, especially if these findings
  could have important consequences outside our immediate research
  community. And as a critical reader we should assume that most
  published research findings are false
  <sup><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151003033024/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2009/01/10/what_science_is_worth_shouting_about/#fn7"></ext-link></sup>
  (Ioannidis 2005).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="references">
  <title>References</title>
  <p>Translational Research: Getting the message across. (2008). Nature,
  453(7197), 839–839.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/453839a">https://doi.org/10.1038/453839a</ext-link></p>
  <p>Ramsey, S., &amp; Scoggins, J. (2008). Commentary: Practicing on
  the Tip of an Information Iceberg? Evidence of Underpublication of
  Registered Clinical Trials in Oncology. The Oncologist, 13(9),
  925–929.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1634/theoncologist.2008-0133">https://doi.org/10.1634/theoncologist.2008-0133</ext-link></p>
  <p>Chan, J. K., Ueda, S. M., Sugiyama, V. E., Stave, C. D., Shin, J.
  Y., Monk, B. J., … Kapp, D. S. (2008). Analysis of Phase II Studies on
  Targeted Agents and Subsequent Phase III Trials: What Are the
  Predictors for Success? Journal of Clinical Oncology, 26(9),
  1511–1518.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1200/jco.2007.14.8874">https://doi.org/10.1200/jco.2007.14.8874</ext-link></p>
  <p>Moore, M. J., Goldstein, D., Hamm, J., Figer, A., Hecht, J. R.,
  Gallinger, S., … Parulekar, W. (2007). Erlotinib Plus Gemcitabine
  Compared With Gemcitabine Alone in Patients With Advanced Pancreatic
  Cancer: A Phase III Trial of the National Cancer Institute of Canada
  Clinical Trials Group. Journal of Clinical Oncology, 25(15),
  1960–1966.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1200/jco.2006.07.9525">https://doi.org/10.1200/jco.2006.07.9525</ext-link></p>
  <p>Miksad, R. A., Schnipper, L., &amp; Goldstein, M. (2007). Does a
  Statistically Significant Survival Benefit of Erlotinib Plus
  Gemcitabine for Advanced Pancreatic Cancer Translate Into Clinical
  Significance and Value? Journal of Clinical Oncology, 25(28),
  4506–4507. https://doi.org/10.1200/jco.2007.13.0401</p>
  <p>Sateren, W. B., Trimble, E. L., Abrams, J., Brawley, O., Breen, N.,
  Ford, L., … Christian, M. C. (2002). How Sociodemographics, Presence
  of Oncology Specialists, and Hospital Cancer Programs Affect Accrual
  to Cancer Treatment Trials. Journal of Clinical Oncology, 20(8),
  2109–2117.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1200/jco.2002.08.056">https://doi.org/10.1200/jco.2002.08.056</ext-link></p>
  <p>Ioannidis, J. P. A. (2005). Why Most Published Research Findings
  Are False. PLoS Medicine, 2(8), e124.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pmed.0020124">https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pmed.0020124</ext-link></p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
