<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>What is a DOI?</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2014-08-06">
<day>6</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2014</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>This Sunday
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://twitter.com/ianmulvany">Ian
Mulvany</ext-link> and I will do a presentation on
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://wikimania2014.wikimedia.org/wiki/Submissions/Open_Scholarship_Tools_-_a_whirlwind_tour.">Open
Scholarship Tools</ext-link> at <italic>Wikimania 2014</italic> in
London. From the abstract:</p>
<p specific-use="wrapper">
  <disp-quote>
    <p>This presentation will give a broad overview of tools and
    standards that are helping with Open Scholarship today.</p>
  </disp-quote>
</p>
<p>One of the four broad topics we have picked are <italic>digital
object identifiers (DOI)s</italic>. We want to introduce them to people
new to them, and we want to show some tricks and cool things to people
who already now them. Along the way we will also try to debunk some
myths about DOIs.</p>
<sec id="what-a-doi-looks-like">
  <title>What a DOI looks like</title>
  <p>DOIs - or better DOI names - start with a prefix in the format
  <monospace>10.x</monospace> where x is 4-5 digits. The suffix is
  determined by the organization registering the DOI, and there is no
  consistent pattern across organizations. The DOI name is typically
  expressed as a URL (see below). An example DOI would look like:
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.5555/12345678">http://dx.doi.org/10.5555/12345678</ext-link>.
  Something in the format <bold><bold>10/hvx</bold></bold> or
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://doi.org/hvx">http://doi.org/hvx</ext-link>
  is a
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://shortdoi.org/">shortDOI</ext-link>,
  and <bold><bold>1721.1/26698</bold></bold> or
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hdl.handle.net/1721.1/26698">http://hdl.handle.net/1721.1/26698</ext-link>
  is a handle. BTW, all DOIs names are also handles, so
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hdl.handle.net/10/hvx">http://hdl.handle.net/10/hvx</ext-link>
  for the shortDOI example above will resolve correctly.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="dois-are-persistent-identifiers">
  <title>DOIs are persistent identifiers</title>
  <p>Links to resources can change, particularly over long periods of
  time. Persistent identifiers are needed so that readers can still find
  the content we reference in a scholarly work (or anything else where
  persistent linking is important) 10 or 50 years later. There are many
  kinds of persistent identifiers, one of the key concepts - and a major
  difference to URLs - is to separate the identifier for the resource
  from its location. Persistent identifiers require technical
  infrastructure to resolve identifiers (DOIs use the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.handle.net/">Handle
  System</ext-link>) and to allow long-term archiving of resources. DOI
  registration agencies such as DataCite or CrossRef are required to
  provide that persistence. Other persistent identifier schemes besides
  DOIs include
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PURL">persistent
  uniform resource locators (PURLs)</ext-link> and
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archival_Resource_Key">Archival
  Resource Keys (ARKs)</ext-link>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="dois-have-attached-metadata">
  <title>DOIs have attached metadata</title>
  <p>All DOIs have metadata attached to them. The metadata are supplied
  by the resource provider, e.g. publisher, and exposed in services run
  by registration agencies, for example metadata search and content
  negotiation (see below). There is a minimal set of required metadata
  for every DOI, but beyond that, different registration agencies will
  use different metadata schemata, and most metadata are optional.
  Metadata are important to build centralized discovery services, making
  it easier to describe a resource, e.g. journal article citing another
  article. Some of the more recent additions to metadata schemata
  include persistent identifiers for people
  (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://orcid.org/">ORCID</ext-link>)
  and funding agencies
  (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.crossref.org/fundref/">FundRef</ext-link>),
  and license information. The following API call will retrieve all
  publications registered with CrossRef that use a
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/deed.en_US">Creative
  Commons Attribution license</ext-link> (and where this information has
  been provided by the publisher):</p>
  <preformat>http://api.crossref.org/funders/10.13039/100000001/works?filter=license.url:http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/deed.en_US</preformat>
</sec>
<sec id="dois-support-link-tracking">
  <title>DOIs support link tracking</title>
  <p>Links to other resources are an important part of the metadata, and
  describing all citations between a large number scholarly documents is
  a task that can only really be accomplished by a central resource. To
  solve this very problem DOIs were invented and the CrossRef
  organization started around 15 years ago.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="not-every-doi-is-the-same">
  <title>Not every DOI is the same</title>
  <p>The DOI system
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.doi.org/doi_handbook/1_Introduction.html">originated
  from an initiative by scholarly publishers</ext-link> (first announced
  at the Frankfurt Book Fair in 1997), with citation linking of journal
  articles its first application. This citation linking system is
  managed by
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.crossref.org/">CrossRef</ext-link>,
  a non-profit member organization of scholarly publishers, and
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://search.crossref.org/help/status">more
  than half</ext-link> of the about
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.doi.org/faq.html">100
  million DOIs</ext-link> that have been assigned to date are managed by
  them.</p>
  <p>But many DOIs are assigned by one of the other 8
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.doi.org/RA_Coverage.html">registration
  agencies</ext-link>. You probably know
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.datacite.org/">DataCite</ext-link>,
  but did you know that the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://publications.europa.eu/index_en.htm">Publications
  Office of the European Union (OP)</ext-link> and the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.eidr.org/">Entertainment
  Identifier Registry (EIDR)</ext-link> also assign DOIs? The
  distinction is important, because some of the functionality is a
  service of the registration agency - metadata search for example is
  offered by CrossRef
  (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://search.crossref.org/">http://search.crossref.org</ext-link>)
  and DataCite
  (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://search.datacite.org/">http://search.datacite.org</ext-link>),
  but you can’t search for a DataCite DOI in the CrossRef metadata
  search. There is an API to find out the registration agency behind a
  DOI so that you know what services to expect:</p>
  <preformat>http://api.crossref.org/works/10.6084/m9.figshare.821213/agency

{
  &quot;status&quot;: &quot;ok&quot;,
  &quot;message-type&quot;: &quot;work-agency&quot;,
  &quot;message-version&quot;: &quot;1.0.0&quot;,
  &quot;message&quot;: {
    &quot;DOI&quot;: &quot;10.6084/m9.figshare.821213&quot;,
    &quot;agency&quot;: {
      &quot;id&quot;: &quot;datacite&quot;,
      &quot;label&quot;: &quot;DataCite&quot;
    }
  }
}</preformat>
</sec>
<sec id="dois-are-urls">
  <title>DOIs are URLs</title>
  <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.doi.org/faq.html">DOI
  names may be expressed as URLs (URIs) through a HTTP proxy
  server</ext-link> - e.g.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.5555/12345679">http://dx.doi.org/10.5555/12345679</ext-link>,
  and this is how DOIs are typically resolved. For this reason the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.crossref.org/02publishers/doi_display_guidelines.htm">CrossRef
  DOI Display Guidelines</ext-link> recommend that <italic>CrossRef DOIs
  should always be displayed as permanent URLs in the online
  environment</italic>. Because DOIs can be expressed as URLs, they also
  have their features:</p>
  <sec id="special-characters">
    <title>Special characters</title>
    <p>Because DOIs can be expressed as URLs, DOIs
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.crossref.org/02publishers/15doi_guidelines.html">should
    only include characters allowed in URLs</ext-link>, something that
    wasn’t always true in the past and can cause problems, e.g. when
    using SICIs
    (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Serial_Item_and_Contribution_Identifier">Serial
    Item and Contribution Identifier</ext-link>), an extension of the
    ISSN for journals:</p>
    <preformat>10.4567/0361-9230(1997)42:&lt;OaEoSR&gt;2.0.TX;2-B</preformat>
  </sec>
  <sec id="content-negotiation">
    <title>Content negotiation</title>
    <p>The DOI resolver at <italic>doi.org</italic> (or
    <italic>dx.doi.org</italic>) normally resolves to the resource
    location, e.g. a landing page at a publisher website. Requests that
    are not for content type <monospace>text/html</monospace> are
    redirected to the registration agency metadata service (currently
    for CrossRef, DataCite and mEDRA DOIs). Using
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.crosscite.org/cn/">content
    negotiation</ext-link>, we can ask the metadata service to send us
    the metadata in a format we specify (e.g. Citeproc JSON, bibtex or
    even a formatted citation in one of thousands of citation styles)
    instead of getting redirected to the resource. This is a great way
    to collect bibliographic information, e.g. to format citations for a
    manuscript. In theory we could also use content negotiation to get a
    particular representation of a resource, e.g.
    <monospace>application/pdf</monospace> for a PDF of a paper or
    <monospace>text/csv</monospace> for a dataset in CSV format. This is
    not widely support and I don’t know the details of the
    implementation in the DOI resolver, but you can try this (content
    negotation is easier with the command line than with a browser):</p>
    <preformat>curl -LH &quot;Accept: application/pdf&quot; http://dx.doi.org/10.7717/peerj.500 &gt;peerj.500.pdf</preformat>
    <p>This will save the PDF of the 500th PeerJ paper published last
    week.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="fragment-identifiers">
    <title>Fragment identifiers</title>
    <p>As discussed in
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://blog.martinfenner.org/2014/08/02/fragment-identifiers-and-dois/">my
    last blog post</ext-link>, we can use frament identifiers to
    subsections of a document with DOIs, e.g.
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0103437#s2">http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0103437#s2</ext-link>
    or
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://doi.org/10.5446/12780#t=00:20,00:27">http://doi.org/10.5446/12780#t=00:20,00:27</ext-link>,
    just as we can with every other URL. This is a nice way to directly
    link to a specific document section, e.g. when discussing a paper on
    Twitter. Fragment identifiers are implemented by the client
    (typically web browser) and depend on the document type, but for
    DOIs that resolve to fulltext HTML documents they can add
    granularity to the DOI without much effort.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="queries">
    <title>Queries</title>
    <p>URLs obviously support queries, but that is a feature I haven’t
    yet seen with DOIs. Queries would allow interesting features, partly
    overlapping with what is possible with fragment identifiers and
    content negotiation, e.g.
    <monospace>http://dx.doi.org/10.7717/peerj.500?format=pdf</monospace>.
    II hope to find out more until Sunday.</p>
  </sec>
</sec>
<sec id="outlook">
  <title>Outlook</title>
  <p>My biggest wish? Make DOIs more machine-readable. They are
  primarily intended for human users, enabling them to find the content
  associated with a DOI. But they sometimes don’t work as well as they
  could with automated tools, one example are the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://blog.martinfenner.org/2013/10/13/broken-dois/">challenges
  automatically resolving a DOI</ext-link> that I described in a blog
  post last year. Thinking about DOIs as URLs - and using them this way
  - is the right direction.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
