<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Why there is no iTunes for science papers</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2015-02-23">
<day>23</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2015</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>The iTunes Store was opened by Apple in 2003 to sell digital music
and other digital assets. Since 2009 music purchased in the iTunes store
is free of Digital Rights Management (DRM). Apple became the largest
music vendor worldwide in 2010, and by 2013 had sold 25 billion
songs.</p>
<p>Scholarly articles are distributed almost exclusively in digital
form. While there is an increasing number of journal articles freely
available via green or gold open access, the majority of them still can
only be read if the reader works at an institution with a subscription
to the journal. Many journals also allow the reader to buy a single
article of interest, for prices between $10 and more than $30:</p>
<fig>
  <caption><p>For an article in Nature</p></caption>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://martinfenner.ghost.io/content/images/2021/01/pay_per_view_nature-1.png" xlink:title="" />
</fig>
<fig>
  <caption><p>For an article in Lancet</p></caption>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://martinfenner.ghost.io/content/images/2021/01/pay_per_view_lancet-1.png" xlink:title="" />
</fig>
<p>There is also a document delivery service provided by libraries, but
that option varies considerably by country and in Germany for example
means a scanned article as printout rather than the original PDF because
of a change in German copyright law a few years ago. There are also the
services
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.deepdyve.com/">DeepDyve</ext-link>
and
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.readcube.com/">ReadCube</ext-link>,
but again you don’t get the PDF (or only for prices similar to those
quoted above), but rather limited access for reading and printing.</p>
<p>In summary, affordable access to scholarly content by subscription
publishers is in a dire state: you either have to work at an academic
institution subscribing to the desired journal, get only a crippled
version of the article (online viewing only), or pay up to $30 for a
single article, which clearly doesn’t scale beyond very occasional
use.</p>
<p>With this background it is obvious that several people have discussed
the iTunes Store-like model to sell scholarly articles:</p>
<list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
    <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://crosstech.crossref.org/2009/09/prc_report_and_ipub_revisited.html">PRC
    Report and “iPub” revisited</ext-link></p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.popsci.com/science/article/2009-10/deepdyve-launches-itunes-science-papers">DeepDyve
    launches iTunes Store-like service for science papers</ext-link></p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://scienceblogs.com/digitalbio/2012/01/10/could-an-itunes-like-model-wor/">Could
    an iTunes-like model work with scientific publishing?</ext-link></p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.bostonglobe.com/business/2012/10/07/start-readcube-program-uses-itunes-payment-model-for-access-scientific-articles/1UopCX1qfEE3uO2UEzuM7L/story.html">A
    plan to open up science journals</ext-link></p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.newyorker.com/tech/elements/when-the-rebel-alliance-sells-out">When
    the Rebel Alliance Sells Out</ext-link></p>
  </list-item>
</list>
<p>The best already existing platforms to build such as service are
reference managers, as most of them have learned now to manage PDF
files, and have an online component. ReadCube is offering a pay-per-view
option already, Papers, Mendeley, Endnote or others could get into this
business.</p>
<p>One of the big advantages of payments for single articles is
transparency, as institutions and users only pay for what they actually
use. Price transparency is one of the big problems with the <italic>big
deal</italic> contracts that academic institutions have with publishers
- read
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1403006111">this
article</ext-link> for more info.</p>
<p>But rather than becoming the predominant way to pay for digital
music, services such as DeepDyve and ReadCube are only playing a
marginal role. Why is that so?</p>
<list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
    <p>whereas digital music is paid for by the consumer, there is
    usually a middleman in the form of the library for scholarly
    articles, which makes the payment process more complex.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>subscription publishers have focused all their efforts on selling
    big deals with increasing numbers of journals to libraries. Prices
    of $30 per article are clearly intended to discourage payment for
    single articles (which could jeopardize journal bundles) rather than
    offering an earnest payment option.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
    <p>Apple was in a strong negotiation position with record labels
    when starting the iTunes store (the extremely popular iPod, record
    labels scared of file-sharing platforms such as Napster). No
    organization is in a similar position with scientific publishers,
    and services such as ReadCube or Mendeley are handicapped because
    they are associated with a particular publisher</p>
  </list-item>
</list>
<p>Unless several large publishers and/or a smart third-party with
enough muscle start an initiative in this space, e.g. by bringing the
pay-per-view prices to a reasonable level (e.g. $4.99), we will never
see an iTunes Store-like service for scholarly articles, and this
currently looks like the most likely outcome. We may have reached the
point where it is too late, as most publishers seem to already work
towards another payment model: gold open access where the authors pay
the article costs.</p>
<p><italic>Update 3/2/15: added link to 2009 CrossTech blog
post.</italic></p>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
