<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Why local hubs in Nature Network are
important</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2008-05-24">
<day>24</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2008</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Earlier this week Matt Brown announced important changes to the
Nature Network software:
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611102855/http://network.nature.com/london/news/blog/matt/2008/05/21/the-first-step-towards-new-local-hubs">The
first step towards new local hubs</ext-link>. Most importantly, it is
now possible to set your location and hub. The hub can be the same as
the location, or a city or region nearby (as in my case
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611102855/http://network.nature.com/hubs/berlin">Berlin</ext-link>).
Later this year, Nature Network will add new hubs to the existing London
and Boston. Hubs that are now picked by many people are more likely to
become full-fledged hubs. Some of the early popular hubs include
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611102855/http://network.nature.com/groups/nyc/notice/2008/05/20/join-the-new-york-hub">New
York</ext-link>,
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611102855/http://network.nature.com/forums/scibarcamp/1597">Toronto</ext-link>
and
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611102855/http://network.nature.com/forums/berlin/1596">Berlin</ext-link>
(there are certainly more, but there is no way for me to see them
listed).</p>
<p>As we know from the London and Boston hubs, local hubs have local
events listings, local meetups, local news and jobs information. We had
several
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611102855/http://network.nature.com/blogs/user/maxine/2008/05/08/web-2-0-and-biology-8-may-2008">discussions</ext-link>
here on Nature Network of what Web 2.0 can bring to scientists and that
only those tools and increase the productivity or add something new will
become popular. Local event and job listings for scientists are two
services that I see as extremely valuable, basically I don't see any way
other than as Web services to do them properly.</p>
<p>Location information is becoming increasingly popular in other parts
of the Web and the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611102855/http://en.oreilly.com/where2008/public/content/home">Where
2.0</ext-link> conference on the topic just finished earlier this month.
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611102855/http://www.researcherid.com/">ResearcherID</ext-link>,
a tool to assign a unique identifier to every researcher, is one example
where scientific information is mapped to locations. You can see a map
of my paper coauthors
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611102855/http://labs.researcherid.com/mashlets/rid/mashletsServer.jsp?rid=A-7225-2008&amp;mid=CollaborationNetwork&amp;cat=Map">here</ext-link>.</p>
<p>Scientific research and communication is not bound to locations, but
local networks are at least as important as virtual networks. We of
course all do this already for many years, but we are just starting to
figure out how social networks such as Nature Network can enhance our
physical networks and connect them to the larger virtual network.
Philipp Selenko has a clear vision, he sees this as a great opportunity
for PhD students to do the same kind of networking that is usually
restricted to seasoned faculty (and often happens behind closed doors).
Read
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611102855/http://network.nature.com/forums/berlin/1332">his
post</ext-link> on the Berlin forum for more details.</p>
<p>And please join the Berlin hub if you work in that region.</p>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
