<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Why can’t I reuse these tables and
figures?</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2010-09-30">
<day>30</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2010</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Tables and figures contain the data of a scientific paper in
condensed (and often visually appealing) form. This is why they are
among the first thing we look at, and why they are often reused when we
discuss the paper in a presentation or blog post.</p>
<fig>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170913082049im_/http://www.plospathogens.org/images/home/ppat.v06.i08.jpg" xlink:title="PLoS Pathogens" />
</fig>
<p><italic>From
doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170913082049/http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.ppat.1001042">10.1371/journal.ppat.1001042</ext-link>.
Image credit: Thomas J. Hannan, Washington University.</italic></p>
<p>Electronic publication has dramatically simplified the reuse of
tables and figures, and therefore reuse has become very common – you
probably find reused material in most presentations given in academic
institutions or at conferences.</p>
<p>Most authors will probably be happy that their results are
disseminated, and reuse is likely to lead to more people reading the
full paper and citing the work.</p>
<fig>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170913082049im_/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/files/2010/09/bmccancer-e1285879074865.jpg" xlink:title="bmccancer" />
</fig>
<p><italic>From
doi:</italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170913082049/http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1471-2407-10-286"><italic>10.1186/1471-2407-10-286</italic></ext-link><italic>.</italic></p>
<p>But this reuse has two problems. The first problem is copyright. Many
journals own the copyright of the papers they publish and don’t allow
reuse without prior permission. Unfortunately copyright is a complicated
issue, and also differs between countries. Most researchers assume
“<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170913082049/http://www.copyright.gov/fls/fl102.html">Fair
use</ext-link>” when they reuse material, but this might not apply to
all situations, e.g. presentations at conferences. And many researchers
don’t understand that they have often given away the copyright to their
own works, so that they can’t show a figure from one of their papers
without permission.</p>
<p>Many publishers have automated the process of obtaining permissions
for copyrighted work, e.g. using the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170913082049/http://www.copyright.com/viewPage.do?pageCode=pu4-n">Rightslink</ext-link>
system of the Copyright Clearance Center. But it still requires a
considerable investment in time (and often money) to obtain all
permissions, especially since these are usually one-time permissions
only. This combination of unawareness of the details of copyright law
and the required extra work means that many researchers probably don’t
obtain permissions prior to reuse.</p>
<p>The solution to the copyright problems is obviously to use material
with a
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170913082049/http://creativecommons.org/">Creative
Commons</ext-link> license whenever possible, as I have done in this
blog post. And most Open Access papers are published under this license,
so there is plenty of material to choose from.</p>
<p>But there is also a second problem with reusing tables and figures.
They were designed to be part of a paper and often look terrible in a
presentation, particularly tables.</p>
<fig>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170913082049im_/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/files/2010/09/plosone-e1285879245843.png" xlink:title="plosone" />
</fig>
<p><italic>From
doi:</italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170913082049/http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0006022"><italic>10.1371/journal.pone.0006022</italic></ext-link>.</p>
<p>The solution to this problem is to provide the data behind the table
or figure, so that the information can be displayed in a way that makes
sense in a presentation. Here we usually have to reduce the amount of
information, but it could also mean that we remix the content with other
sources. The Creative Commons licenses discussed above are
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170913082049/http://pantonprinciples.org/">not
appropriate</ext-link> for data. Whenever possible, scientific data
should be placed in the public domain.</p>
<p>It is important to distinguish the publication of table and figure
data from the publication of the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170913082049/http://blogs.openaccesscentral.com/blogs/bmcblog/entry/bmc_research_notes_wants_your">whole
research dataset</ext-link>. The open questions with the latter (e.g.
standard data formats, appropriate repositories, archiving) don’t apply
to the former. This means that publishers could start providing these
data immediately. I’m confident that they would see an increase in paper
downloads and citations. But more importantly I hope this would lead to
better presentations in seminars and at conferences.</p>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
