<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Why do we go to conferences?</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2009-06-07">
<day>7</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2009</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>I just returned from the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002134927/http://www.asco.org/ascov2/Meetings/ASCO+Annual+Meeting">American
Society of Clinical Oncology</ext-link> (ASCO) meeting in Orlando, with
approximately 30.000 participants one of the largest oncology
conferences. Like other conferences of this size, the experience can be
overwhelming, but thankfully the organizers are getting better every
year in using technology that helps in finding the most interesting
sessions. Most sessions are made available as video podcasts or
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002134927/http://www.asco.org/ASCOv2/MultiMedia/Virtual+Meeting">online
presentations</ext-link>. There is currently still a delay of 24 hours,
but I wouldn't be surprised to see the sessions streamed live as video
over the internet in coming years. This year's ASCO also had the first
official Twitter meet-up, although there still was relatively little
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002134927/http://twitter.com/asco">Twitter
activity</ext-link> compared to other conferences.</p>
<p>Last week
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002134927/http://www.scienceonlinelondon.org/">we
announced</ext-link> <italic><italic>Science Online
London</italic></italic>, the follow-up conference of last year's
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002134927/http://network.nature.com/groups/sciblog2008/forum/topics">Science
Blogging 2008: London</ext-link>, to take place August 22 at the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002134927/http://www.rigb.org/registrationControl?action=home">Royal
Institution</ext-link>. I am helping to organize the conference, and I'm
finding myself in the middle of discussions about session topics,
speakers and the right format to present and discuss science blogging,
wikis, and other science-related activities happening online.</p>
<fig>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002134927im_/http://www.mendeley.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2009/05/solologo.gif" xlink:title="" />
</fig>
<p>These two events started me thinking about the reasons I go to
conferences. After all, traveling to conferences is not only expensive,
but can also be exhausting, and too much airline travel is certainly not
good for the environment (places like
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002134927/http://www.dopplr.com/">Dopplr</ext-link>
can calculate your carbon profile). Here are a few points that I think
make a conference a good conference worth attending in person:</p>
<sec id="conferences-should-present-new-and-exciting-information-which-can-not-be-presented-differently">
  <title>Conferences should present new and exciting information which
  can not be presented differently</title>
  <p>Oral presentations at conferences are usually the first public
  presentation of interesting research findings before they appear as
  published paper a little (or much) later. What we don't want to see is
  the presentation of the same old data that we have already seen the
  year before. Good educational sessions and keynote lectures find
  informative or entertaining ways to present their information, and
  again should not be simply a repeat performance (unless the audience
  is completely different).</p>
  <p>Most conferences encourage the presentation of unpublished work,
  but speakers are often careful in doing so for a variety of reasons,
  e.g. fear of getting scooped, fear of problems with journal
  submissions or fear of problems with patentable work. This fear can
  make conference presentations rather boring, as presenters might hold
  back with the real exiting stuff until these results are at least
  accepted for publication.</p>
  <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002134927/http://meetings.cshl.edu/">Cold
  Spring Harbor Laboratory</ext-link> try to solve this problem by
  policies that essentially make their meetings non-public. During the
  last week we have seen an intensive discussion (e.g.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002134927/http://scienceblogs.com/geneticfuture/2009/06/on_the_challenges_of_conferenc.php">On
  the challenges of conference blogging</ext-link>) whether or not the
  sessions in a CSHL meeting can be communicated publicly by
  participating scientists via blogs or Twitter. I think that there is
  nothing wrong with small conferences being non-public, and that the
  same rules should apply to science bloggers as they do apply to
  journalists. But the conference organizers should clearly state their
  policies regarding blogging (including Twitter, FriendFeed and other
  microblogging tools).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="conferences-should-enable-as-much-active-participation-of-as-many-participants-as-possible">
  <title>Conferences should enable as much active participation of as
  many participants as possible</title>
  <p>If we just want to listen to a presentation, we could do that
  without going to a conference, thanks to video streaming,
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002134927/http://www.slideshare.net/">SlideShare</ext-link>
  and other ways of presenting online. Sometimes a paper is even
  published on the same the day as the plenary session, as happened
  recently with the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002134927/http://network.nature.com/people/mfenner/blog/2008/11/23/what-are-the-right-numbers-for-jupiter">JUPITER</ext-link>
  trial.</p>
  <p>Smaller sessions that leave enough room for discussions,
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002134927/http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unconference">unconferences</ext-link>
  and poster sessions are all good formats to encourage active
  participation. It should be a goal at least for smaller conferences
  that every attendee has had a chance for active participation in one
  way or another. But active participation in a session is much more
  focussed than disussions in coffee breaks between sessions or
  afterwards in the bar.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="conferences-should-facilitate-personal-networking">
  <title>Conferences should facilitate personal networking</title>
  <p>Meeting someone in person is very different from interacting online
  via email, Twitter or social network. For many people this is the real
  reason to go to a conference. Or as Henry Gee puts it (slightly out of
  context), “the most important part is to
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002134927/http://network.nature.com/people/U9556F6A5/blog/2007/08/06/someday-all-conferences-will-be-like-this">hang
  around in bars</ext-link>.” Smaller conferences (e.g. 100-150 people),
  enough time for coffee and lunch breaks between sessions, and social
  activities around conferences (from
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002134927/http://network.nature.com/groups/sciblog2008/forum/topics/1959">science
  tours</ext-link> to skiing) all facilitate networking.</p>
  <p>I'm looking forward to go to a very special conference in five
  weeks:
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002134927/http://www.nature.com/nature/meetings/scifoo/index.html">Science
  Foo Camp</ext-link>. And let's see whether we can put together an
  interesting <italic><italic>Science Online London</italic></italic>
  conference. Please suggest and discuss session topics and speakers in
  the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002134927/http://network.nature.com/groups/solondon/forum/topics">Nature
  Network Forum</ext-link>,
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002134927/http://friendfeed.com/solondon">FriendFeed
  group</ext-link> or via
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002134927/mailto:topics%40scienceonlinelondon.org">email</ext-link>
  until June 19. We are still looking for interesting session ideas,
  speaker suggestions and other suggestions to make this an exciting
  conference.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
