<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>WordPress for Reference Management</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2010-12-28">
<day>28</day>
<month>12</month>
<year>2010</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>One of the more complicated aspects of scientific writing is
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611082245/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/tag/reference-management/">reference
management</ext-link> – an important limitation of online collaborative
tools such as <italic><italic>Google Docs</italic></italic>. I have
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611082245/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2010/12/05/blogging-beyond-the-pdf/">argued
before</ext-link> that WordPress has the potential to become a great
scientific writing tool. Wordpress can’t do reference management out of
the box, and the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611082245/http://wordpress.org/extend/plugins/search.php?q=bibtex">available
plugins</ext-link> are somewhat limited. But WordPress is a good
platform to add reference management functions: it is not only extremely
popular (meaning a lot of people have expertise and many tools are
available), but also already knows a lot about links, and has a
wonderful plugin architecture.</p>
<sec id="reference-database">
  <title>Reference database</title>
  <p>The first question with reference management in WordPress is where
  to store the references. Should they not be stored at all and be
  directly imported from the source (journal website or bibliographic
  database such as PubMed)? This is what most of us are currently doing
  when writing blog posts, but this approach has obvious limitations on
  more ambitious writing projects. Or should references be inserted from
  an online reference manager such as CiteULike, Mendeley, Refworks or
  Endnote Web? This is how we use these reference managers with
  Microsoft Word and similar word processors.</p>
  <p>Instead I prefer a third approach: store the references in the
  built-in Links Manager in WordPress. References are nothing more than
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611082245/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2010/12/11/citations-are-links-so-where-is-the-problem/">specialized
  links</ext-link> after all. We loose functionality compared to
  reference manager databases, but we get some very interesting features
  for free, including
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611082245/http://wordpress.org/extend/plugins/broken-link-checker/">automatic
  checking of broken links</ext-link>,
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611082245/http://wordpress.org/extend/plugins/blogrollsync/">automatic
  link synchronization</ext-link> with other WordPress installations,
  and all the other cool things for links that people have come up with.
  And this makes it much easier for authors to collaborate if they use
  different reference managers, as all required references are stored in
  a common database.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="bibtex-importer">
  <title>BibTeX Importer</title>
  <p>There is currently no good solution to important references into
  the Links Manager, so I wrote a WordPress plugin to do just that. It
  took me two days, which says less about my skills, but more about the
  WordPress plugin architecture. Like all plugins hosted at
  WordPress.org, my
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611082245/http://wordpress.org/extend/plugins/bibtex-importer/">BibTeX
  Importer</ext-link> plugin can be installed directly from within your
  WordPress installation in less than 5 minutes.</p>
  <p>The plugin takes any BibTeX file (BibTeX is one of the more common
  file formats for references, all good reference managers can export
  into that format) and imports it into the WordPress Links Manager. The
  plugin can also import a BibTex file via URL (e.g.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611082245/http://www.citeulike.org/bibtex/user/mfenner">http://www.citeulike.org/bibtex/user/mfenner</ext-link>).</p>
  <fig>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611082245im_/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/files/2010/12/screenshot-2-500x198.jpg" xlink:title="BibTeX Importer" />
  </fig>
  <p>The plugin creates WordPress links where the link name is in the
  format <bold><bold>first author – year – title</bold></bold>. The
  original BibTeX entry is stored in the link notes. The plugin does
  some extra work, e.g. checks for duplicates before importing and picks
  the DOI if several URLs are available for the link. The plugin also
  checks the BibTex entry type (article, PhD thesis, book chapter, etc.)
  and automatically assigns a link category with that name. The next
  step would be a solution that automatically synchronizes your
  WordPress Links Manager with a reference manager.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="inserting-references">
  <title>Inserting references</title>
  <p>Once the references are in the Links Manager, we can use them in
  the articles we write. Unfortunately WordPress doesn’t provide an easy
  way to do that. I personally like the WordPress TinyMCE editor, so I
  made some changes to the wonderful
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611082245/http://wordpress.org/extend/plugins/link-to-post/">Link
  to Post</ext-link> plugin. The plugin provides a searchable interface
  to link to the posts, pages, categories and tags of your own WordPress
  blog. It took me half a day to add a link section, so now I can search
  for links and insert them into a post in a way not that different from
  how we use reference managers with Microsoft Word. The plugin also
  searches for co-authors, journal names and words in abstracts, as all
  this information is stored in the Link notes as BibTeX entry. I will
  make the updated Link to Post plugin available for download (I have
  contacted the plugin author), for the time being please contact me if
  you are interested.</p>
  <fig>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611082245im_/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/files/2010/12/link2post-500x377.jpg" xlink:title="Link to Post" />
  </fig>
</sec>
<sec id="providing-a-bibliography">
  <title>Providing a bibliography</title>
  <p>This is the last feature that I need for reference management with
  WordPress, and that should also be feasible to do. Ideally the
  bibliography should be created automatically from the links in the
  text, using the BibTeX info stored in the links database. In fact,
  this is something that a publisher could also do after manuscript
  submission, as the required information is all there. The bibliography
  should use the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611082245/http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2010/09/24/citation-style-language-an-interview-with-rintze-zelle-and-ian-mulvany/">Citation
  Style Language,</ext-link> and
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611082245/http://ocoins.info/">COinS</ext-link>
  (a standard for publishing machine-readable reference information in
  HTML), and should check for duplicate references, broken links,
  etc.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
