<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Word processor support in citation managers: Is there a
better way?</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2009-03-21">
<day>21</day>
<month>3</month>
<year>2009</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Citations of the relevant literature are an essential feature of
scientific papers. Reference Manager software helps adding these
citations and creating a bibliography. Are there differences in how
reference managers work together with your word processor of choice?</p>
<sec id="support-for-your-favorite-word-processor">
  <title>Support for your favorite word processor</title>
  <fig>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150906104449im_/http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3447/3371450153_62cbe77494.jpg" xlink:title="" />
  </fig>
  <p>Support for word processors other than Microsoft Word is spotty.
  The
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150906104449/http://www.mendeley.com/download_client">Mendeley
  plugin</ext-link> is only a few months old, and the latest Zotero
  release (1.5b)
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150906104449/http://www.zotero.org/support/word_processor_integration">broke
  the plugin for Word 2004</ext-link>. I expect the Word for Macintosh
  support of both these tools to become better over time. Google Docs
  doesn't have any reference manager integration. This greatly limits
  its usefulness for writing scientific papers. The RefWorks plugin
  connects to an online database, so you can't add or edit references
  without an internet connection.</p>
  <p>Most word processor plugins add an extra menu that allows to add
  and edit citations (allowing the user to search the reference manager
  database), and to add and edit bibliographies (allowing the user to
  pick a citation style, see below). Most reference managers also allow
  scanning for reference tags in documents produced by other word
  processors (e.g. in the .rtf format), but that process requires a few
  extra steps.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="support-for-your-favorite-journal">
  <title>Support for your favorite journal</title>
  <p>I think it is very unfortunate that paper authors have to deal with
  a large number of different citation styles. All that we really need
  for paper references is the DOI (e.g.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150906104449/http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/455708a">doi:10.1038/455708a</ext-link>)
  to make the reference automatically identifiable and some basic
  information (authors, title, journal, year, issue) to make the
  reference readable. But it is beyond my understanding why anybody
  would care about formatting details such as whether the pulication
  year appears before or after the journal name. There have been
  initiatives to standardize the formatting of references (e.g.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150906104449/http://www.nlm.nih.gov/citingmedicine/">Citing
  Medicine</ext-link>), but for now paper authors have to format their
  bibliographies in the style required by the journal. Citation styles
  are an important asset for those that write reference manager
  software. Many people will recall that Thomson Reuters (who makes
  Endnote)
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150906104449/http://www.nature.com/nature/journal/v455/n7214/full/455708a.html">sued</ext-link>
  George Mason University (who makes Zotero) last year, because Zotero
  added a feature that could convert Endnote .ens citation style files
  into
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150906104449/http://xbiblio.sourceforge.net/csl/">Citation
  Style Language</ext-link> .csl files. Mendeley is also using .csl for
  citation styles.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="is-there-a-better-way">
  <title>Is there a better way?</title>
  <p>Word processor plugins are fragile and usually break when a new
  software version is released (see for example
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150906104449/http://www.endnote.com/support/en_wpchart_mac.asp">this
  chart</ext-link> for Endnote and Word for Macintosh). Native word
  processor support for references allows a much tighter integration
  into the word processor interface. Lastly, documents produced by
  different reference managers are not interchangeable, as each plugin
  uses a slightly different formatting approach. This means you can't
  write on a paper using Endnote and send it to your coauthor who uses
  Zotero.</p>
  <p>The latest versions of Microsoft Word (2007 and 2008 Macintosh)
  have
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150906104449/http://blogs.msdn.com/joe_friend/archive/2006/07/13/664960.aspx">built-In
  support for citations and bibliographies</ext-link>, but this feature
  is severely limited for the requirements of academic papers. Only a
  handful of citation styles are supported, adding more styles is
  possible but requires
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150906104449/http://blogs.msdn.com/microsoft_office_word/archive/2007/12/14/bibliography-citations-1011.aspx">some
  serious skills in XML editing</ext-link>. References are stored in one
  flat file
  (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150906104449/https://www.uwec.edu/help/Word07/bib-srcfile.htm">Sources.xml</ext-link>)
  and can't be searched. OpenOffice is also struggling with built-in
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150906104449/http://bibliographic.openoffice.org/">bibliographic
  support</ext-link>.</p>
  <p>LaTex has long included support for references using
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150906104449/http://www.bibtex.org/About">BibTex</ext-link>
  and shows how citation support should be done. Tools like
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150906104449/http://jabref.sourceforge.net/">JabRef</ext-link>
  or
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150906104449/http://bibdesk.sourceforge.net/">BibDesk</ext-link>
  extend this functionality, and most reference managers will
  import/export bibtex files.</p>
  <p>Both Microsoft Word and OpenOffice should open up their citation
  APIs to third-party tools. This would create better citation tools,
  allows the easier exchange of documents between authors (journal
  submissions), and would it make easier for smaller tools such as
  Papers to integrate with word processors (a workaround is described
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150906104449/http://vnoel.wordpress.com/2008/02/14/papers-word-2008-bibliography-heaven/">here</ext-link>).
  If they wait too long, we will probably see the online word processors
  such as Google Docs, Zoho Writer start adding an API for citations and
  bibliographies and all of the sudden become very serious alternatives
  for writing scientific papers.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150906104449/http://network.nature.com/people/mfenner/blog/2009/02/27/lemon8-xml-interview-with-mj-suhonos">Lemon8-XML</ext-link>
  already has very good bibliography support.</p>
  <p><italic><italic>P.S. Bruce D'Arcus has recently come to similar
  conclusions
  (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150906104449/http://community.muohio.edu/blogs/darcusb/archives/2009/03/01/the-babel-of-citations">The
  Babel of Citations</ext-link>).</italic></italic></p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
