<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Writing a paper with Buzzword</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2007-12-20">
<day>20</day>
<month>12</month>
<year>2007</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611091413/http://www.buzzword.com/">Buzzword</ext-link>
is a free online word processor based on the Adobe Flash technology. I
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611091413/http://network.nature.com/blogs/user/mfenner/2007/09/27/more-on-online-writing-tools-buzzword-is-different">previously</ext-link>
wrote about Buzzword and how it could be used to write a scientific
paper. The first impressions were positive, so I decided to write my
next paper with Buzzword. This paper has been submitted this week. What
did I like and dislike about Buzzword?</p>
<sec id="good">
  <title>Good</title>
  <p>Most importantly, there is only one version of your manuscript. You
  and your coauthors can simultaneously work on different parts of the
  manuscript, the software saves all versions of the text. Buzzword is
  very pleasant to use, thanks to the elegant interface. Importing and
  exporting to Microsoft Word is possible. And Buzzword is free.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="bad">
  <title>Bad</title>
  <p>Buzzword doesn't handle references. You can create footnotes, but
  for referencing papers, you have to use another software. That's what
  I did in the final stages of manuscript writing, switching to
  Microsoft Word and Endnote. Buzzword doesn't show you the changes
  between different versions of a manuscript. This makes it difficult to
  see the changes that your coauthors made. Because Buzzword is an
  online word processor, you can't use it without an internet
  connection. One of my coauthors had Buzzword crashing several times,
  probably because of a slow internet connection.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="conclusions">
  <title>Conclusions</title>
  <p>Manuscript writing with Buzzword is fun. But without support for
  references and better version management, it is not ready for prime
  time.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
