<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>eXtyles: Interview with Elizabeth Blake and Bruce
Rosenblum</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2009-05-01">
<day>1</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2009</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Scientific papers are submitted to a journal as word processor files,
usually in Microsoft Word format. After the paper is accepted for
publication, the journal takes the manuscript and translates the text
into a format that is better suited for publication online and/or in
print. XML and the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002164418/http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/">NLM
DTD</ext-link> – a set of XML schema modules – have evolved as the
standard data format for this purpose. Files in the NLM DTD format can
in turn be translated into HTML and/or PDF for publication. The NLM DTD
format is also used to transfer journal articles from publishers to
archives (e.g.
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002164418/http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/">PubMed
Central</ext-link>) and for long-term archiving.</p>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002164418/http://www.inera.com/extylesinfo.shtml">eXtyles</ext-link>
is a tool that facilitate the translation between these different
document formats, and in the process also help to clean up broken
references and other errors in the manscript. As paper authors usually
don’t see much of what happens to their manuscript after submission, I
thought I’d ask Elizabeth Blake and Bruce Rosenblum from
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002164418/http://www.inera.com/">Inera</ext-link>
(the company behind eXtyles) a few questions.</p>
<sec id="1-can-you-describe-what-extyles-is-and-does">
  <title>1. Can you describe what eXtyles is and does?</title>
  <p>Elizabeth Blake:
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002164418/http://www.inera.com/">Inera</ext-link>
  offers several
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002164418/http://www.inera.com/extylesinfo.shtml">eXtyles
  products</ext-link>, all of which are designed to clean up, structure,
  validate, and export scholarly content. The desktop version of eXtyles
  is the most widely used product; it’s a plug-in to Microsoft Word that
  is customized according to the editorial style and production
  requirements of each publisher that uses it. eXtyles:</p>
  <list list-type="bullet">
    <list-item>
      <p>collects and exports manuscript metadata</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>cleans up extraneous or incorrect document formatting</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>applies structure to the document on the paragraph and
      character level (using author- and editor-friendly Word styles
      rather than visually intrusive tags)</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>automatically enforces certain editorial style requirements
      through large-scale, context-sensitive find and replace</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>parses, restructures, links, and corrects bibliographic
      references using internal templates and databases as well as
      external sources such as
      <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002164418/http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sites/entrez">PubMed</ext-link>
      and
      <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002164418/http://www.crossref.org/">CrossRef</ext-link></p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>links citations and callouts to their respective references and
      objects</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>exports high-quality XML from Word according to the
      <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002164418/http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/">NLM
      DTD</ext-link> or any other DTD required by the publisher</p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
  <p>eXtyles is a uniquely flexible tool in that it can accommodate any
  editorial style and the wide variety of workflows used by different
  publishers, and it can also process any Word-readable,
  author-submitted manuscript.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="2-what-is-the-difference-between-extyles-and-the-microsoft-word-article-authoring-add-in">
  <title>2. What is the difference between eXtyles and the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002164418/http://www.microsoft.com/mscorp/tc/scholarly_communication.mspx#Tools">Microsoft
  Word Article Authoring Add-in</ext-link> ?</title>
  <p><italic><italic>Bruce Rosenblum:</italic></italic> eXtyles makes
  two assumptions. First, eXtyles does not rely on the author to
  complete document structuring tasks – in our experience, journals have
  not succeeded in having authors provide sufficiently accurate styling
  or markup in Word files (the application used by most scholarly
  authors) to allow for automatic creation of high-quality XML. Second,
  eXtyles assumes that authors make other kinds of mistakes, whether
  adding inappropriate formatting, using unsupported fonts for special
  characters, or making informational errors in reference lists, and all
  of these problems must be corrected as part of the publishing
  process.</p>
  <p>eXtyles is designed to overcome the limitations of how authors
  commonly prepare manuscripts by providing the tools that publishers
  need to clean up, rapidly edit, and then convert manuscripts to XML.
  eXtyles has been carefully developed over ten years to accurately
  address the reality of what publishers see in author submissions.</p>
  <p>By contrast, the Microsoft Word Article Authoring Add-in has been
  developed as a content creation tool. It is designed for authors to
  structure articles in Word 2007 as they write. In this model, authors
  must add structural information rather than just submit the text of
  their article. The Add-in assumes authors will create reference lists
  with the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002164418/http://office.microsoft.com/en-us/word/HA100674921033.aspx">Word
  2007 citation manager</ext-link> and will adhere to all requirements
  necessary to successfully save the manuscript to NLM DTD XML when they
  have completed writing their article. Also, the Microsoft Add-in does
  not provide tools to prepare an article for XML conversion if the
  Add-in was not used during creation of the article, which is a key
  feature of eXtyles.</p>
  <p>Fundamentally the target audience differs: the Microsoft Add-in
  assumes use by authors, whereas eXtyles provides tools to publishing
  personnel that allow authors to concentrate on great scientific
  research rather than the technical aspects of article publication.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="3-what-are-the-most-common-problems-in-submitted-manuscripts-that-can-be-fixed-by-extyles-are-there-problems-that-have-to-be-fixed-manually">
  <title>3. What are the most common problems in submitted manuscripts
  that can be fixed by eXtyles? Are there problems that have to be fixed
  manually?</title>
  <p><italic><italic>Elizabeth Blake:</italic></italic> The most common
  problems range from relatively simple issues such as extraneous
  formatting or misapplied styles to more complex issues such as missing
  data or incorrect or uncited references. Hovering in between these are
  violations of editorial style – for example, British versus American
  spelling or non-standard abbreviations for units of measure – which
  eXtyles can also correct.</p>
  <p>Some problems do have to be fixed manually. eXtyles does not take
  the place of an editor; rather, it automates as much of the low-level
  copy editing as can be reliably automated while drawing the editor’s
  attention to issues that require follow up. An example would be
  eXtyles flagging a callout to a table that is missing from the
  manuscript; this obviously requires human intervention, but the
  warning saves time and flags problems early in the workflow when they
  are easier to resolve.</p>
  <p>On a larger scale, the problem eXtyles is designed to solve is
  getting the accepted author manuscript published as quickly and
  accurately as possible. The fully eXtyled file can be flowed into a
  typesetting system such as InDesign with the paragraph styles aligned
  to the composition template, saving a lot of labor during the
  typesetting stage, or the Word file can be converted directly to NLM
  XML with the push of a button, allowing users to create rich, valid
  XML without any XML knowledge or expertise.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="4-extyles-helps-with-editorial-tasks-such-as-document-cleanup-and-citation-checking-why-shouldn-t-these-tasks-be-left-to-the-authors-and-checked-when-a-manuscript-is-submitted">
  <title>4. eXtyles helps with editorial tasks such as document cleanup
  and citation checking. Why shouldn’t these tasks be left to the
  authors and checked when a manuscript is submitted?</title>
  <p><italic><italic>Elizabeth Blake:</italic></italic> Theoretically
  these tasks are the authors’ responsibility! In practice it is an
  extremely rare manuscript that doesn’t have errors, particularly
  reference errors. Our goal is not to discourage authors from
  submitting clean and accurate manuscripts; our goal is to facilitate
  the process when that doesn’t happen, which is most of the time. The
  eXtyles reference-processing tools, in particular the tools that link
  and correct references with data retrieved from PubMed and CrossRef,
  go a step beyond what even a very thorough copy editor is typically
  able to flush out given the time constraints of a deadline-driven
  workflow.</p>
  <p>As for performing these tasks at submission, the eXtyles
  integration with
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002164418/http://www.editorialmanager.com/homepage/home.htm">Editorial
  Manager</ext-link> does just that, providing an informative reference
  quality check early in the workflow so that responsibility for fixing
  the references can, if the publisher prefers, be pushed back on the
  authors.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="5-if-extyles-validates-and-corrects-references-why-do-most-journals-insist-on-bibliographies-formatted-in-a-specific-house-style">
  <title>5. If eXtyles validates and corrects references, why do most
  journals insist on bibliographies formatted in a specific house
  style?</title>
  <p><italic><italic>Elizabeth Blake:</italic></italic> There are two
  ways in which eXtyles corrects references: one is by correcting the
  data (e.g., PubMed reports that the first author in reference 2 is
  incorrect) and the other is by correcting the format according to the
  publisher’s house style. Ensuring correct data in a reference, which
  eXtyles does with
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002164418/http://www.inera.com/refcorrection.shtml">Automatic
  Reference Correction</ext-link>, is part of ensuring accuracy in the
  scientific record. As for the varieties of reference styles, many
  developed as necessary elements of print publication – for instance,
  some abbreviated house styles were devised as paper-saving measures.
  So long as print is not dead, these concerns are still relevant.
  However, in an electronic world, formatting of references may be less
  important, though a good editor will always have an argument for why
  their style is preferable (I say that as a former editor). We at Inera
  remain neutral on the topic since eXtyles can reformat references
  according to any preferred editorial style if a publisher requires
  it.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="6-what-is-the-nlm-dtd-what-was-your-part-in-developing-it">
  <title>6. What is the NLM DTD? What was your part in developing
  it?</title>
  <p>Bruce Rosenblum: The
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002164418/http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/">NLM
  DTD</ext-link> is a family of tag sets designed for full-text XML
  markup of scholarly articles. The intent of the NLM DTD Suite is to
  mark up and preserve the intellectual content of journals independent
  of the form in which the content is delivered.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002164418/http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/faq.html">The
  suite can be used to publish and archive journal content, and to
  facilitate content interchange between organizations</ext-link>. And
  despite the NLM moniker, the suite was designed from day-one for
  full-text markup of journal content in any discipline.</p>
  <p>Our work on the NLM DTD started in 2001 when the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002164418/http://lib.harvard.edu/">Harvard
  University Library</ext-link>, under a
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002164418/http://www.mellon.org/">Mellon
  Foundation</ext-link> grant, was asked to study formats for long-term
  archiving of eJournal content. Harvard decided that PDF was not a
  viable archive format, and discovered that every publisher had a
  proprietary DTD. Harvard then approached Inera, because of our
  experience working with many DTDs including
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002164418/http://download.www.techstreet.com/cgi-bin/pdf/free/228869/12083-a.pdf">ISO
  12083</ext-link>, to study the feasibility of developing a single DTD
  into which the content from all publishers could be converted for the
  purposes of long-term archiving. The
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002164418/http://www.diglib.org/preserve/hadtdfs.pdf">e-Journal
  Archjive DTD Feasibility Study</ext-link> we wrote describes the
  requirements for such a DTD.</p>
  <p>At the same time, NLM was making major revisions to the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002164418/http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/">PubMed
  Central</ext-link> 1.0 DTD. NLM, Harvard, and Mellon decided to
  combine resources on a single project co-developed by NLM,
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002164418/http://www.mulberrytech.com/">Mulberry
  Technologies</ext-link>, and Inera. Version 1.0 of the NLM DTD was
  released in April 2003. The scope of use was originally focused on the
  needs of PubMed Central, and a long-term archive (now
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002164418/http://www.portico.org/">Portico</ext-link>)
  seed-funded by the Mellon Foundation.</p>
  <p>The NLM DTD was quickly adopted by others when they discovered the
  coverage and flexibility. And as publishers switched from SGML to XML,
  they found that adopting an off-the-shelf public DTD was far less
  expensive than converting their existing SGML DTDs to XML. As use has
  expanded, support has grown so that many off-the-shelf solutions are
  now available for working with the DTD. Inera continues to serve on
  the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002164418/http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/working-group.html">NLM
  DTD Advisory Board</ext-link>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="7-how-does-extyles-use-the-nlm-dtd">
  <title>7. How does eXtyles use the NLM DTD?</title>
  <p><italic><italic>Bruce Rosenblum:</italic></italic> eXtyles users,
  with no knowledge of XML, can create high-quality XML according to the
  NLM DTD as a simple one-button action after using eXtyles to easily
  complete editorial preparation of a manuscript. In other words,
  eXtyles XML creation is a natural by-product of normal manuscript
  preparation for publication, and it requires no specialized user
  knowledge.</p>
  <p>Because eXtyles was developed as an open platform that can be
  customized to the editorial and production needs of any publisher, it
  is internally DTD agnostic. In this regard, eXtyles can be used to
  convert content to any of the DTDs in the NLM DTD Suite
  (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002164418/http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/">Journal
  Publishing</ext-link>,
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002164418/http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/">Archive
  and Interchange</ext-link>, or
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002164418/http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/book/">Book</ext-link>).</p>
  <p>Furthermore, the NLM DTD suite actually allows for a wide range of
  interpretation, and eXtyles can easily meet any of those
  interpretations. For example, the NLM DTD supports two table models,
  XHTML and
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20151002164418/http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/options/OASIS/tag-library/19990315/n-xe20.html">CALS</ext-link>.
  eXtyles can produce content in either table model, depending on the
  workflow requirements of the publisher. A wide range of other
  configuration options are available to meet the needs of specific
  publisher requirements.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="8-can-the-nlm-dtd-also-used-by-authors-to-submit-their-papers-to-journals-or-repositories-if-not-what-are-the-limitations">
  <title>8. Can the NLM DTD also used by authors to submit their papers
  to journals or repositories? If not, what are the limitations?</title>
  <p><italic><italic>Bruce Rosenblum:</italic></italic> In theory
  authors could submit their papers to journals or repositories in XML.
  However, in practice this has not occurred and we do not consider it
  likely to occur in the near future. There are a few key obstacles.</p>
  <p>First, the primary job of researchers is to conduct research and
  report the results. Because technical knowledge of publishing formats
  is not a required part of the typical researcher’s job, the majority
  of researchers do not submit papers to journals or repositories in XML
  when they can much more easily do so in PDF or Word.</p>
  <p>By extension of this point, most publishers are interested in
  high-quality research. One publisher told us, “If a manuscript with
  great science is submitted on birch bark, we’ll find a way to publish
  it.” We believe that in a world where journals compete for the best
  papers, publishers will continue to put research quality ahead of
  submission formats.</p>
  <p>Second, creation of high-quality XML is just not that simple. Even
  with the tools that have been developed in the past ten years,
  publishers with experienced editorial and production teams still have
  problems producing consistently high-quality XML; if you doubt this
  point, please look at a typical first round PubMed Central publisher
  validation report. If publishers with experienced production teams do
  not find this easy, then we believe that production of consistently
  high-quality XML by authors is not likely to occur in the next few
  years.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="10-what-are-your-responsibilities-at-inera">
  <title>10. What are your responsibilities at Inera?</title>
  <p><italic><italic>Bruce Rosenblum:</italic></italic> As CEO, I am
  involved in all aspects of Inera. My background is originally in
  software development, and I use this expertise to guide the
  development and quality assurance of eXtyles. I am also responsible
  for managing the business side of Inera. But probably my most
  important role is coordinating the incredibly creative team of people
  who work on eXtyles.</p>
  <p><italic><italic>Elizabeth Blake:</italic></italic> My role is
  primarily customer facing, from marketing to configuration and
  training up through support. My goal is to ensure that potential
  customers get all the information they need about eXtyles to make the
  right decision and to ensure that, once they become customers, they
  continue to be happy with that decision. We rely heavily on customer
  feedback when planning enhancements to eXtyles, and I tend to focus on
  the user experience when we work through the details of any new
  project.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="11-what-did-you-do-before-starting-to-work-on-extyles">
  <title>11. What did you do before starting to work on eXtyles?</title>
  <p><italic><italic>Bruce Rosenblum:</italic></italic> Before eXtyles,
  Inera spent years providing SGML and XML consulting and software
  development services to publishers. Prior to that, I spent 15 years
  developing commercial software products for companies like Microsoft,
  Word Perfect, Houghton Mifflin, and Broderbund. Going way back, I’ve
  always had an interest in problems of working with text – my first
  professional software project was building a word processor for
  Chinese on an Apple II in 1980.</p>
  <p><italic><italic>Elizabeth Blake:</italic></italic> I started in
  scholarly publishing as a copy editor for the Cell Press journal
  <italic><italic>Neuron</italic></italic> and then worked as the
  managing editor of <italic><italic>Neuron</italic></italic> for
  several years before moving to <italic><italic>The New England Journal
  of Medicine</italic></italic>. At Inera, my years of real-world
  editorial and production experience have been very valuable and help
  to ensure that eXtyles development is centered on solving the problems
  that publishers face every day.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
