<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Yet another look at blogging networks</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2010-07-26">
<day>26</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2010</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>The last few days we have seen a number of blog posts reflecting on
the pros and cons of science blogging networks. Bora Zivkovic last week
announced his departure from scienceblogs.com, and in his must-read post
reflected on the history of science blogging
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611102940/http://scienceblogs.com/clock/2010/07/scienceblogs_and_me_and_the_ch.php">A
Farewell to Scienceblogs: the Changing Science Blogging
Ecosystem</ext-link>). Richard Grant on Saturday wrote down his thoughts
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611102940/http://blogs.nature.com/rpg/2010/07/24/on-nature-network">On
Nature Network</ext-link>. Cameron Neylon draws an interesting parallel
between science networks and scientific journals
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611102940/http://cameronneylon.net/blog/the-nature-of-science-blog-networks/">The
Nature of Science Blog Networks</ext-link>). And Katherine Haxton
compared her experience blogging on Nature Network vs. blogging on her
own blog
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611102940/http://www.possibilitiesendless.com/?p=270">Science
Blogging Networks</ext-link>).</p>
<p>My thoughts on this: it's complicated. I don't see how blogging
networks (or any particular network) can be inherently better or worse
than setting up your own blog. It's an individual decision. Right now I
like to write as part of a blogging network. But I may change my mind
and write for a different network, or on an individually hosted blog. I
would like to add three considerations to the discussion.</p>
<sec id="consider-institutional-blogs">
  <title>Consider institutional blogs</title>
  <p>We shouldn't forget that there is also a third alternative to
  blogging networks and individually hosted blogs: a blog hosted by your
  institution. An institutional blog has a different set of advantages
  and disadvantages and is therefore not the right choice for everybody.
  But I will soon start an official blog for the cancer center of my
  medical school (I've gotten the green light from administration and
  the PR department, the WordPress 3.0 test system is set up, but it
  probably will be a few weeks before the first post). I have no
  intentions stopping the Gobbledygook blog – the new blog will have a
  different focus, and it will be in German.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611102940/http://network.nature.com/profile/rpg">Richard</ext-link>
  have written institutional blogs for years, but this will be new for
  me – and will also be the first official blog at our university.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="we-need-a-better-aggregator-for-science-blogs">
  <title>We need a better aggregator for science blogs</title>
  <p>Most of us probably have subscribed to a good number of science
  blogs with an RSS reader. The best way to find interesting new posts
  is probably through links in blogs we read regularly. In addition, we
  stumble upon interesting posts via links in blog networks, blog rolls,
  <italic><italic>Twitter</italic></italic>,
  <italic><italic>FriendFeed</italic></italic>, or shared items in
  <italic><italic>Google Reader</italic></italic>.</p>
  <p>In addition, we also need a good aggregator of science blogs. I
  have to admit that I have stopped using
  <italic><italic>Technorati</italic></italic> a while ago.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611102940/http://blogs.nature.com/">Nature.com
  Blogs</ext-link> was a good start, and
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611102940/http://www.researchblogging.org/">ResearchBlogging</ext-link>
  does a good job of covering blog posts about peer-reviewed literature.
  But we probably can do much better. Whether the best strategy would be
  to put more resources into one of the existing services (see also
  Lou's
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611102940/http://blogs.nature.com/rpg/2010/07/24/on-nature-network#comment-61864">comment</ext-link>
  from earlier today), or whether to start building something new, I
  don't know. But there is a lot of potential for building a better
  discovery service that at the same time will become an interesting
  archive of what the science blogosphere is talking about.
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611102940/http://blogs.nature.com/mfenner/2009/08/20/streamosphere-interview-with-euan-adie">Streamosphere</ext-link>
  is already a good step in the right direction.</p>
  <fig>
    <caption><p>Flickr Photo by Eva Amsen. Taken during Science Online
    London 2009 at the Royal Institution.</p></caption>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611102940im_/http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3538/3849275338_d77a382643.jpg" xlink:title="" />
  </fig>
</sec>
<sec id="personal-interactions-are-important">
  <title>Personal interactions are important</title>
  <p>It is usually much more rewarding to interact with someone online
  whom you have also met in person. This is true not only for scientific
  collaborations, but of course also for social media. This is obviously
  much easier if you live in places like London, but even Hannover
  (where I live) has a really nice
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611102940/http://blogs.nature.com/mfenner/2010/05/11/action-points">Science
  2.0 community</ext-link>. And this is why science blogging conferences
  such as
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611102940/http://www.scienceonline2010.com/index.php/wiki/">ScienceOnline2010</ext-link>
  or
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120611102940/http://www.scienceonlinelondon.org/">Science
  Online London 2010</ext-link> are so important. Science Online London
  is only six weeks away (September 3-4 at the British Library), and I'm
  really excited not only about the program, but also because of all the
  people I will for the first time or again meet in person.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
