<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<title-group>
<article-title>Zotero: Interview with Trevor Owens</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>Martin Fenner</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2009-03-04">
<day>4</day>
<month>3</month>
<year>2009</year>
</pub-date>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150906100323/http://www.zotero.org/">Zotero</ext-link>
is a reference manager built as an extension of the
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150906100323/http://www.mozilla-europe.org/en/firefox/">Firefox</ext-link>
web browser. The best introduction to Zotero is probably this short
video.</p>
<p>Last week the newest version (1.5 beta)
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150906100323/http://www.zotero.org/blog/zotero-15-beta-released-join-us-in-the-clouds/">was
announced</ext-link> on the Zotero blog. Among the most exciting new
features is the synchronization of library data with the Zotero server,
which in the future will allow a lot of interesting social features. I
asked <italic><italic>Trevor Owens</italic></italic> from Zotero a few
questions about Zotero, particularly some of the new features.</p>
<sec id="1-can-you-describe-what-zotero-is-and-does">
  <title>1. Can you describe what Zotero is and does?</title>
  <p>Zotero is an easy-to-use yet powerful research tool that helps you
  gather, organize, and analyze sources (citations, full texts, web
  pages, images, and other objects), and lets you share the results of
  your research in a variety of ways. An extension to the popular
  open-source web browser Firefox, Zotero includes the best parts of
  older reference manager software — the ability to store author, title,
  and publication fields and to export that information as formatted
  references — and the best parts of modern software and web
  applications (like iTunes and
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150906100323/http://www.delicious.com/">del.icio.us</ext-link>),
  such as the ability to interact, tag, and search in advanced ways.
  Zotero integrates tightly with online resources; it can sense when
  users are viewing a book, article, or other object on the web, and on
  most major research and library sites it will find and automatically
  save the full reference information for the item. Since it lives in
  the web browser, it can effortlessly transmit information to, and
  receive information from, other web services and applications; since
  it runs on one's personal computer, it can also communicate with
  software running there (such as Microsoft Word). And it can be used
  offline as well (e.g., on a plane, in an archive without WiFi).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="2-why-is-zotero-a-firefox-plugin-and-not-a-desktop-application">
  <title>2. Why is Zotero a Firefox plugin and not a desktop
  application?</title>
  <p>For most researchers the web is the first and primary point of
  entry for their research process. We thought it would be ideal to
  integrate Zotero as tightly as possible with the interface researchers
  already use to interact with the the journals, libraries, and
  databases they regularly consult.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="3-why-is-zotero-a-firefox-plugin-and-not-a-web-based-application">
  <title>3. Why is Zotero a Firefox plugin and not a web-based
  application?</title>
  <p>Two reasons, first as a extension Zotero can sit alongside any page
  a researcher visits. Many of our users will keep Zotero partway open
  as they work on research online, allowing them to organize and
  annotate their research without leaving the page they are on. Second,
  as an extension users have full access to their collections when they
  are offline. This is particularly important for researchers working in
  remote locations or with flakey connections. For example, researchers
  working in offline archives can manually add items and attach scans
  and photos. If you're writing a paper on a plane you can add citations
  to your documents. In short being inside the browser gives us the best
  of both worlds. Zotero offers direct connectivity to web content,
  while still always remaining accessible. The last thing I would note
  is that Zotero is rapidly becoming a web application. With our newest
  release users can browse and share their collections online and in the
  near future users will be able to further manipulate their collections
  through our web application.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="4-did-you-consider-google-gears-for-offline-access">
  <title>4. Did you consider Google Gears for offline access?</title>
  <p>Both
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150906100323/http://gears.google.com/">Google
  Gears</ext-link> and Zotero rely on a local instance of
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150906100323/http://www.sqlite.org/about.html">sqlite</ext-link>
  for data storage, but Zotero predates Gears by over a year. Google
  Gears is intended more to synchronize a web application for offline
  use, while Zotero fundamentally is a research database that users
  expect to be able to interact with fully regardless of their network
  connectivity.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="5-does-zotero-work-with-google-docs">
  <title>5. Does Zotero work with Google Docs?</title>
  <p>Yes, users can drag and drop citations and bibliographic entries
  into google documents, or for that matter any sort of text field. We
  have a
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150906100323/http://www.zotero.org/support/zotero_and_google_tools">short
  screencast</ext-link> which demos this functionality.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="6-can-you-briefly-describe-the-citation-style-language-csl-">
  <title>6. Can you briefly describe the Citation Style Language
  (CSL)?</title>
  <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150906100323/http://www.zotero.org/support/dev/creating_citation_styles">CSL</ext-link>
  is an XML language for citation formatting. It is designed to provide
  a nice balance between power and ease-of-use. It is also designed to
  be independent of any particular application, document format, or
  programming language.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="7-how-can-zotero-users-share-their-references-with-others">
  <title>7. How can Zotero users share their references with
  others?</title>
  <p>At the moment users can export collections and libraries and email
  them to associates. Users can also share their library online, and by
  next week users will be able to import references directly from any
  users shared library. By next month users will be able to create
  groups for more seamless sharing of references and attachments.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="8-for-zotero-2-0-you-plan-to-offer-users-the-ability-to-share-collections-with-others-through-the-zotero-server-is-there-a-difference-to-similar-services-e-g-connotea-citeulike-or-mendeley-and-do-you-plan-integration-with-them">
  <title>8. For Zotero 2.0 you plan to offer users the ability to share
  collections with others through the Zotero Server. Is there a
  difference to similar services (e.g. Connotea, CiteULike or Mendeley)
  and do you plan integration with them?</title>
  <p>In many ways the collaborative features currently in the works for
  Zotero are similar to the other services you mention. I think the
  biggest difference is the way in which sharing collections through
  groups will be tightly coupled into the Zotero client, and writing
  applications through our Word and Open Office plugins. The social and
  collaborative features we are launching directly connect into our
  hundreds of thousands of users' existing workflows. Zotero is also a
  non-commercial, open-source project directed by academics who are
  committed to enabling scholarship. Finally, Zotero is oriented toward
  storing anything related to your research (papers, books, audio,
  video, datasets, images, etc) while other solutions are almost
  entirely oriented toward working with research papers.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="9-what-are-your-responsibilities-within-the-zotero-project">
  <title>9. What are your responsibilities within the Zotero
  project?</title>
  <p>Over the last two years as the community lead and evangelist I have
  been responsible for spreading the word about Zotero through workshops
  and presentations at conferences and institutions, as well as helping
  support the ever growing community of users, evangelists, and
  developers through Zotero's forums and by writing a majority of
  Zotero's user documentation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="10-what-did-you-do-before-starting-to-work-on-zotero">
  <title>10. What did you do before starting to work on Zotero?</title>
  <p>Before working on Zotero I worked as the press coordinator for the
  Games Learning and Society Conference in Madison and as a Academic
  Advisor at the University of Wisconsin. My undergraduate degree is in
  the History of Science.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="11-do-you-want-to-talk-about-future-plans-for-zotero">
  <title>11. Do you want to talk about future plans for Zotero?</title>
  <p>You can consult our development roadmap online
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150906100323/http://www.zotero.org/support/development_roadmap">here</ext-link>.
  Beyond that I would recommend taking a look at the work we are doing
  with the internet archive
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150906100323/http://www.dancohen.org/2007/12/12/zotero-and-the-internet-archive-join-forces/">here</ext-link>.
  Once you take a look at those I would be happy to
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150906100323/http://www.zotero.org/support/contact_us">answer
  any questions</ext-link> that come up.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
